<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>MUSAEUS: A MONODY TO THE MEMORY of Mr. POPE. In Imitation of MILTON'S Lycidas.</title>
    <author>William Mason</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">19</measure>
    <measure unit="line">283</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>William Mason_musaeus-a-monody-to-the-memory</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>MUSAEUS: A MONODY TO THE MEMORY of Mr. POPE. In Imitation of MILTON'S Lycidas.</title>
     <author>William Mason</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>MUSAEUS: A MONODY TO THE MEMORY of Mr. POPE. In Imitation of MILTON'S Lycidas.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">SOrrowing I catch the reed, and call the Muse;</l>
     <l n="2">If yet a Muse on Britain's plain abide,</l>
     <l n="3">Since rapt MUSAEUS tun'd his parting strain:</l>
     <l n="4">With him they liv'd, with him perchance they dy'd.</l>
     <l n="5">For who e'er since their virgin train espy'd,</l>
     <l n="6">Or on the banks of Thames, or that mild plain,</l>
     <l n="7">Where Isis sparkles to the sunny ray?</l>
     <l n="8">Or have they deign'd to play,</l>
     <l n="9">Where Camus winds along his broider'd vale,</l>
     <l n="10">Feeding each white pink, and each daisie pied,</l>
     <l n="11">That mingling paint his rushy-fringed side?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="12">Yet ah! celestial maids, ye are not dead;</l>
     <l n="13">Immortal as ye are, ye may not die:</l>
     <l n="14">And well I ween, ye cannot quite be fled,</l>
     <l n="15">Ere ye entune his mournful elegy.</l>
     <l n="16">Stay then awhile, O stay, ye fleeting fair;</l>
     <l n="17">Revisit yet, nor hallow'd Hippocrene,</l>
     <l n="18">Nor Thespia's shade; till your harmonious teen</l>
     <l n="19">Be grateful pour'd on some slow-ditted air,</l>
     <l n="20">Such tribute paid, again ye may repair</l>
     <l n="21">To what lov'd haunt you whilom did erect;</l>
     <l n="22">Whether Lycaeus, or that mountain fair</l>
     <l n="23">Trim Maenelaus, with piny verdure deck'd.</l>
     <l n="24">But now it boots you not in these to stray,</l>
     <l n="25">Or yet Cyllene's hoary shade to chuse,</l>
     <l n="26">Or where mild Ladon's swelling waters play.</l>
     <l n="27">Forego each vain excuse,</l>
     <l n="28">And haste to Thames's shores; for Thames shall join</l>
     <l n="29">Our sad society, and passing mourn,</l>
     <l n="30">Letting cold tears bedew his silver urn.</l>
     <l n="31">And, when the poet's wither'd grot he laves,</l>
     <l n="32">His reed-crown'd locks shall shake, his head shall bow,</l>
     <l n="33">His tide no more in eddies blithe shall rove,</l>
     <l n="34">But creep soft by with long-drawn murmurs slow.</l>
     <l n="35">For oft the poet rous'd his charmed waves</l>
     <l n="36">With martial notes, or lull'd with strains of love.</l>
     <l n="37">He must not now in brisk meanders flow</l>
     <l n="38">Gamesome, and kiss the sadly-silent shore,</l>
     <l n="39">Without the loan of some poetick woe.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="40">Can I forget, how erst his osiers made</l>
     <l n="41">Sad sullen musick, as bleak Eurus fann'd?</l>
     <l n="42">Can I forget, how gloom'd yon laureat shade,</l>
     <l n="43">Ere death remorseless wav'd his ebon wand?</l>
     <l n="44">How, midst yon grot, each silver-trickling spring</l>
     <l n="45">Wander'd the shelly channels all among;</l>
     <l n="46">While as the coral roof did softly ring</l>
     <l n="47">Reponsive to their sweetly-doleful song?</l>
     <l n="48">Meanwhile all pale th' expiring poet laid,</l>
     <l n="49">And sunk his aweful head,</l>
     <l n="50">While vocal shadows pleasing dreams prolong:</l>
     <l n="51">For so, his sick'ning spirits to release,</l>
     <l n="52">They pour'd the balm of visionary peace.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="53">First, sent from Cam's fair banks, like Palmer old,</l>
     <l n="54">Came TITYRUS slow, with head all silver'd o'er,</l>
     <l n="55">And in his hand an oaken crook he bore,</l>
     <l n="56">And thus in antique guise short talk did hold.</l>
     <l n="57">"Grete clerk of Fame' is house, whose excellence</l>
     <l n="58">"Maie wele befitt thilk place of eminence,</l>
     <l n="59">"Mickle of wele betide thy houres last,</l>
     <l n="60">"For mich gode wirkè to me don and past.</l>
     <l n="61">"For syn the daies whereas my lyre ben strongen,</l>
     <l n="62">"And deftly many a mery laie I songen,</l>
     <l n="63">"Old Time, which alle things don maliciously,</l>
     <l n="64">"Gnawen with rusty tooth continually,</l>
     <l n="65">"Gnattrid my lines, that they all cancrid ben,</l>
     <l n="66">"Till at the last thou smoothen 'hem hast again;</l>
     <l n="67">"Sithence full semely gliden my rhymes rude,</l>
     <l n="68">"As, (if fitteth thilk similitude)</l>
     <l n="69">"Whannè shallow brooke yrenneth hobling on,</l>
     <l n="70">"Ovir rough stones it maken full rough song:</l>
     <l n="71">"But, them stones removen, this lite rivere</l>
     <l n="72">"Stealen forth by, making pleasant murmere:</l>
     <l n="73">"So my sely rhymes, whoso may them note,</l>
     <l n="74">"Thou maken everichone to ren right sote;</l>
     <l n="75">"And in my verse entuneth so fetisely,</l>
     <l n="76">"That men sayen I make trewe melody,</l>
     <l n="77">"And speaken every dele to myne honoure,</l>
     <l n="78">"Mich wele, grete clerk, betide thy parting houre! "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5" stanza_type="sestet">
     <l n="79">He ceas'd his homely rhyme.</l>
     <l n="80">When COLIN CLOUT, Eliza's shepherd swain,</l>
     <l n="81">The blithest lad that ever pip'd on plain,</l>
     <l n="82">Came with his reed soft-warbling on the way,</l>
     <l n="83">And thrice he bow'd his head with motion mild,</l>
     <l n="84">And thus his gliding numbers 'gan essay.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6" stanza_type="sestet">
     <l n="85">"Ah! luckless swain, alas! how art thou lorn,</l>
     <l n="86">"Who once like me could'st frame thy pipe to play</l>
     <l n="87">"Shepherds devise, and chear the ling'ring morn:</l>
     <l n="88">"Ne bush, ne breere, but learnt thy roundelay.</l>
     <l n="89">"Ah plight too sore such worth to equal right!</l>
     <l n="90">"Ah worth too high to meet such piteous plight!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7" stanza_type="sestet">
     <l n="91">"But I nought strive, poor Colin, to compare</l>
     <l n="92">"My Hobbin's, or my Thenot's rustick skill</l>
     <l n="93">"To thy deft Swains, whose dapper ditties rare</l>
     <l n="94">"Surpass ought else of quaintest shepherd's quill.</l>
     <l n="95">"Ev'n Roman Tityrus, that peerless wight,</l>
     <l n="96">"Mote yield to thee for dainties of delight.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8" stanza_type="nine-line">
     <l n="97">"Eke when in Fable's flow'ry path you stray'd,</l>
     <l n="98">"Masking in cunning feints Truth's splendent face;</l>
     <l n="99">"Ne Sylph, ne Sylphid, but due tendence paid,</l>
     <l n="100">"To shield Belinda's lock from felon base,</l>
     <l n="101">"But all mote nought avail such harm to chase,</l>
     <l n="102">"Than Una fair 'gan droop her princely mein,</l>
     <l n="103">"Eke Florimel, and all my Faery race:</l>
     <l n="104">"Belinda far surpast by beauties sheen,</l>
     <l n="105">"Belinda, subject meet for such soft lay I ween.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9" stanza_type="nine-line">
     <l n="106">"Like as in villag'd troop of birdlings trim,</l>
     <l n="107">"Where Chanticleer his red crest high doth hold,</l>
     <l n="108">"And quaking Ducks, that wont in lake to swim,</l>
     <l n="109">"And Turkeys proud, and Pigeons nothing bold;</l>
     <l n="110">"If chance the Peacock doth his plumes unfold</l>
     <l n="111">"Eftsoons their meaner beauties all decaying,</l>
     <l n="112">"He glist'neth purple, and he glist'neth gold,</l>
     <l n="113">"Now with bright green, now blue himself arraying.</l>
     <l n="114">"Such is thy beauty bright, all other beauties swaying.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10" stanza_type="nine-line">
     <l n="115">"But why do I descant this toyish rhyme,</l>
     <l n="116">"And fancies light in simple guise pourtray?</l>
     <l n="117">"Listing to chear thee at this rueful time,</l>
     <l n="118">"While as black Death doth on thy heartstrings prey.</l>
     <l n="119">"Yet rede aright, and if this friendly lay</l>
     <l n="120">"Thou nathless judgest all too slight and vain,</l>
     <l n="121">"Let my well-meaning mend my ill essay:</l>
     <l n="122">"So may I greet thee with a nobler strain,</l>
     <l n="123">"When soon we meet for aye, in yon star-sprinkled plain."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="124">Last came a bard of more exalted tread,</l>
     <l n="125">And THYRSIS hight by Dryad, Fawn, or Swain,</l>
     <l n="126">Whene'er he mingled with the sylvan train;</l>
     <l n="127">But seldom that; for higher thoughts he fed;</l>
     <l n="128">For him full oft the heav'nly Muses led</l>
     <l n="129">To clear Euphrates, and the secret mount,</l>
     <l n="130">To Araby, and Eden, fragrant climes;</l>
     <l n="131">All which the sacred bard would oft recount:</l>
     <l n="132">And thus in strain, unus'd in grove or shade,</l>
     <l n="133">To sad MUSAEUS rightful homage paid.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="134">"Thrice hail, thou heav'n-taught warbler, last and best</l>
     <l n="135">"Of all the train! Poet, in whom conjoin'd</l>
     <l n="136">"All that to ear, or heart, or head, could yield</l>
     <l n="137">"Rapture; harmonious, manly, clear, sublime!</l>
     <l n="138">"Accept this gratulation: may it chear</l>
     <l n="139">"Thy sinking soul; nor these corporeal ills</l>
     <l n="140">"Ought daunt thee, or appall. Know, in high heav'n</l>
     <l n="141">"Fame blooms eternal o'er that spirit divine,</l>
     <l n="142">"Who builds immortal verse. There thy bold Muse,</l>
     <l n="143">"Which while on earth could breathe Maeonian fire,</l>
     <l n="144">"Shall soar seraphick heights; while to her voice</l>
     <l n="145">"Ten thousand Hierarchies of angels harp</l>
     <l n="146">"Symphonious, and with dulcet harmonies</l>
     <l n="147">"Usher the song rejoicing. I meanwhile,</l>
     <l n="148">"To sooth thee in these irksome hours of pain,</l>
     <l n="149">"Approach thy visitant, with mortal laud</l>
     <l n="150">"To praise thee mortal. First, (as first beseems)</l>
     <l n="151">"For rhyme subdu'd; rhyme, erst the minstrel rude</l>
     <l n="152">"Of Chaos, Anarch old: she near his throne</l>
     <l n="153">"Oft taught the rattling elements to chime</l>
     <l n="154">"With tenfold din; till late to earth upborn</l>
     <l n="155">"On strident wing, what time fair poesie</l>
     <l n="156">"Emerg'd from Gothick cloud, and faintly shot</l>
     <l n="157">"Rekindling gleams of lustre. Her the fiend</l>
     <l n="158">"Oppress'd; forcing to utter uncouth dirge,</l>
     <l n="159">"Runick, or Leonine; and with dire chains</l>
     <l n="160">"Fetter'd her scarce-fledg'd pinion. I such bonds</l>
     <l n="161">"Aim'd to destroy, mistaking: bonds like these</l>
     <l n="162">"'Twere greater art t' ennoble, and refine.</l>
     <l n="163">"For this superior part MUSAEUS came:</l>
     <l n="164">"Thou cam'st, and at thy magick touch the chains</l>
     <l n="165">"Off dropt, and (passing strange!) soft-wreathed bands</l>
     <l n="166">"Of flow'rs their place supply'd! which well the Muse</l>
     <l n="167">"Might wear for choice, not force; obstruction none,</l>
     <l n="168">"But loveliest ornament. Wond'rous this, yet here</l>
     <l n="169">"The wonder rests not; various argument</l>
     <l n="170">"Remains for me, all doubting, where to cull</l>
     <l n="171">"The primal grace, where countless graces charm.</l>
     <l n="172">"Various this peaceful scene, this mineral roof;</l>
     <l n="173">"This 'semblance meet of coral, ore, and shell;</l>
     <l n="174">"These pointed crystals fair, 'mid each obscure</l>
     <l n="175">"Bright glist'ring; all these slowly-dripping rills,</l>
     <l n="176">"That tinkling stray amid the cooly cave.</l>
     <l n="177">"Yet not this various peaceful scene; with this</l>
     <l n="178">"Its mineral roof; nor this assemblage meet</l>
     <l n="179">"Of coral, ore, and shell; nor 'mid th' obscure</l>
     <l n="180">"These pointed crystals, glist'ring fair; nor rills,</l>
     <l n="181">"That straying tinkle thro' the cooly cave;</l>
     <l n="182">"Deal charms more various to each raptur'd sense,</l>
     <l n="183">"Than thy mellifluous lay —"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="184">"Cease, friendly swain;</l>
     <l n="185">(MUSAEUS cry'd, and rais'd his aching head)</l>
     <l n="186">"All praise is foreign, but of true desert;</l>
     <l n="187">"Plays round the head, but comes not to the heart.</l>
     <l n="188">"Ah! why recall the toys of thoughtless youth?</l>
     <l n="189">"When flow'ry fiction held the place of truth:</l>
     <l n="190">"When fancy rul'd; when trill'd each trivial strain,</l>
     <l n="191">"But idly sweet, and elegantly vain.</l>
     <l n="192">"O! in that strain, if all of wit had flow'd,</l>
     <l n="193">"All musick warbled, and all beauty glow'd;</l>
     <l n="194">"Had liveliest nature, happiest art combin'd,</l>
     <l n="195">"That lent each grace, and this each grace refin'd;</l>
     <l n="196">"Alas! how little were my proudest boast!</l>
     <l n="197">"The sweetest trifler of my tribe at most.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14" stanza_type="sestet">
     <l n="198">"To sway the judgment, while he charms the ear;</l>
     <l n="199">"To curb mad passion in its wild career;</l>
     <l n="200">"To blend with skill, as loftiest themes inspire,</l>
     <l n="201">"All reason's rigour, and all fancy's fire;</l>
     <l n="202">"Be this the poet's praise; with this uncrown'd,</l>
     <l n="203">"Wit dies a jest, and poetry a sound.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="204">"Come then that honest fame; whose sober ray</l>
     <l n="205">"Or gilds the satire, or the moral lay,</l>
     <l n="206">"Which dawns, tho' thou, rough DONNE! hew out the line,</l>
     <l n="207">"But beams, sage HORACE, from each strain of thine.</l>
     <l n="208">"O! if, like these, one poet more could brave</l>
     <l n="209">"The venal statesman, or the titled slave;</l>
     <l n="210">"Brand frontless Vice, strip all her stars and strings,</l>
     <l n="211">"Nor spare her basking in the smile of kings:</l>
     <l n="212">"Yet stoop to Virtue, tho' the prostrate maid</l>
     <l n="213">"Lay sadly pale in bleak misfortune's shade:</l>
     <l n="214">"If grave, yet lively; rational, yet warm;</l>
     <l n="215">"Clear to convince, and eloquent to charm;</l>
     <l n="216">"He pour'd, for her lov'd cause, serene along</l>
     <l n="217">"The purest precept, in the sweetest song:</l>
     <l n="218">"For her lov'd cause, he trac'd his moral plan,</l>
     <l n="219">"Yon various region of bewild'ring man;</l>
     <l n="220">"Explor'd alike each scene, that frown'd or smil'd,</l>
     <l n="221">"The flow'ry garden, or the weedy wild;</l>
     <l n="222">"Unmov'd by sophistry, unaw'd by name,</l>
     <l n="223">"No dupe to doctrines, and no fool to fame;</l>
     <l n="224">"Led by no system's devious glare astray,</l>
     <l n="225">"As earth-born meteors glitter to betray:</l>
     <l n="226">"But all his soul to reason's rule resign'd,</l>
     <l n="227">"And heav'n's own views fair op'ning on his mind,</l>
     <l n="228">"Catch'd from bright nature's flame the living ray,</l>
     <l n="229">"Thro' passion's cloud pour'd in resistless day;</l>
     <l n="230">"And this great truth in all its lustre shew'd,</l>
     <l n="231">"That GOD IS WISE, and ALL CREATION GOOD:</l>
     <l n="232">"If this his boast, pour here the welcome lays:</l>
     <l n="233">"Praise less than this, is impotence of praise. "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="234">"To pour that praise be mine," fair VIRTUE cry'd,</l>
     <l n="235">And shot all radiant, thro' an op'ning cloud.</l>
     <l n="236">But ah! my Muse, how will thy voice express</l>
     <l n="237">Th' immortal strain, harmonious, as it flow'd?</l>
     <l n="238">Ill suits immortal strain a dorick dress:</l>
     <l n="239">And far too high already hast thou soar'd.</l>
     <l n="240">Enough for thee, that, when the lay was o'er,</l>
     <l n="241">The goddess clasp'd him to her throbbing breast.</l>
     <l n="242">But what might that avail? Blind Fate before</l>
     <l n="243">Had op'd her shears, to slit his vital thread;</l>
     <l n="244">And who may hope gainsay her stern behest?</l>
     <l n="245">Then thrice he wav'd the hand, thrice bow'd the head,</l>
     <l n="246">And sigh'd his soul to rest.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
     <l n="247">Then wept the Nymphs; witness, ye waving shades!</l>
     <l n="248">Witness, ye winding streams! the Nymphs did weep;</l>
     <l n="249">The heav'nly Goddess too with tears did steep</l>
     <l n="250">Her plaintive voice, that echo'd thro' the glades;</l>
     <l n="251">And, "cruel gods," and "cruel stars," she cry'd:</l>
     <l n="252">Nor did the shepherds, thro' the woodlands wide,</l>
     <l n="253">On that sad day, or to the pensive brook,</l>
     <l n="254">Or stagnant river, drive their thirsty flocks;</l>
     <l n="255">Nor did the wild-goat bronze the steepy rocks;</l>
     <l n="256">And Philomel her custom'd oak forsook;</l>
     <l n="257">And roses wan were wav'd by zephyrs weak,</l>
     <l n="258">As Nature's self was sick;</l>
     <l n="259">And every lilly droop'd its velvet head;</l>
     <l n="260">And groan'd each faded lawn, and leasless grove;</l>
     <l n="261">Sad sympathy! yet sure his rightful meed,</l>
     <l n="262">Who charm'd all nature: well might Nature mourn</l>
     <l n="263">Thro' all her sweets; and flow'r, and lawn, and shade,</l>
     <l n="264">All vocal grown, all weep MUSAEUS dead.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18">
     <l n="265">Here end we, Goddess: this your shepherd sang,</l>
     <l n="266">All as his hands an ivy chaplet wove.</l>
     <l n="267">O! make it worthy of the sacred bard,</l>
     <l n="268">And make it equal to the shepherd's love.</l>
     <l n="269">Nor thou, MUSAEUS, from thine ear discard,</l>
     <l n="270">For well I ween thou hear'st my doleful song;</l>
     <l n="271">Whether 'mid angel troops, the stars among,</l>
     <l n="272">From golden harps thou call'st seraphick lays;</l>
     <l n="273">Or, anxious for thy dearest Virtue's fare,</l>
     <l n="274">Thou still art hov'ring o'er her tuneless sphere,</l>
     <l n="275">And mov'st some hidden spring her weal to raise.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19" stanza_type="octet">
     <l n="276">Thus the fond swain on dorick oate essay'd,</l>
     <l n="277">Manhood's prime honours downing on his cheek:</l>
     <l n="278">Trembling he strove to court the tuneful maid</l>
     <l n="279">With stripling arts, and dalliance all too weak;</l>
     <l n="280">Unseen, unheard, beneath an hawthorn shade.</l>
     <l n="281">But now dun clouds the welkin 'gan to streak;</l>
     <l n="282">And now down-dropt the larks, and ceas'd their strain:</l>
     <l n="283">They ceas'd, and with them ceas'd the shepherd swain.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>