<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>A SPOUSAL HYMN. ADDRESSED TO HIS MAJESTY ON HIS MARRIAGE.</title>
    <author>James Scott</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">19</measure>
    <measure unit="line">190</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>James Scott_a-spousal-hymn-addressed-to-hi</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>A SPOUSAL HYMN. ADDRESSED TO HIS MAJESTY ON HIS MARRIAGE.</title>
     <author>James Scott</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>A SPOUSAL HYMN. ADDRESSED TO HIS MAJESTY ON HIS MARRIAGE.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">AS, when diffus'd in solemn trance</l>
     <l n="2">Her dear delight the Latmian shepherd lay,</l>
     <l n="3">Fond Cynthia came with lightning-glance,</l>
     <l n="4">And o'er his bosom stream'd her virgin ray:</l>
     <l n="5">So come, O gentle Muse, if e'er aright</l>
     <l n="6">I paid my vows, if e'er implor'd</l>
     <l n="7">One scanty beam of thy celestial light;</l>
     <l n="8">Proof to the muckworm miser's golden hoard,</l>
     <l n="9">Nor envious of the statesman's fair renown,</l>
     <l n="10">The warrior's death-bought wreath, and monarch's thorny crown.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="11">Come, Guardian of my natal hour,</l>
     <l n="12">That bad'st me chuse the still sequester'd grove,</l>
     <l n="13">The pathless mead, and woodbine bower,</l>
     <l n="14">Where placid Cares, and pensive Pleasures rove;</l>
     <l n="15">Where oft by moon-light's silent, solemn glade,</l>
     <l n="16">Pale Passion musing loves to stray,</l>
     <l n="17">And hand in hand, by Melancholy led,</l>
     <l n="18">In thoughtful loneness wears herself away;</l>
     <l n="19">O come, in all thy radiant charms confest,</l>
     <l n="20">And fire with glowing zeal my fond, devoted breast!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="21">I ask not flowrets fresh and gay,</l>
     <l n="22">From Pindus cull'd to please the vainly great;</l>
     <l n="23">No silken strain, no tinsel lay,</l>
     <l n="24">To cloke some public Knave from public hate:</l>
     <l n="25">No, Virgin, no — Fair Freedom's vestal flame</l>
     <l n="26">Pervades my soul; for Her I twine</l>
     <l n="27">The votive wreath, for Her thy hallow'd name</l>
     <l n="28">Invoke, O make thy choicest treasures mine;</l>
     <l n="29">Breathe Inspiration thro' each glowing line,</l>
     <l n="30">Thy genuine form impress, and stamp the work divine!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="31">Then shalt thou, George, the song approve,</l>
     <l n="32">O British-born! O Freedom's sacred heir!</l>
     <l n="33">O thou, whom all the Graces love,</l>
     <l n="34">Religion's boast, and Virtue's darling care!</l>
     <l n="35">Fain would the Muse attempt thy various praise,</l>
     <l n="36">But ah, in vain! — thro' Ida's bowers</l>
     <l n="37">With dubious foot th' astonish'd woodman strays;</l>
     <l n="38">Where shall his work begin? — Ye sylvan Powers</l>
     <l n="39">Direct the blow; here oaks aspiring rise,</l>
     <l n="40">There, Monarchs of the grove, tall cedars prop the skies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="41">Say, shall the Muse thy patriot Sire</l>
     <l n="42">Recall to view? Tell how with conscious state</l>
     <l n="43">She saw the god-like Prince retire</l>
     <l n="44">To glorious exile, like Timoleon great?</l>
     <l n="45">Glad heard the voice, "Avaunt, ye wretched Train,</l>
     <l n="46">" Shall I my Country's cause betray?</l>
     <l n="47">"Betray my soul, my God, for sordid gain?</l>
     <l n="48">" Perish the thought! — Ye Slaves of gold away! —</l>
     <l n="49">"In venal courts tho' base corruption reigns,</l>
     <l n="50">" Know Liberty shall breathe thro' Kew's indignant plains. "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="51">He spoke, and lo! the reptile crew</l>
     <l n="52">Struck dumb with wonder fled! — Hail, sacred source,</l>
     <l n="53">Whence George his patriot morals drew:</l>
     <l n="54">Prosper, ye heavenly Powers, their genial course!</l>
     <l n="55">O bid them branch into a thousand rills,</l>
     <l n="56">A thousand streams! — Where-e'er they flow,</l>
     <l n="57">Whether all glist'ring down the loftier hills,</l>
     <l n="58">Or thro' the still, and humbler vales below,</l>
     <l n="59">Let Health pursue, no noxious weeds be found,</l>
     <l n="60">But flowers immortal rise fresh-breathing sweets around!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="61">Prophetic wish! — See Discord flies,</l>
     <l n="62">With all her rebel rout, her hell-born train!</l>
     <l n="63">See Faction falls, and Party dies,</l>
     <l n="64">They die fell serpents, in his dawning reign:</l>
     <l n="65">Thus sure presage of many a glorious deed,</l>
     <l n="66">Blest omen of immortal fame,</l>
     <l n="67">The Son of Jove, when near his infant head</l>
     <l n="68">Devouring snakes in poisonous volumes came,</l>
     <l n="69">Grasp'd in his brawny arms the scaly foes,</l>
     <l n="70">Smil'd on the danger past, and sunk to soft repose.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="71">And now again, with careful hand,</l>
     <l n="72">Her goodly plants fair Science joys to rear;</l>
     <l n="73">And now again all blooming stand</l>
     <l n="74">The beauteous Progeny of Art; they fear</l>
     <l n="75">No killing frosts, no thick unkindly dews,</l>
     <l n="76">Such as from Belgian plains arise;</l>
     <l n="77">The genial clouds their pearly drops diffuse,</l>
     <l n="78">And shower increase of sweetness from the skies;</l>
     <l n="79">The youthful Sun, in his meridian throne,</l>
     <l n="80">Beams with indulgent ray his fostering influence down.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="81">Hail, favour'd Isle! blest seat of Fame!</l>
     <l n="82">For conquering arms, and peerless arts renown'd!</l>
     <l n="83">Hail, mighty George! thy darling name</l>
     <l n="84">Oft shall the Muse with honest joy refound:</l>
     <l n="85">Not that abstemious, prudent, just, and wise,</l>
     <l n="86">Thy every deed fair Virtue guides;</l>
     <l n="87">Nor that thy thoughts with holy ardor rise</l>
     <l n="88">From Earth's low base, where Vice and Passion bides,</l>
     <l n="89">To Heaven's bright mansions, there their sweets dispense,</l>
     <l n="90">Grateful as hallow'd fumes from breathing frankincense.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="91">Ay me so great, so bold a flight</l>
     <l n="92">Beseems not shepherd-swain, in lowly Mead</l>
     <l n="93">Far from Preferment's giddy height</l>
     <l n="94">Condemn'd, alas, an hireling flock to feed!</l>
     <l n="95">Yet will I sing how thy discerning eye</l>
     <l n="96">The boisterous sea of life surveys,</l>
     <l n="97">Where toiling fore the Sons of Merit lie,</l>
     <l n="98">Till call'd by thee their weary heads they raise:</l>
     <l n="99">What minute Drop, but cherish'd by thy care</l>
     <l n="100">A costly Pearl becomes of matchless Beauty rare?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="101">Charm then your pipes, ye shepherd swains,</l>
     <l n="102">And bid the hills, and dales the Song repeat,</l>
     <l n="103">Your Patron, your Augustus reigns! —</l>
     <l n="104">But hark, with undulation soft, and sweet,</l>
     <l n="105">What melting music steals upon the ear!</l>
     <l n="106">Am I deceiv'd, or doth a Choir</l>
     <l n="107">Of winged Cupids fan the buxom air</l>
     <l n="108">Till Silence smiles; while from their silver lyre</l>
     <l n="109">Harmonious numbers flow, whose dulcet breath</l>
     <l n="110">Would recreate a soul beneath the pangs of death?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="111">I did not err, a Choir of Loves</l>
     <l n="112">Sublime in air attune th' enchanting lay;</l>
     <l n="113">They leave Idalia's blooming groves,</l>
     <l n="114">And Cypria's myrtle shades, where jocund stray</l>
     <l n="115">The Graces, Smiles, and Hours, where Nature's care</l>
     <l n="116">Profusely kind allures the sight,</l>
     <l n="117">And wraps the sense in bliss: ye Virgins fair</l>
     <l n="118">Of Britain's Isle, sweet daughters of delight,</l>
     <l n="119">Receive the cherub throng, to you they fly</l>
     <l n="120">With welcome tidings fraught, blest harbingers of Joy.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="121">Lo! lo she comes from th' Albine shore,</l>
     <l n="122">Your maiden Queen, adorn'd with peerless charms:</l>
     <l n="123">Like Phoebe, when by Taurus hoar</l>
     <l n="124">Enamour'd Alpheus strove with eager arms</l>
     <l n="125">To grasp the Fair: ah, fond and hapless boy!</l>
     <l n="126">Ah, cruel wayward Dame! — in vain</l>
     <l n="127">He breath'd his amorous soul, for all too coy</l>
     <l n="128">Swift as the Roe she sought the distant plain;</l>
     <l n="129">Left him to pour in tears his plaintive theme,</l>
     <l n="130">Till chang'd by love and grief he melted to a stream.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="131">See where from Ocean's pearly bed,</l>
     <l n="132">Whose huddling waters pass unwilling by,</l>
     <l n="133">She comes with easy modest tread,</l>
     <l n="134">'Midst echoing crowds, and rapturous shouts of joy:</l>
     <l n="135">'Twas thus, the life-resembling tablet shews,</l>
     <l n="136">In youth and beauty fresh and gay</l>
     <l n="137">The Paphian Goddess from the waves arose,</l>
     <l n="138">While dolphins gamboll'd thro' the watry way,</l>
     <l n="139">Old Neptune smil'd, the sea-green sisters sung,</l>
     <l n="140">And all the rooks around with Iö Triumph rung.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="141">But ah, what Daedal hand can trace</l>
     <l n="142">The glowing beauties of her air and mien;</l>
     <l n="143">The lively sweetness of her face,</l>
     <l n="144">And eyes where wisdom's azure beams are seen?</l>
     <l n="145">Her bosom fraught with honour's maiden treasure,</l>
     <l n="146">Unblemish'd faith, mild modesty,</l>
     <l n="147">Eternal love, unsoil'd by baser pleasure,</l>
     <l n="148">And constant truth, and spotless chastity,</l>
     <l n="149">Where thoughts, that angels might admire, are bred,</l>
     <l n="150">And flames of holy zeal, by pure Religion fed?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="151">Hail, Virgin, hail, divinely blest,</l>
     <l n="152">By Heaven endow'd with all that's good and great!</l>
     <l n="153">O Flower of Virtue, in whose breast,</l>
     <l n="154">Imperial Reason dwells in royal state!</l>
     <l n="155">There, there she sits as Queen on ivory throne,</l>
     <l n="156">The vassal Passions round her stand,</l>
     <l n="157">In suppliant guise her rightful power they own,</l>
     <l n="158">And hear her still small voice, her soft command:</l>
     <l n="159">Far from the pure and unpolluted shrine</l>
     <l n="160">Each base affection flies, each haggard nurse of sin.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
     <l n="161">Leave then, ye Sisters, leave the Spring</l>
     <l n="162">Whose hallow'd waters flow thro' Minyas' land;</l>
     <l n="163">Conduct to Britain's blooming King</l>
     <l n="164">This all-accomplish'd work of Nature's hand:</l>
     <l n="165">'Tis yours, imperial Nymphs, whate'er is sweet,</l>
     <l n="166">And fair and splendid to bestow;</l>
     <l n="167">On you attend Wealth, Wisdom, Beauty, Wit;</l>
     <l n="168">Nor seated on Olympus' laughing brow</l>
     <l n="169">Will choirs celestial move till you advance,</l>
     <l n="170">Nor share th' ambrosial feast, nor lead the sprightly dance.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18">
     <l n="171">And thou, O Queen of soft desires,</l>
     <l n="172">Whose radiant smiles dispel the gloom of care,</l>
     <l n="173">And kindling friendship's purest fires,</l>
     <l n="174">Chase from the soul Suspicion, Doubt, and Fear,</l>
     <l n="175">Those griesly forms: O come, bewitching Power,</l>
     <l n="176">Come gently, o'er the bridal bed</l>
     <l n="177">In genial dews thy choicest pleasures shower;</l>
     <l n="178">Such as in Arcady's voluptuous shade</l>
     <l n="179">Lycaeus felt, when stretch'd on Maia's breast</l>
     <l n="180">An image of himself th' enraptur'd God imprest.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19">
     <l n="181">Nor thou, Lucina chaste and fair,</l>
     <l n="182">Nor thou, sweet Genius of the nuptial bower,</l>
     <l n="183">Be absent; on the royal Pair</l>
     <l n="184">Profuse of joy your kindly blessings pour!</l>
     <l n="185">O haste, ye Guardians of the sacred rites,</l>
     <l n="186">Whose aid prolific power supplies,</l>
     <l n="187">So shall Britannia bless their pure delights,</l>
     <l n="188">When future Georges, future Charlottes rise;</l>
     <l n="189">By whom reflected distant times shall find</l>
     <l n="190">The Mother's matchless Grace, the Father's virtuous Mind.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>