<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>PAPLET: OR, Love and Innocence.</title>
    <author>Thomas Purney</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">36</measure>
    <measure unit="line">233</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Thomas Purney_paplet-or-love-and-innocence</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>PAPLET: OR, Love and Innocence.</title>
     <author>Thomas Purney</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>PAPLET: OR, Love and Innocence.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">Gentle Swain yfed in  Mead,</l>
     <l n="2">The gentlest Swain that ever</l>
     <l n="3">Flock did feed.</l>
     <l n="4">Soft he beside the Stream of</l>
     <l n="5">EDEN lay,</l>
     <l n="6">And graz'd abie the Banks of fair MEDWAY.</l>
     <l n="7">Up with the Morn, as lith as Lark, he'd rise;</l>
     <l n="8">And  he, so said him Shepherd Boys.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="9">So as he sate, with LASS or toys the YOUTH;</l>
     <l n="10">Or soft he sooth's, for soft can  sooth.</l>
     <l n="11">There sweetly oped each Flower the little Lip,</l>
     <l n="12">Fresh Honey-dew and Evening Air to sip.</l>
     <l n="13">Was, when his CADE he'd kiss, and pretty play:</l>
     <l n="14">Or bath in  then roll on tender</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="15">Sooth! would too RHIMES go make as loose he lay,</l>
     <l n="16">(Though God-wot, to make RHIMES small Wit had he.)</l>
     <l n="17">And wont out-scrawl and print 'em on the</l>
     <l n="18">All as he lay along with Crook in Hand.</l>
     <l n="19">Poor Pen, you'll say: — Ay and poor Poet too!</l>
     <l n="20">But 'lack, must do what  will have Us do.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="21">Yet happy he, in time, found means to mark</l>
     <l n="22">His witless Tattle on a MAPLE's BARK.</l>
     <l n="23">But ah, how should he, poor Boy, 'ere find out,</l>
     <l n="24">Lines near enough to deck his TREE about.</l>
     <l n="25">Forc'd was he Swains o'rehear behind some balk,</l>
     <l n="26">Then on his TREE go print the tender Talk.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="27">Late he abie a Place of Pleasure lay,</l>
     <l n="28">All fairly deckt in Sweets of fairest MAY.</l>
     <l n="29">Where silkie Thighs in Dew  bath'd;</l>
     <l n="30">And merry cherruping, so rosie breath'd.</l>
     <l n="31">Ye  Swains! and  Swains have bliss;</l>
     <l n="32">I dare Ye show so soft a SHADE as this!</l>
     <l n="33">Atween the dewie Leaves as Air was blown,</l>
     <l n="34">The dewie Leaves yquivered every one.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="35">The why he came here was all for two Maids,</l>
     <l n="36">He thought, were chatting nigh, of Love and Lads.</l>
     <l n="37">He came the one to warn, that</l>
     <l n="38">The less did know of Love, did love the less.</l>
     <l n="39">Pity'd her the soft Swain: to warn he strove,</l>
     <l n="40">Lest the young HEART might hap to fall in love.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="41">Foreby him sate these Maids in loose Array,</l>
     <l n="42">As fair and fresh as Summer Eve might see.</l>
     <l n="43">Sweet gay-green Flowers, so pretty put anear,</l>
     <l n="44">The Pink and Pancet pretty put anear.</l>
     <l n="45">and  they; (ah dainty THEY!)</l>
     <l n="46">That ripe as Rose, this a soft-aged MEY.</l>
     <l n="47">Both lith as  all-tender too</l>
     <l n="48">As  that lives on twinkling Dew.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="49">a CHRISTIAN's and a JEWES's Child,</l>
     <l n="50">Scarce five Year old, was laid, to starve in Field;</l>
     <l n="51">For that the BABE' they could no longer hide:</l>
     <l n="52">But all by hap an anciant SIRE it spy'd;</l>
     <l n="53">Just starving; for the tender Teeth been broak,</l>
     <l n="54">As twould crack Nutt: It smiled when up he took</l>
     <l n="55">HIPS!</l>
     <l n="56">!</l>
     <l n="57">He tookt to's ; and pull'd the Thorns all out</l>
     <l n="58">Her pretty Feet; they bled with walk about.</l>
     <l n="59">There brought her up with  fresh his Son,</l>
     <l n="60">Who hunts wild Beasts, 'tis what they live epon.</l>
     <l n="61">Now sick if  or  she moans him meet,</l>
     <l n="62">Soft tend's, with cheary Chat, and soothing sweet</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="63">These gentle HEARTS small thought were  lay;</l>
     <l n="64">In sooth some halfendeal undeckt they be.</l>
     <l n="65">Honey-lip Gales soft breathed on their Hair,</l>
     <l n="66">Waved their Cloaths, and did their Bosoms bare</l>
     <l n="67">And well Iwis, as bare their bosoms, all</l>
     <l n="68">The Flowerets out that decked 'em did fall.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="69">A Willow on the bank upheld their Heads,</l>
     <l n="70">(Oh happy Tree, to hold such lovely Maids!)</l>
     <l n="71">A soothing shade the rosie Sweetbreer gave;</l>
     <l n="72">Where sang the Bird that sings so soft at Eve.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="73">Believe Me now, thus show'd they; by my fay</l>
     <l n="74">As lovely show'd, as Lilly on the !</l>
     <l n="75">But sure that  was the tend'rest Lass!</l>
     <l n="76">Well ween I  lay at little Ease.</l>
     <l n="77">So soft she seem'd! By Heav'n seem'd more</l>
     <l n="78">than soft!</l>
     <l n="79">Her Lip to touch he wish'd him, O how oft!</l>
     <l n="80">Now soothly  was the tend'rest !</l>
     <l n="81">Ah God! I small ween'd could so tender be!</l>
     <l n="82">Some-deal her Paps been pufft, that sooth might</l>
     <l n="83">seem</l>
     <l n="84">The LITTLE LIFE now just of Love gan dream?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="85">Now say me, Shepherds, who could help ha'</l>
     <l n="86">strove,</l>
     <l n="87">To save so sweet a HEART from pain of Love?</l>
     <l n="88">Love is a gentle pain, a pretty pain:</l>
     <l n="89">He came to keep from loving  Swain.</l>
     <l n="90">was fair as Morning DROP is fair,</l>
     <l n="91">And  tender as the Evening Air.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="92">When chatted they, so sweet their chatting were!</l>
     <l n="93">Oh I could hear, methought, for ever hear!</l>
     <l n="94">On FELLOW first, then TREE, they pretty loll,</l>
     <l n="95">Quiver their little Lips, their Eyen roll.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="96">Sooth, ever and anon, as  spoak,</l>
     <l n="97">in extasie would hide her LOOK.</l>
     <l n="98">Then asken more; yet shamed to asken more,</l>
     <l n="99">(Of MEN and LOVE) but long'd to know so sore.</l>
     <l n="100">Sometimes she'd fling her self epon the Grass:</l>
     <l n="101">Then up, and catch in Arms her</l>
     <l n="102">Why may'nt we Men, yquoth the youngling MEY,</l>
     <l n="103">And why may'nt we grasp them? Us graspen they</l>
     <l n="104">So pleased she was, and eager still to know,</l>
     <l n="105">In sooth so pleased, she knew not what to do.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="106">But ill I say how sweet the Lasses sate,</l>
     <l n="107">Oh that you'd seen 'em,, I'd give any what!</l>
     <l n="108">This sooth I say (for sooth the Shepherds say)</l>
     <l n="109">Soft simpering thus said the YOUNGLING MEY.</l>
     <l n="110">The meaning of the MEY no whit I ween.</l>
     <l n="111">I'm sure, when near I came, just thus she sain.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="112">Paplet,  Paplet,</l>
     <l n="113">Soflies</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
     <l n="114">If be but why, small harm ybe I weet.</l>
     <l n="115">and I late roved, Nuts to get.</l>
     <l n="116">I witless was so bonny and so brag,</l>
     <l n="117">( beware not be with Love so wag)</l>
     <l n="118">I scratchen Chin; ah luckless Lass the when!</l>
     <l n="119">See here but, ! I all scratch'd my Chin!</l>
     <l n="120">The Wound he wiped, and kist it 'ore and 'ore;</l>
     <l n="121">Why sooth now,  else 'twould been a sore.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18">
     <l n="122">Whatso I could to bar my blush, I did;</l>
     <l n="123">Yet ween not whether somedeal look'd not red.</l>
     <l n="124">But 'twas allfor his Eyes so soft did seem:</l>
     <l n="125">While Honeybreath epon my Neck would steam.</l>
     <l n="126">And oh, his ringlet-locks too, where they fell</l>
     <l n="127">Tittled my breasts! and I was 'shamed to tell.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19">
     <l n="128">Ay? say'st in sooth? and then — why dost not say?</l>
     <l n="129">Was it not lovely, when so loose he lay?</l>
     <l n="130">Meseems I should ha' pleased with tender Tongue</l>
     <l n="131">Or sooth'd, the while, with softness of a Song.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="20">
     <l n="132">()</l>
     <l n="133">Fellow's</l>
     <l n="134">Soflie :</l>
     <l n="135">!  Cubbin !</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="21">
     <l n="136">Dainty? Ay dainty more than heart may weet</l>
     <l n="137">Don't look at me,  and I'll tell thee what.</l>
     <l n="138">I putten hand in's bosom now that be's,</l>
     <l n="139">So silkie soft! then gently gave't a kiss!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="22">
     <l n="140" />
     <l n="141">Paplet ;</l>
     <l n="142">:</l>
     <l n="143">Cubbin !</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="23">
     <l n="144">O simple he's of Chear, and meek of Mein;</l>
     <l n="145">All-fine his Flesh, and sooth as soft his Skin!</l>
     <l n="146">So prettily his Words slip off his Tongue,</l>
     <l n="147">With a little waggish Lisp emong!</l>
     <l n="148">But when he sooths too pleasant 'tis to bear!</l>
     <l n="149">He kisses, I ask if a rosie be near!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="24">
     <l n="150">But see there!  CADE! how that came there?</l>
     <l n="151">Sure by the Lamb the Lassie should be near!</l>
     <l n="152">Oh! Well beween'd! We bath in Brook this Eve</l>
     <l n="153">You see where SPRAYS so sweet a shadow give.</l>
     <l n="154">You're one; and  Lass so heavenly hewn;</l>
     <l n="155">And  maiden ripe as Rose in</l>
     <l n="156">This  loves; and  fresh love that;</l>
     <l n="157">say some. Up Lass! mayhap they wait.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="25">
     <l n="158">THEY go: Their BOSOMS ope to th' Evening Air:</l>
     <l n="159">And dip their blooming BEAUTYS fresh and fair:</l>
     <l n="160">They pretty play and paddle in the :</l>
     <l n="161">And strow with fairest Flow'rs the</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="26">
     <l n="162">But  wistful was; On bank she set,</l>
     <l n="163">Siping the Honeysukles juicie SWEET.</l>
     <l n="164">But ah, her mind elsewhere! alass on love!</l>
     <l n="165">Oh  thou hast wrong'd a tender DOVE!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="27">
     <l n="166">When parted All; and All hied home; she made</l>
     <l n="167">As if she too; but silent by</l>
     <l n="168">Stale back to th' BUSH; with hands in bosom laid,</l>
     <l n="169">(Those hands all fair as flower) and hanging head.</l>
     <l n="170">Mayhap (soft said she) now HE goes to Bed.</l>
     <l n="171">I wonder how HE lyes when there he's laid!</l>
     <l n="172">Besure HE mind's not me when 'mong the Swains.</l>
     <l n="173">O could I touch HIM but, just touch meseems!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="28">
     <l n="174">Yet looked she at  on the ;</l>
     <l n="175">That twinkled fair, and strove not think on him.</l>
     <l n="176">Mused too on th' varying FIGURES made on Grass,</l>
     <l n="177">By th' Light, that 'tween the waving Trees did pass.</l>
     <l n="178">Where fancyeth she depainten this and that,</l>
     <l n="179">(But all of Love) atill to th' BUSH did get.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="29">
     <l n="180">There blush'd when first it saw to think that she</l>
     <l n="181">Should so steal back to th' place where  lay.</l>
     <l n="182">And am I then? And am I grown, she sain,</l>
     <l n="183">(With that gan pretty finger put in Eyen).</l>
     <l n="184">So sly and false? Oh Heav'n! don't see! or do,</l>
     <l n="185">Forgive! — small weeneth  where I now.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="30">
     <l n="186">So saying on the bank adown she laid.</l>
     <l n="187">Just where the  lean'd, as  said.</l>
     <l n="188">Then, smiling, thus: MAYHAP his head was put</l>
     <l n="189">Where mine is now: Who knows? O happy ROOT!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="31">
     <l n="190">This gentle  did see and hear,</l>
     <l n="191">Waiting abie, the pretty HEART to chear.</l>
     <l n="192">He went to sooth her soft, and warn her how</l>
     <l n="193">She thought on All would not do.</l>
     <l n="194">Soon as she saw, she started from her seat:</l>
     <l n="195">Ne would she hear him Pipe, ne talk awhit.</l>
     <l n="196">So that he made as if went strait away;</l>
     <l n="197">But went no farther then afore he lay.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="32">
     <l n="198">The dainty-limbed Lass, as soft to see,</l>
     <l n="199">As springing Flowrets in the Month of</l>
     <l n="200">Smooth laid her slender  down again,</l>
     <l n="201">All on the sweetness of the Flowrie Plain.</l>
     <l n="202">Ah gentle HEART! ah HEART of prettiness!</l>
     <l n="203">Where is the Dalliance, and the tender Kiss?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="33">
     <l n="204">Then sigh'd out this the rosie-liped Lass,</l>
     <l n="205">Soft as her Eye on Heaven yfixen was.</l>
     <l n="206">WHAT aileth, O what aileth thee, my Heart;</l>
     <l n="207">Now sooth meseem's thou be'st not as thou wer't.</l>
     <l n="208">Be  (ah would he other was!)</l>
     <l n="209">Far fairer than the fairest Lad or Lass,</l>
     <l n="210">Yet what have I to do with ?</l>
     <l n="211">Let me not be, e're be for  Pain!</l>
     <l n="212">Tho', methinks, were he not her's, I could well</l>
     <l n="213">Wish he were mine, Oh me, how wish him well!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="34">
     <l n="214">Thus sate the YOUNGLING MEY, till far the Night</l>
     <l n="215">Was spent, and sooth the Moon nigh lost her light.</l>
     <l n="216">Then up gan rise; but 'ere she 'gan up rise,</l>
     <l n="217">Tuck'd up her Hair, and wiped her dewie Eyes.</l>
     <l n="218">The SOFTHEART SWAIN (for Swainets all are so)</l>
     <l n="219">Staid till he wept, and when he wept did go.</l>
     <l n="220">Unhappy ! Now there love's with thee,</l>
     <l n="221">The sweetest  that ever Sun did see.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="35">
     <l n="222">All he had seen or heard, in head kept he,</l>
     <l n="223">To cut on  or mark upon his</l>
     <l n="224">For sure there is not who can envy that;</l>
     <l n="225">Not one, I ween, can envy LASSE's CHAT.</l>
     <l n="226">But why so fond of LASSES CHAT, say you.</l>
     <l n="227">Oh, had you seen 'em, you'd ha' been so too!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="36">
     <l n="228">Ye gentle YOUTHS! who rove where led by chance</l>
     <l n="229">If be on  grief your Eye should glance,</l>
     <l n="230">Think the poor Lass mishap enough has had;</l>
     <l n="231">Ah don't you add, by hating what she said!</l>
     <l n="232">Ween, if ye maken mock at it, ye make</l>
     <l n="233">At  mock; don't so, for  sake!</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>