<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>IMMORTALITY: or, the Consolation of HUMAN LIFE. A MONODY.</title>
    <author>Thomas Denton</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">31</measure>
    <measure unit="line">310</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Thomas Denton_immortality-or-the-consolation</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>IMMORTALITY: or, the Consolation of HUMAN LIFE. A MONODY.</title>
     <author>Thomas Denton</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>IMMORTALITY: or, the Consolation of HUMAN LIFE. A MONODY.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="1" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">WHEN black-brow'd Night her dusky mantle spread,</l>
     <l n="2" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And wrapt in solemn gloom the sable sky;</l>
     <l n="3" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">When soothing Sleep her opiate dews had shed,</l>
     <l n="4" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And seal'd in silken slumbers ev'ry eye:</l>
     <l n="5" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">My wakeful thoughts admit no balmy rest,</l>
     <l n="6" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor the sweet bliss of soft oblivion share;</l>
     <l n="7" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">But watchful woe distracts my aching breast,</l>
     <l n="8" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">My heart the subject of corroding care:</l>
     <l n="9" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">From haunts of men with wand'ring steps and slow</l>
     <l n="10" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">I solitary steal, and sooth my pensive woe.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="11" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Yet no fell passion's rough discordant rage</l>
     <l n="12" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Untun'd the music of my tranquil mind;</l>
     <l n="13" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ambition's tinsell'd charms could ne'er engage,</l>
     <l n="14" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">No harbour there could sordid av'rice find:</l>
     <l n="15" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">From lust's foul spring my grief disdains to flow,</l>
     <l n="16" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">No sighs of envy from my bosom break,</l>
     <l n="17" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">But soft compassion melts my soul to woe,</l>
     <l n="18" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And social tears fast trickle down my cheek;</l>
     <l n="19" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ah me! when nature gives one general groan,</l>
     <l n="20" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Each heart must beat with woe, each voice responsive moan.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="21" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where'er I cast my moist'ned eyes around,</l>
     <l n="22" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Or stretch my prospect o'er the distant land,</l>
     <l n="23" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">There foul  tainted steps are found,</l>
     <l n="24" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And  grim-visag'd waves his iron hand.</l>
     <l n="25" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' now soft  gild the smiling scene,</l>
     <l n="26" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And sportive  call forth her festive train,</l>
     <l n="27" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Sinking in night each vital form is seen,</l>
     <l n="28" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Like air-blown bubbles on the wat'ry plain;</l>
     <l n="29" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Fell  like brooding  the repast</l>
     <l n="30" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Will snatch with talons foul, or sour its grateful taste.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="31" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ye smiling glories of the youthful year,</l>
     <l n="32" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">That ope your fragrant bosoms to the day,</l>
     <l n="33" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">That clad in all the pride of spring appear,</l>
     <l n="34" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And steep'd in dew your silken leaves display:</l>
     <l n="35" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">In  richest robes tho' thus bedight,</l>
     <l n="36" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' her soft pencil trace your various dye,</l>
     <l n="37" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' lures your roseate hue the charmed sight,</l>
     <l n="38" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' odours sweet your nect'rous breath supply,</l>
     <l n="39" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Soon on your leaves  cank'rous tooth shall prey,</l>
     <l n="40" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Your dulcet dews exhale, your beauteous bloom decay.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="41" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ye hedge-row elms, beneath whose spreading shade</l>
     <l n="42" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The grazing herds defy the ratt'ling shower;</l>
     <l n="43" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ye lofty oaks, in whose wide arms display'd</l>
     <l n="44" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The clam'rous rook builds high his airy bower;</l>
     <l n="45" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Stript by hoar Winter's rough inclement rage,</l>
     <l n="46" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">In mournful heaps your leafy honours lie,</l>
     <l n="47" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ev'n your hard ribs shall feel the force of age,</l>
     <l n="48" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And your bare trunks the friendly shade deny;</l>
     <l n="49" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">No more by cheerful vegetation green,</l>
     <l n="50" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Your sapless bolls shall sink, and quit th' evanid scene.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="51" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ye feather'd warblers of the vernal year</l>
     <l n="52" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">That careless sing, nor fear the frowns of fate,</l>
     <l n="53" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tune your sad notes to death and winter drear!</l>
     <l n="54" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ill suit these mirthful strains your transient state.</l>
     <l n="55" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">No more with cheerful song nor sprightly air</l>
     <l n="56" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Salute the blushes of the rising day,</l>
     <l n="57" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">With doleful ditties, drooping wings repair</l>
     <l n="58" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">To the lone covert of the nightly spray:</l>
     <l n="59" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where love-lorn  strains her throat,</l>
     <l n="60" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Surround the budding thorn, and swell the mournful note.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="61" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Come, sighing  with sweetest airs</l>
     <l n="62" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Of melting music teach my grief to flow,</l>
     <l n="63" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">I too must mix my sad complaint with theirs,</l>
     <l n="64" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Our fates are equal, equal be our woe.</l>
     <l n="65" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Come,  spread thy raven wing,</l>
     <l n="66" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And in thy ebon car, by Fancy led,</l>
     <l n="67" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">To the dark charnel vault thy vot'ry bring,</l>
     <l n="68" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The murky mansions of the mould'ring dead,</l>
     <l n="69" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where dank dews breathe, and taint the sickly skies,</l>
     <l n="70" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where in sad loathsome heaps all human glory lies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="71" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Wrapt in the gloom of uncreated night</l>
     <l n="72" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Secure we slept in senseless matter's arms,</l>
     <l n="73" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor pain could vex, nor pallid fear affright,</l>
     <l n="74" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Our quiet fancy felt no dream's alarms.</l>
     <l n="75" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Soon as to life our animated clay</l>
     <l n="76" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Awakes, and conscious being opes our eyes,</l>
     <l n="77" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Care's fretful family at once dismay,</l>
     <l n="78" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">With ghastly air a thousand phantoms rise,</l>
     <l n="79" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Sad  hangs o'er all the deep'ning gloom,</l>
     <l n="80" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">prompts the labour'd sigh,  opes the marble tomb.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="81" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Yet life's strong love intoxicates the soul,</l>
     <l n="82" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And thirst of bliss inflames the fev'rous mind,</l>
     <l n="83" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">With eager draughts we drain the pois'nous bowl,</l>
     <l n="84" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And in the dregs the cordial hope to find.</l>
     <l n="85" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">O heav'n! for this light end were mortals made,</l>
     <l n="86" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And plac'd on earth, with happiness in view,</l>
     <l n="87" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">To catch with cheated grasp the flitting shade,</l>
     <l n="88" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And with vain toil the fancied form pursue,</l>
     <l n="89" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Then give their short-liv'd being to the wind,</l>
     <l n="90" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">As the wing'd arrow flies, and leaves no track behind!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="91" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thus lonely wand'ring thro' the nightly shade</l>
     <l n="92" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Against the stern decrees of stubborn Fate,</l>
     <l n="93" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">To mockful Echo my complaints I made,</l>
     <l n="94" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Of life's short period, or its toilsome state.</l>
     <l n="95" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">'Tis death-like silence all, no sound I hear,</l>
     <l n="96" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Save the hoarse raven croaking from the sky,</l>
     <l n="97" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Or scaly beetle murm'ring thro' the air,</l>
     <l n="98" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Or screech-owl screaming with ill-o men'd cry;</l>
     <l n="99" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Save when with brazen tongue from yon high tow'r</l>
     <l n="100" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The clock deep-sounding speaks, and counts the passing hour.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="101" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Pale Cynthia mounted on her silver car</l>
     <l n="102" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">O'er heav'n's blue concave drives her nightly round:</l>
     <l n="103" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">See a torn abbey, wrapt in gloom, appear</l>
     <l n="104" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Scatter'd in wild confusion o'er the ground.</l>
     <l n="105" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Here rav'nous  lifts her wasteful hands</l>
     <l n="106" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">O'er bri'ar-grown grots and bramble-shaded graves;</l>
     <l n="107" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Safe from her wrath one weeping marble stands,</l>
     <l n="108" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">O'er which the mournful yew its umbrage waves;</l>
     <l n="109" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ope, ope thy pond'rous jaws, thou friendly tomb,</l>
     <l n="110" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Close the sad deathful scene, and shroud me in thy womb!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="111" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Forth issuing lovely from the gloomy shade,</l>
     <l n="112" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Which stately pines in phalanx deep compose,</l>
     <l n="113" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Fair above mortals comes a smiling maid</l>
     <l n="114" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">To sooth my sighs, and cheer my heart-felt woes.</l>
     <l n="115" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Here nurs'd by  matron sage,</l>
     <l n="116" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where with mute  she loves to dwell,</l>
     <l n="117" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">In truth's fair lore she form'd her early age,</l>
     <l n="118" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And trim'd the midnight lamp in lonely cell,</l>
     <l n="119" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Here learn'd clear reason's heav'n-sprung light to raise</l>
     <l n="120" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">O'er passion's low-born mists, or pleasure's spurious blaze.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="121" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Her azure mantle flows with easy grace,</l>
     <l n="122" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor fashion's folds constrain, nor custom's tye;</l>
     <l n="123" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">An optic tube she bears, each sphere to trace</l>
     <l n="124" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">That rolls its rapid orbit round the sky:</l>
     <l n="125" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Yet not to heav'n alone her view's confin'd;</l>
     <l n="126" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">A clear reflecting plane she holds, to show</l>
     <l n="127" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The various movements of the reas'ning mind,</l>
     <l n="128" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">How strange ideas link, and habits grow,</l>
     <l n="129" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Passion's fierce impulse, will's free power to scan,</l>
     <l n="130" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">To paint the featur'd soul, and mark th' internal man.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="131" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Whence these sad strains, said she, of plaintive grief,</l>
     <l n="132" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Which pierce the sleep-clos'd ear of peaceful rest?</l>
     <l n="133" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Oft has the sick'ning mind here found relief,</l>
     <l n="134" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Here quell'd the throbbing tumults of the breast:</l>
     <l n="135" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Lift up thy loaden eyes to yon fair cloud,</l>
     <l n="136" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where moon-sprung  blends her beauteous dyes:</l>
     <l n="137" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">I lift them soon, and as I gazing stood,</l>
     <l n="138" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The fleeting phantom in a moment flies;</l>
     <l n="139" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where beam'd the gilded arch of gaudy hue,</l>
     <l n="140" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Frowns the dark lou'ring cloud all gloomy to the view.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="141" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Life's emblem fit, said I, that roscid bow!</l>
     <l n="142" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The gay illusive pageant of an hour</l>
     <l n="143" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">To real semblance tricks her air shew,</l>
     <l n="144" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Then sinks in night's dull arms, and is no more!</l>
     <l n="145" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ah! fool, said she, tho' now to fancy's sight</l>
     <l n="146" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The violet pale, the blushing red decays,</l>
     <l n="147" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' now no painted cloud reflect the light,</l>
     <l n="148" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor drops prismatic break the falling rays,</l>
     <l n="149" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Yet still the colours live, tho' none appear,</l>
     <l n="150" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Glow in the darting beam that gilds yon crystal sphere.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="151" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Then let not  with her vagrant blaze</l>
     <l n="152" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Mislead in trackless paths of wild deceit;</l>
     <l n="153" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">On Reason's steady lamp still ardent gaze;</l>
     <l n="154" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Led by her sober light to Truth's retreat.</l>
     <l n="155" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' wond'ring Ign'rance sees each form decay,</l>
     <l n="156" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The breathless bird, bare trunk, and shrivel'd flow'r:</l>
     <l n="157" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">New forms successive catch the vital ray,</l>
     <l n="158" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Sing their wild notes, or smile th' allotted hour,</l>
     <l n="159" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And search creation's ample circuit round,</l>
     <l n="160" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' modes of being change, all life's immortal found.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="161" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">See the slow reptile grov'ling o'er the green,</l>
     <l n="162" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">That trails thro' slimy paths its cumbrous load,</l>
     <l n="163" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Start in new beauty from the lowly scene,</l>
     <l n="164" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And wing with flutt'ring pride th' aetherial road;</l>
     <l n="165" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Burst their shell-prisons, see the feather'd kind,</l>
     <l n="166" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Where in dark durance pent awhile they lie,</l>
     <l n="167" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Dispread their painted plumage to the wind,</l>
     <l n="168" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Brush the brisk air, swift shooting thro' the sky,</l>
     <l n="169" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Hail with their choral hymns the new-born day,</l>
     <l n="170" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Distend their joy-swoln breasts, and carol the sweet lay.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="171" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">See man by varied periods fixt by fate</l>
     <l n="172" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Ascend perfection's scale by slow degree;</l>
     <l n="173" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The plant-like foetus quits its senseless taste,</l>
     <l n="174" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And helpless hangs sweet-smiling on the knee;</l>
     <l n="175" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Soon outward objects steal into the brain,</l>
     <l n="176" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Next prattling childhood lisps with mimic air,</l>
     <l n="177" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Then mem'ry links her fleet ideal train,</l>
     <l n="178" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And sober reason rises to compare,</l>
     <l n="179" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The full-grown breast some manly passion warms,</l>
     <l n="180" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">It pants for glory's meed, or beats to love's alarms.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="181" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Then say, since nature's high behest appears</l>
     <l n="182" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">That living forms should change of being prove,</l>
     <l n="183" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">In which new joy the novel scene endears,</l>
     <l n="184" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">New objects rise to please, new wings to move;</l>
     <l n="185" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Since man too, taught by sage experience, knows</l>
     <l n="186" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">His frame revolving treads life's varying stage,</l>
     <l n="187" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">That the man-plant first vegetating grows,</l>
     <l n="188" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Then sense directs, then reason rules in age;</l>
     <l n="189" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Say, is it strange, should death's all-dreaded hour</l>
     <l n="190" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Waft to some unknown scenes, or wake some-untried pow'r?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="20" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="191" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The wise Creator wrapt in fleshly veil</l>
     <l n="192" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The ray divine, the pure aetherial mate;</l>
     <l n="193" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' worn by age the brittle fabric fail,</l>
     <l n="194" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The smiling soul survives the frowns of fate:</l>
     <l n="195" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Each circling year, each quick-revolving day</l>
     <l n="196" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Touches with mould'ring tooth thy flitting frame,</l>
     <l n="197" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">With furtive slight repairs th' unseen decay;</l>
     <l n="198" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">For ever changing, yet in change the same,</l>
     <l n="199" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Oft hast thou dropt unhurt thy mortal part,</l>
     <l n="200" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Dare the grim terror then, nor dread his guiltless dart.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="21" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="201" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The twinkling eye, whose various-humour'd round</l>
     <l n="202" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Takes in soft net th' inverted form behind,</l>
     <l n="203" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The list'ning ears, that catch the waving sound,</l>
     <l n="204" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Are but mere organs of the feeling mind:</l>
     <l n="205" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">External matter thus can lend its aid,</l>
     <l n="206" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And distant shapes with foreign pow'r supply;</l>
     <l n="207" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thus the long tube by  made</l>
     <l n="208" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Brings home the wonders of the peopled sky:</l>
     <l n="209" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The pow'r percipient then feels no decay,</l>
     <l n="210" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' blind the tube, and darkness blot the visual ray.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="22" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="211" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">When lock'd in short suspence by sleep's soft pow'r</l>
     <l n="212" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">In temporary death the senses lie,</l>
     <l n="213" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">When solemn silence reigns at midnight hour,</l>
     <l n="214" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Deaf the dull ear, and clos'd the curtain'd eye;</l>
     <l n="215" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Objects of sense, each conscious sense asleep,</l>
     <l n="216" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">With lively image strike the wakeful soul,</l>
     <l n="217" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Some frowning rock that threats the foaming deep,</l>
     <l n="218" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Or wood-hung vale, where streams meand'ring roll,</l>
     <l n="219" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Some long-lost friend's returning voice you hear,</l>
     <l n="220" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Clasp the life-pictur'd shade, and drop the pleasing tear.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="23" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="221" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Each outward organ, as ideas rise,</l>
     <l n="222" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Gives easy entrance to the motley train;</l>
     <l n="223" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">calm, with retrospective eyes</l>
     <l n="224" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Surveys her treasures in the formful brain;</l>
     <l n="225" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' Death relentless shed his baleful dew,</l>
     <l n="226" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">In Lethe dip each form-conveying pow'r,</l>
     <l n="227" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Unhurt Reflection may her themes pursue,</l>
     <l n="228" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Smile at the ruin, safe amidst her store;</l>
     <l n="229" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Without one sense's aid in life's low vale,</l>
     <l n="230" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Fancy can furnish joys, and reason lift her scale.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="24" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="231" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thus the lone lover in the pensive shade</l>
     <l n="232" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">In day-dreams rapt of soft ecstatic bliss,</l>
     <l n="233" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Pursues in thought the visionary maid,</l>
     <l n="234" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Feasts on the fancy'd smile, and favour'd kiss:</l>
     <l n="235" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thus the young poet at the close of day</l>
     <l n="236" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Led by the magic of some fairy song</l>
     <l n="237" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thro' the dun umbrage winds his heedless way,</l>
     <l n="238" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor hears the babbling brook that brawls along:</l>
     <l n="239" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thus deathless  deaf to nature's cries</l>
     <l n="240" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Would measure  and  and travel 'round the skies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="25" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="241" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">When just expiring hangs life's trembling light,</l>
     <l n="242" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And fell disease strikes deep the deadly dart,</l>
     <l n="243" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Reason and mem'ry burn with ardour bright,</l>
     <l n="244" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And gen'rous passions warm the throbbing heart;</l>
     <l n="245" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Oft will the vig'rous soul in life's last stage</l>
     <l n="246" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">With keenest relish taste pure mental joys:</l>
     <l n="247" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Since the fierce efforts of distemper's rage</l>
     <l n="248" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor 'bates her vigour, nor her pow'rs destroys,</l>
     <l n="249" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Say, shall her lustre death itself impair?</l>
     <l n="250" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">When in high noon she rides, then sets in dark despair?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="26" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="251" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' through the heart no purple tide should flow,</l>
     <l n="252" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">No quiv'ring nerve should vibrate to the brain,</l>
     <l n="253" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The mental pow'rs no mean dependence know;</l>
     <l n="254" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thought may survive, and each fair passion reign;</l>
     <l n="255" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">As when  ends the pangful strife,</l>
     <l n="256" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Lifts the young babe, and lights her lambent flame,</l>
     <l n="257" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Some pow'rs new-waking hail the dawning life,</l>
     <l n="258" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Some unsuspended live, unchang'd, the same;</l>
     <l n="259" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">So from our dust fresh faculties may bloom,</l>
     <l n="260" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Some posthumous survive, and triumph o'er the tomb.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="27" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="261" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">This fibrous frame by nature's kindly law,</l>
     <l n="262" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Which gives each joy to keen sensation here,</l>
     <l n="263" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">O'er purer scenes of bliss the veil may draw,</l>
     <l n="264" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And cloud reflection's more exalted sphere.</l>
     <l n="265" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">When Death's cold hand with all-dissolving pow'r</l>
     <l n="266" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Shall the close tie with friendly stroke unbind,</l>
     <l n="267" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Alike our mortal as our natal hour</l>
     <l n="268" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">May to new being raise the waking mind:</l>
     <l n="269" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">On death's new genial day the soul may rise,</l>
     <l n="270" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Born to some higher life, and hail some brighter skies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="28" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="271" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The moss-grown tree, that shrinks with rolling years,</l>
     <l n="272" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The drooping flow'rs that die so soon away,</l>
     <l n="273" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Let not thy heart alarm with boding fears,</l>
     <l n="274" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor thy own ruin date from their decay:</l>
     <l n="275" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The blushing rose that breathes the balmy dew,</l>
     <l n="276" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">No pleasing transports of perception knows,</l>
     <l n="277" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The rev'rend oak, that circling springs renew,</l>
     <l n="278" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thinks not, nor by long age experienc'd grows;</l>
     <l n="279" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Thy fate and theirs confess no kindred tie:</l>
     <l n="280" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Tho' their frail forms may fade, shall sense and reason die?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="29" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="281" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nor let life's ills, that in dire circle rage,</l>
     <l n="282" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Steal from thy heaving breast those labour'd sighs;</l>
     <l n="283" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">These, the kind tutors of thy infant age,</l>
     <l n="284" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Train the young pupil for the future skies:</l>
     <l n="285" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Unschool'd in early prime, in riper years</l>
     <l n="286" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Wretched and scorn'd still struts the bearded boy;</l>
     <l n="287" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The tingling rod bedew'd with briny tears</l>
     <l n="288" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Shoots forth in graceful fruits of manly joy:</l>
     <l n="289" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The painful cares that vex the toilsome spring</l>
     <l n="290" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Shall plenteous crops of bliss in life's last harvest bring.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="30" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="291" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">She ceas'd, and vanish'd into sightless wind —</l>
     <l n="292" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">O'er my torn breast alternate passions sway,</l>
     <l n="293" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Now Doubt desponding damps the wav'ring mind,</l>
     <l n="294" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Now Hope reviving sheds her cheerful ray.</l>
     <l n="295" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Soon from the skies in heav'nly white array'd,</l>
     <l n="296" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">to my sight reveal'd, fair Cherub! stood,</l>
     <l n="297" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">With life replete the volume she display'd,</l>
     <l n="298" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Seal'd with the ruddy stains of crimson blood;</l>
     <l n="299" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Each fear now starts away, as spectres fly</l>
     <l n="300" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">When the sun's orient beam first gilds the purple sky.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="31" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="301" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Mean while the faithful herald of the day</l>
     <l n="302" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The village cock crows loud with trumpet shrill,</l>
     <l n="303" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The warbling lark soars high, and morning grey</l>
     <l n="304" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Lifts her glad forehead o'er the cloud-wrapt hill:</l>
     <l n="305" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Nature's wild music fills the vocal vale;</l>
     <l n="306" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The bleating flocks that bite the dewy ground,</l>
     <l n="307" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">The lowing herds that graze the woodland dale,</l>
     <l n="308" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">And cavern'd echo, swell the cheerful sound;</l>
     <l n="309" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Homeward I bend with clear unclouded mind,</l>
     <l n="310" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+|-+">Mix with the busy world, and leave each care behind.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>