<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The Wood-Pile</title>
    <author>Robert Frost</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">1</measure>
    <measure unit="line">40</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Robert Frost_the-wood-pile</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>For Better For Verse</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>The Wood-Pile</title>
     <author>Robert Frost</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>The Wood-Pile</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="blank verse">
     <l n="1" met="-+---+-+--+">Out walking in the frozen swamp one gray day,</l>
     <l n="2" met="-+-++--+-+">I paused and said, "I will turn back from here.</l>
     <l n="3" met="+--+-+--+-+">No, I will go on farther--and we shall see."</l>
     <l n="4" met="-+++-+-+-+">The hard snow held me, save where now and then</l>
     <l n="5" met="++---+-+-+">One foot went through. The view was all in lines</l>
     <l n="6" met="++-+-+++">Straight up and down of tall slim trees</l>
     <l n="7" met="-+-+-+-+-+-|+--+-+-+-+-">Too much alike to mark or name a place by</l>
     <l n="8" met="+--+-+-+-+">So as to say for certain I was here</l>
     <l n="9" met="-+-++--+-+|-+-+--++-+">Or somewhere else: I was just far from home.</l>
     <l n="10" met="-+++-+---+-">A small bird flew before me. He was careful</l>
     <l n="11" met="-+-+-+-+-+-">To put a tree between us when he lighted,</l>
     <l n="12" met="-+++-+---+|-+++-+-+-+">And say no word to tell me who he was</l>
     <l n="13" met="--++-+-+-+-|+-++---+-+-">Who was so foolish as to think what he thought.</l>
     <l n="14" met="+--+-+--+-+-|-+-+-+--+-+-">He thought that I was after him for a feather--</l>
     <l n="15" met="-+-+-+-+-+">The white one in his tail; like one who takes</l>
     <l n="16" met="+--+-+--+-+">Everything said as personal to himself.</l>
     <l n="17" met="++-+---+-+-">One flight out sideways would have undeceived him.</l>
     <l n="18" met="-+-+-+-+-+">And then there was a pile of wood for which</l>
     <l n="19" met="+-+--+-+-+">I forgot him and let his little fear</l>
     <l n="20" met="+--+-+-+-+">Carry him off the way I might have gone,</l>
     <l n="21" met="-+-+-+-+-+">Without so much as wishing him good-night.</l>
     <l n="22" met="-+-+--+-++">He went behind it to make his last stand.</l>
     <l n="23" met="+--+-+-+-+">It was a cord of maple, cut and split</l>
     <l n="24" met="-+-+-+-+-+">And piled--and measured, four by four by eight.</l>
     <l n="25" met="-+-+-+-+-+">And not another like it could I see.</l>
     <l n="26" met="-+-+-+-+++-">No runner tracks in this year's snow looped near it.</l>
     <l n="27" met="-+-+-+-+-+-">And it was older sure than this year's cutting,</l>
     <l n="28" met="-+-++--+-+">Or even last year's or the year's before.</l>
     <l n="29" met="-+-+--++-+-">The wood was gray and the bark warping off it</l>
     <l n="30" met="--++-+-+-+">And the pile somewhat sunken. Clematis</l>
     <l n="31" met="-+++-+---+-">Had wound strings round and round it like a bundle.</l>
     <l n="32" met="-+-+-++--+">What held it though on one side was a tree</l>
     <l n="33" met="++---+-+-+">Still growing, and on one a stake and prop,</l>
     <l n="34" met="-+--+-+-+-+-">These latter about to fall. I thought that only</l>
     <l n="35" met="+--+-+--++">Someone who lived in turning to fresh tasks</l>
     <l n="36" met="-+-+-+-+-+">Could so forget his handiwork on which</l>
     <l n="37" met="-+-+-+-+-+">He spent himself, the labor of his ax,</l>
     <l n="38" met="-+-++--+-+--">And leave it there far from a useful fireplace</l>
     <l n="39" met="-+-+-+-+-+">To warm the frozen swamp as best it could</l>
     <l n="40" met="--++-+-+-+">With the slow smokeless burning of decay.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>