<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>VERSES Humbly presented to the KING At His Arrival in HOLLAND: After the DISCOVERY Of the late horrid CONSPIRACY Against His most Sacred Person.</title>
    <author>Matthew Prior</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">10</measure>
    <measure unit="line">78</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Matthew Prior_verses-humbly-presented-to-the</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>VERSES Humbly presented to the KING At His Arrival in HOLLAND: After the DISCOVERY Of the late horrid CONSPIRACY Against His most Sacred Person.</title>
     <author>Matthew Prior</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>VERSES Humbly presented to the KING At His Arrival in HOLLAND: After the DISCOVERY Of the late horrid CONSPIRACY Against His most Sacred Person.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="1">YE careful Angels whom eternal Fate</l>
     <l n="2">Ordains on Earth and humane Acts to wait;</l>
     <l n="3">Who turn with secret Power this restless Ball;</l>
     <l n="4">And bid determin'd Empires rise and fall:</l>
     <l n="5">Your sacred Aid religious Princes own</l>
     <l n="6">When first they merit, then ascend the Throne:</l>
     <l n="7">But Tyrants dread you, lest your just Decree</l>
     <l n="8">Transfer the Power, and set the People free.</l>
     <l n="9">See rescu'd BRITAIN, at your Altars bow,</l>
     <l n="10">And hear her hymns your happy care avow.</l>
     <l n="11">That yet her Axes and her Rods support</l>
     <l n="12">Her Judges hand, and grace her awful Court,</l>
     <l n="13">Where Law with all her pompous terrour stands</l>
     <l n="14">To wrest the Dagger from the Traitours hands,</l>
     <l n="15">Where rigid Justice reads the fatal Word,</l>
     <l n="16">Poises the Ballance first, then draws the Sword.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="17">To your blest guidance She her safety owns,</l>
     <l n="18">That she can sep'rate Parricides from Sons,</l>
     <l n="19">And boldly give those Criminals their doom,</l>
     <l n="20">Who would, like  rip their Parents womb:</l>
     <l n="21">That, Death and Hell disarm'd, She lives and reigns,</l>
     <l n="22">Her freedom Kept by Him who broke her chains.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="23">And thou, blest Guardian, destin'd to defend</l>
     <l n="24">That Sacred Life on which all ours depend:</l>
     <l n="25">Thou sure, whose charge of old was  Court,</l>
     <l n="26">When sent from Heav'n great  strong support,</l>
     <l n="27">Thy arm unseen eluded cruel</l>
     <l n="28">And struck the useless Javelin to the Wall.</l>
     <l n="29">Thy later care o'er WILLIAM'S Temples held</l>
     <l n="30">On  propitious Banks the heav'nly Shield,</l>
     <l n="31">When EUROPE pale betwixt two Armies stood,</l>
     <l n="32">And trembling BRITAIN doubted to be good,</l>
     <l n="33">Till Miracles did WILLIAM'S right declare,</l>
     <l n="34">And Cannons mark't whom they were bid to spare.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="35">Still, blessed Angel, be thy care the same,</l>
     <l n="36">Be WILLIAM'S Life untouch'd as is his Fame:</l>
     <l n="37">Let Him own Thine as BRITAIN owns his Hand;</l>
     <l n="38">And save the King, as He has sav'd the Land.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="39">We Angels forms in pious Monarchs view,</l>
     <l n="40">We reverence WILLIAM, for He acts like You;</l>
     <l n="41">Like You commission'd to chastize and bless,</l>
     <l n="42">He must avenge the World, and give it Peace.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="43">Our Prayers are heard, new Miracles are shown,</l>
     <l n="44">The Powers that rescu'd will preserve the Throne:</l>
     <l n="45">The Hero dear to Earth, by Heav'n belov'd,</l>
     <l n="46">By troubles must be vex't, by dangers prov'd;</l>
     <l n="47">His Foes must contribute to make Him great,</l>
     <l n="48">And fix his Glory sure on their defeat.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="49">So tho' with sudden rage the Tempest comes,</l>
     <l n="50">Tho' the Winds roar, and tho' the Water foams,</l>
     <l n="51">Fair BRITAIN on the angry Sea looks down,</l>
     <l n="52">And smiling sees Her Rebel Subject frown;</l>
     <l n="53">Heav'n in assaulting Her confirms her power,</l>
     <l n="54">The Waves but whiten Her triumphant Shore;</l>
     <l n="55">In vain they would advance, in vain retreat,</l>
     <l n="56">Broken they dash and perish at Her feet.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="57">'Tis done, once more thro' BRITAIN's joyful Sea</l>
     <l n="58">Her glorious Monarch plows his Prosp'rous way,</l>
     <l n="59">Arm'd with those Fleets who have in thunder said</l>
     <l n="60">To distant Worlds, whose Empire they obey'd:</l>
     <l n="61">He lands, and sees united Nations stand,</l>
     <l n="62">Their parts of Glory dealt by His command,</l>
     <l n="63">Their glowing Brests with fresh Ideas fir'd,</l>
     <l n="64">How WILLIAM conquer'd, and how FRANCE retir'd,</l>
     <l n="65">When fixt as Fate he stood in  Field,</l>
     <l n="66">Till Rocks and Floods and Fire were taught to yield,</l>
     <l n="67">Till  freed the Hero's arm confest,</l>
     <l n="68">But trembled for the Courage which she blest.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="69">He comes; pale GALLIA dreads his Arms a-far,</l>
     <l n="70">And bent on Parricide refuses War,</l>
     <l n="71">But 'well she knows his Vengeance n'er will tread</l>
     <l n="72">Those Paths of horrour which her guilt has led.</l>
     <l n="73">The Trumpets Sounds shall tell the arming Foe</l>
     <l n="74">When WILLIAM meditates the noble Blow,</l>
     <l n="75">Before the foremost Troops in open fight</l>
     <l n="76">The Hero's arm shall prove the Monarchs right.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="77">'Tis done, and EUROPE freed must own his hand,</l>
     <l n="78">Whilst THAMES shall flow, or BRITAINS Empire stand.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>