<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Presented to the KING, AT HIS ARRIVAL in HOLLAND, AFTER THE Discovery of the Conspiracy 1696.</title>
    <author>Matthew Prior</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">10</measure>
    <measure unit="line">83</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Matthew Prior_presented-to-the-king-at-his-a</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>Presented to the KING, AT HIS ARRIVAL in HOLLAND, AFTER THE Discovery of the Conspiracy 1696.</title>
     <author>Matthew Prior</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>Presented to the KING, AT HIS ARRIVAL in HOLLAND, AFTER THE Discovery of the Conspiracy 1696.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="1">careful Angels, whom eternal Fate</l>
     <l n="2">Ordains, on Earth and human Acts to wait;</l>
     <l n="3">Who turn with secret Pow'r this restless Ball,</l>
     <l n="4">And bid predestin'd Empires rise and fall:</l>
     <l n="5">Your sacred Aid religious Monarchs own;</l>
     <l n="6">When first They merit, then ascend the Throne:</l>
     <l n="7">But Tyrants dread Ye, lest your just Decree</l>
     <l n="8">Transfer the Pow'r, and set the People free:</l>
     <l n="9">See rescu'd  at your Altars bow:</l>
     <l n="10">And hear her Hymns your happy Care avow:</l>
     <l n="11">That still her Axes and her Rods support</l>
     <l n="12">The Judge's Frown, and grace the awful Court:</l>
     <l n="13">That Law with all her pompous Terror stands,</l>
     <l n="14">To wrest the Dagger from the Traitor's Hands;</l>
     <l n="15">And rigid Justice reads the fatal Word;</l>
     <l n="16">Poises the Ballance first, then draws the Sword.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="17">Her Safety to your Guidance owns,</l>
     <l n="18">That She can sep'rate Parricides from Sons;</l>
     <l n="19">That, impious Rage disarm'd, She lives and Reigns,</l>
     <l n="20">Her Freedom kept by Him, who broke Her Chains.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="21">And Thou, great Minister, above the rest</l>
     <l n="22">Of Guardian Spirits, be Thou for ever blest:</l>
     <l n="23">Thou, who of old wert sent to  Court,</l>
     <l n="24">With secret Aid great  strong Support;</l>
     <l n="25">To mock the frantick Rage of cruel ;</l>
     <l n="26">And strike the useless Jav'lin to the Wall.</l>
     <l n="27">Thy later Care o'er  Temples held,</l>
     <l n="28">On  propitious Banks, the heav'nly Shield;</l>
     <l n="29">When Pow'r Divine did Sov'reign Right declare;</l>
     <l n="30">And Cannons mark'd, Whom They were bid to spare.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="31">Still, blessed Angel, be thy Care the same;</l>
     <l n="32">Be  Life untouch'd, as is his Fame:</l>
     <l n="33">Let Him own Thine, as  owns His Hand:</l>
     <l n="34">Save Thou the King, as He has sav'd the Land.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="35">We Angels Forms in pious Monarchs view:</l>
     <l n="36">We reverence ; for He acts like You;</l>
     <l n="37">Like You, Commission'd to chastize and bless,</l>
     <l n="38">He must avenge the World, and give it Peace.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="39">Indulgent Fate our potent Pray'r receives;</l>
     <l n="40">And still  smiles, and  lives:</l>
     <l n="41">The Hero dear to Earth, by Heav'n belov'd,</l>
     <l n="42">By Troubles must be vex'd, by Dangers prov'd:</l>
     <l n="43">His Foes must aid to make his Fame compleat,</l>
     <l n="44">And fix his Throne secure on their Defeat.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="45">So, tho' with sudden Rage the Tempest comes;</l>
     <l n="46">Tho' the Winds roar; and tho' the Water foams;</l>
     <l n="47">Imperial  on the Sea looks down,</l>
     <l n="48">And smiling sees her Rebel Subject frown:</l>
     <l n="49">Striking her Cliff the Storm confirms her Pow'r:</l>
     <l n="50">The Waves but whiten her Triumphant Shore:</l>
     <l n="51">In vain They wou'd advance, in vain retreat:</l>
     <l n="52">Broken They dash, and perish at her Feet.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="53">For  still new Wonders shall be shown:</l>
     <l n="54">The Pow'rs that rescu'd, shall preserve the Throne.</l>
     <l n="55">Safe on his Darling  joyful Sea,</l>
     <l n="56">Behold, the Monarch plows his liquid Way:</l>
     <l n="57">His Fleets in Thunder thro' the World declare,</l>
     <l n="58">Whose Empire they obey, whose Arms they bear.</l>
     <l n="59">Bless'd by aspiring Winds He finds the Strand</l>
     <l n="60">Blacken'd with Crowds; He sees the Nations stand</l>
     <l n="61">Blessing his Safety, proud of his Command.</l>
     <l n="62">In various Tongues He hears the Captains dwell</l>
     <l n="63">On their great Leader's Praise: by Turns They tell,</l>
     <l n="64">And listen, each with emulous Glory fir'd,</l>
     <l n="65">How  conquer'd, and how  retir'd;</l>
     <l n="66">How  freed the Hero's Arm confess'd,</l>
     <l n="67">But trembl'd for the Courage which She blest.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="68">, from this great Example know,</l>
     <l n="69">To be at once a Hero, and a Foe:</l>
     <l n="70">By sounding Trumpets, Hear, and ratl'ing Drums,</l>
     <l n="71">When  to the open Vengeance comes:</l>
     <l n="72">And See the Soldier plead the Monarch's Right,</l>
     <l n="73">Heading His Troops, and Foremost in the Fight.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="74">Hence then, close Ambush and perfidious War,</l>
     <l n="75">Down to your Native Seats of Night repair.</l>
     <l n="76">And Thou, , weep thy cruel Pride</l>
     <l n="77">Restrain'd, behind the Victor's Chariot ty'd</l>
     <l n="78">In brazen Knots, and everlasting Chains.</l>
     <l n="79">(So  Peace, so  Fate ordains.)</l>
     <l n="80">While on the Iv'ry Chair, in happy State</l>
     <l n="81">He sits, Secure in Innocence, and Great</l>
     <l n="82">In regal Clemency; and views beneath</l>
     <l n="83">Averted Darts of Rage, and pointless Arms of Death.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>