<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>AN ODE, &amp;c.</title>
    <author>Matthew Prior</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">13</measure>
    <measure unit="line">276</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Matthew Prior_an-ode-c</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>AN ODE, &amp;c.</title>
     <author>Matthew Prior</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>AN ODE, &amp;c.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">HOW long, deluded  wilt Thou lie</l>
     <l n="2">In the Lethargic Sleep, the sad Repose,</l>
     <l n="3">By which thy close, thy constant Enemy,</l>
     <l n="4">Has softly lull'd Thee to Thy Woes?</l>
     <l n="5">Or Wake, degenerate Isle, or Cease to own</l>
     <l n="6">What Thy Old Kings in  Camps have done;</l>
     <l n="7">The Spoils They brought Thee back, the Crowns They won.</l>
     <l n="8">(so Fate requires) again is Arm'd;</l>
     <l n="9">Thy Father to the Field is gone:</l>
     <l n="10">Again  Weeps Her absent Lord;</l>
     <l n="11">For Thy Repose content to Rule alone.</l>
     <l n="12">Are Thy Enervate Sons not yet Alarm'd?</l>
     <l n="13">When  Fights, dare they look tamely on,</l>
     <l n="14">So slow to get their Ancient Fame Restor'd,</l>
     <l n="15">As nor to melt at Beauties Tears, nor follow Valours Sword?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="16">See the Repenting Isle Awakes,</l>
     <l n="17">Her Vicious Chains the generous Goddess breaks:</l>
     <l n="18">The Foggs around Her Temples are Dispell'd;</l>
     <l n="19">Abroad She Looks, and Sees Arm'd  stand</l>
     <l n="20">Prepar'd to meet their common Lords Command;</l>
     <l n="21">Her Lions Roaring by Her Side, Her Arrows in Her Hand;</l>
     <l n="22">And Blushing to have been so long withheld,</l>
     <l n="23">Weeps off Her Crime, and hastens to the Field:</l>
     <l n="24">Henceforth Her Youth shall be inur'd to bear</l>
     <l n="25">Hazardous Toil and Active War:</l>
     <l n="26">To march beneath the Dog-Stars raging Heat,</l>
     <l n="27">Patient of Summers Drought, and Martial Sweat.</l>
     <l n="28">And only Grieve in Winters Camps to find,</l>
     <l n="29">Its Days too short for Labours They design'd:</l>
     <l n="30">All Night beneath hard heavy Arms to Watch;</l>
     <l n="31">All Day to Mount the Trench, to Storm the Breach;</l>
     <l n="32">And all the rugged Paths to tread,</l>
     <l n="33">Where  and His Virtue lead.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="34">Silence is the Soul of War;</l>
     <l n="35">Deliberate Counsel must prepare</l>
     <l n="36">The Mighty Work, which Valour must compleat:</l>
     <l n="37">Thus  Rescued, thus Preserves the State;</l>
     <l n="38">Thus Teaches Us to Think and Dare;</l>
     <l n="39">As whilst his Cannon just prepar'd to Breath</l>
     <l n="40">Avenging Anger and swift Death,</l>
     <l n="41">In the try'd Mettle the close Dangers glow,</l>
     <l n="42">And now too late the Dying Foe</l>
     <l n="43">Perceives the Flame, yet cannot ward the Blow;</l>
     <l n="44">So whilst in  Breast ripe Counsels lie,</l>
     <l n="45">Secret and sure as Brooding Fate,</l>
     <l n="46">No more of His Design appears</l>
     <l n="47">Than what Awakens  Fears;</l>
     <l n="48">And (though Guilts Eye can sharply penetrate)</l>
     <l n="49">Distracted  can discry</l>
     <l n="50">Only a long unmeasur'd Ruine nigh.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="51">On  Coasts and Banks of frighted</l>
     <l n="52">Lo! the Impending Storms begin:</l>
     <l n="53">safely through her Masters Sea</l>
     <l n="54">Plows up her Victorious Way.</l>
     <l n="55">The  throws his Bolts in vain,</l>
     <l n="56">Whilst the true Thunderer asserts the Main:</l>
     <l n="57">'Tis done! to Shelves and Rocks his Fleets retire,</l>
     <l n="58">Swift Victory in Vengeful Flames</l>
     <l n="59">Burns down the Pride of their Presumptuous Names:</l>
     <l n="60">They run to Shipwrack to avoid our Fire,</l>
     <l n="61">And the torn Vessels that regain their Coast</l>
     <l n="62">Are but sad Marks to shew the rest are lost:</l>
     <l n="63">All this the Mild, the Beauteous, Queen has done,</l>
     <l n="64">And  softer half shakes Throne:</l>
     <l n="65">does the Sea command</l>
     <l n="66">Whilst  flies her Husband's Arms by Land,</l>
     <l n="67">So, the Sun absent, with full sway, the Moon</l>
     <l n="68">Governs the Isles, and rules the Waves alone;</l>
     <l n="69">So  thunders when her  is gone.</l>
     <l n="70">loose thy Oceans Chains</l>
     <l n="71">Whilst  strikes the Blow Thy Queen ordains:</l>
     <l n="72">Thus Rescued, thus Rever'd, for ever stand,</l>
     <l n="73">And bless the Counsel, and Reward the Hand,</l>
     <l n="74">thy  Reigns.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="75">From  Conquests, and the Rescued Main,</l>
     <l n="76">Let  look forth to  armed Shore,</l>
     <l n="77">And boast her Joy for  Death no more.</l>
     <l n="78">He lives, let  confess, the Victor lives:</l>
     <l n="79">Her Triumphs for his Death were vain,</l>
     <l n="80">And spoke her Terrour of his Life too plain.</l>
     <l n="81">The mighty years begin, the day draws nigh,</l>
     <l n="82">In which  of many Wives,</l>
     <l n="83">Who by the baleful force of guilty Charms,</l>
     <l n="84">Has long enthraul'd Him in Her wither'd Arms,</l>
     <l n="85">Shall o're the Plains from distant Towers on high</l>
     <l n="86">Cast a-round her mournful Eye,</l>
     <l n="87">And with Prophetick Sorrow cry:</l>
     <l n="88">Why does my ruin'd Lord retard his flight?</l>
     <l n="89">Why does despair provoke his Age to fight?</l>
     <l n="90">As well the Wolf may venture to engage</l>
     <l n="91">The angry Lyons generous rage;</l>
     <l n="92">The ravenous Vultur, and the Bird of Night,</l>
     <l n="93">As safely tempt the stooping Eagles flight,</l>
     <l n="94">As  to unequal Arms defy</l>
     <l n="95">Yon' Heroe, crown'd with blooming Victory</l>
     <l n="96">Just triumphing o're Rebel rage restrain'd,</l>
     <l n="97">And yet unbreath'd from Battels gain'd.</l>
     <l n="98">See! all yon' dusty Fields quite cover'd o're</l>
     <l n="99">With Hostil Troops, and  at their Head,</l>
     <l n="100">destin'd to compleat</l>
     <l n="101">The great Designs of labouring Fate,</l>
     <l n="102">the Name that Tyrants Dread:</l>
     <l n="103">He comes, our ruin'd Empire is no more,</l>
     <l n="104">Down, like the  goes the  Throne,</l>
     <l n="105">flies, young  urges on.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="106">Now from the dubious Battel's mingled heat</l>
     <l n="107">Let Fear look back, and stretch her hasty Wing,</l>
     <l n="108">Impatient to secure a base retreat:</l>
     <l n="109">Let the pale Coward leave his Wounded King,</l>
     <l n="110">For the vile privilege to breath,</l>
     <l n="111">To live with shame in dread of glorious Death.</l>
     <l n="112">In vain: for Fate has swifter Wings than fear,</l>
     <l n="113">She follows hard, and strikes Him in the rear,</l>
     <l n="114">Dying and Mad the Traytor bites the ground,</l>
     <l n="115">His Back transfix'd with a Dishonest Wound;</l>
     <l n="116">Whilst through the fiercest Troops, and thickest Press,</l>
     <l n="117">Virtue carries on Success;</l>
     <l n="118">Whilst equal Heaven guards the distinguisht brave,</l>
     <l n="119">And Armies cannot hurt whom Angels save.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="120">Virtue to Verse immortal Lustre gives,</l>
     <l n="121">Each by the other's mutual Friendship lives;</l>
     <l n="122">suffer'd, and  fought,</l>
     <l n="123">The Heroes acts enlarg'd the Poets thought,</l>
     <l n="124">Or  Majesty, and  Rage</l>
     <l n="125">Had ne're like lasting Nature vanquish'd Age;</l>
     <l n="126">Whilst  then his rising Terrour drowns</l>
     <l n="127">With Drums Alarms and Trumpets Sounds,</l>
     <l n="128">Whilst hid in arm'd Retreats and guarded Towns,</l>
     <l n="129">From Danger as from Honour far,</l>
     <l n="130">He bribes close Murder against open War:</l>
     <l n="131">In vain you  Muses strive</l>
     <l n="132">With labour'd Verse to keep his Fame alive,</l>
     <l n="133">Your mouldring Monuments in vain ye raise</l>
     <l n="134">On the weak Basis of the Tyrants Praise:</l>
     <l n="135">Your Songs are sold, your Numbers are Prophane,</l>
     <l n="136">'Tis Incense to an Idol given,</l>
     <l n="137">Meat offer'd to Man,</l>
     <l n="138">That had no Soul from Heaven.</l>
     <l n="139">Against his Will you chain your frighted King</l>
     <l n="140">On rapid  divided Bed;</l>
     <l n="141">And Mock your Heroe, whilst ye Sing</l>
     <l n="142">The Wounds for which he never bled;</l>
     <l n="143">Falshood does poyson on your Praise defuse,</l>
     <l n="144">And  fear gives Death to  Muse.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="145">On it's own Worth True Majesty is rear'd,</l>
     <l n="146">And Virtue is her own Reward,</l>
     <l n="147">With solid Beams and Native Glory bright,</l>
     <l n="148">She neither Darkness dreads, nor covets Light;</l>
     <l n="149">True to Her self, and fix't to inborn Laws,</l>
     <l n="150">Nor sunk by spight, nor lifted by Applause,</l>
     <l n="151">She from Her settled Orb looks calmly down,</l>
     <l n="152">On Life or Death, a Prison or a Crown.</l>
     <l n="153">When bound in double Chains poor  lay</l>
     <l n="154">To foreign Arms, and inward strife a Prey,</l>
     <l n="155">Whilst One Good Man buoy'd up Her sinking State,</l>
     <l n="156">And Virtue labour'd against Fate;</l>
     <l n="157">When fortune basely with ambition joyn'd,</l>
     <l n="158">And all was conquer'd but the  mind,</l>
     <l n="159">When Storms let loose, and raging Seas</l>
     <l n="160">Just ready the torn Vessel to o'rewhelm,</l>
     <l n="161">Forc'd not the faithful Pilot from his Helm,</l>
     <l n="162">Nor all the Syren Songs of future Peace,</l>
     <l n="163">And dazling Prospect of a promis'd Crown,</l>
     <l n="164">Could lure his stubborn Virtue down;</l>
     <l n="165">But against Charms, and Threats, and Hell, He stood,</l>
     <l n="166">To that which was severely good;</l>
     <l n="167">Then, had no Trophies justified his Fame,</l>
     <l n="168">No Poet blest his Song with  Name,</l>
     <l n="169">Virtue alone did all that Honour bring,</l>
     <l n="170">And Heaven as plainly pointed out</l>
     <l n="171">As when He at the Altar stood</l>
     <l n="172">In all his Types and Robes of Power,</l>
     <l n="173">Whilst at His Feet Religious  bow'd,</l>
     <l n="174">And own'd him next to what We there Adore.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="175">Say joyful  and  Victorious Flood,</l>
     <l n="176">(For each has mixt his Waves with Royal Blood)</l>
     <l n="177">When  Armies past, did He retire,</l>
     <l n="178">Or view from far the Battel's distant Fire?</l>
     <l n="179">Could He believe His Person was too dear?</l>
     <l n="180">Or use His Greatness to conceal His Fear?</l>
     <l n="181">Could Prayers or Sighs the dauntless Heroe move?</l>
     <l n="182">Arm'd with Heaven's Justice, and His People's Love,</l>
     <l n="183">Through the first Waves He wing'd His Vent'rous Way,</l>
     <l n="184">And on the Adverse Shore arose,</l>
     <l n="185">(Ten thousand flying Death's in vain oppose)</l>
     <l n="186">Like the great Ruler of the Day,</l>
     <l n="187">With Strength and Swiftness mounting from the Seas:</l>
     <l n="188">Like Him all Day He Toil'd, but long in Night</l>
     <l n="189">The God had eas'd His wearied light,</l>
     <l n="190">'Ere Vengeance left the stubborn Foes,</l>
     <l n="191">Or  Labours found repose.</l>
     <l n="192">When His Troops falter'd, stept not He between,</l>
     <l n="193">Restor'd the dubious Fight again,</l>
     <l n="194">Mark'd out the Coward that durst fly,</l>
     <l n="195">And led the fainting Brave to Victory?</l>
     <l n="196">Still as she fled Him, did He not o'ertake,</l>
     <l n="197">Her doubtful course, still brought Her Bleeding back?</l>
     <l n="198">By His keen Sword did not the Boldest fall?</l>
     <l n="199">Was He not King, Commander, Souldier, All —?</l>
     <l n="200">His Dangers such, as with becoming Dread,</l>
     <l n="201">His Subjects yet Un-Born shall Weep to Read;</l>
     <l n="202">And were not those the only Days that ere</l>
     <l n="203">The Pious Prince refus'd to hear</l>
     <l n="204">His Friends Advices, or His Subjects Prayer.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="205">Where e're old  his fruitful Water turns,</l>
     <l n="206">Or fills his Vassals Tributary Urns;</l>
     <l n="207">To  sav'd Dominions, and the Sea,</l>
     <l n="208">Whose righted Waves rejoice in  sway.</l>
     <l n="209">Is there a Town where Children are not Taught,</l>
     <l n="210">Here  Prosper'd, for here  Fought,</l>
     <l n="211">Through Rapid Waters, and through flying Fire:</l>
     <l n="212">Here rush'd the Prince, Here made whole  retire. —</l>
     <l n="213">By different Nations be this Valour blest,</l>
     <l n="214">In different Languages confest,</l>
     <l n="215">And then let  Speak the rest:</l>
     <l n="216">Let  Speak, how on her wond'ring Shore,</l>
     <l n="217">When Conquest hov'ring on his Arms did wait,</l>
     <l n="218">And only ask'd some Lives to Bribe her o're.</l>
     <l n="219">The God-like Man, the more than Conqueror,</l>
     <l n="220">With high Contempt sent back the specious Bait,</l>
     <l n="221">And Scorning Glory at a Price too great,</l>
     <l n="222">With so much Power such Piety did joyn,</l>
     <l n="223">As made a Perfect Virtue Soar</l>
     <l n="224">A Pitch unknown to Man before,</l>
     <l n="225">And lifted  Waves o'er those of</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="226">Nor do his Subjects only share</l>
     <l n="227">The Prosp'rous Fruits of His Indulgent Reign;</l>
     <l n="228">His Enemies approve the Pious War,</l>
     <l n="229">Which, with their Weapon, takes away their Chain:</l>
     <l n="230">More than His Sword, His Goodness strikes His Foes;</l>
     <l n="231">They Bless His Arms, and Sigh they must oppose.</l>
     <l n="232">Justice and Freedom on his Conquests wait,</l>
     <l n="233">And 'tis for Man's Delight that He is Great:</l>
     <l n="234">Succeeding Times shall with long Joy contend,</l>
     <l n="235">If He were more a Victor, or a Friend:</l>
     <l n="236">So much His Courage and His Mercy strive,</l>
     <l n="237">He Wounds, to Cure; and Conquers, to Forgive.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="238">Ye Heroes, that have Fought Your Countries Cause,</l>
     <l n="239">Redress'd Her Injuries, or Form'd Her Laws,</l>
     <l n="240">To my Advent'rous Song just Witness bear,</l>
     <l n="241">Assist the Pious Muse, and hear Her Swear,</l>
     <l n="242">That 'tis no Poet's Thought, no Flight of Youth,</l>
     <l n="243">But solid Story, and severest Truth,</l>
     <l n="244">That  Treasures up a greater Name,</l>
     <l n="245">Than any Country, any Age, can Boast:</l>
     <l n="246">And all that Ancient Stock of Fame</l>
     <l n="247">He did from His Fore-Fathers take,</l>
     <l n="248">He has improv'd, and gives with Interest back;</l>
     <l n="249">And in His Constellation does unite</l>
     <l n="250">Their scatter'd Rays of Fainter Light:</l>
     <l n="251">Above or Envy's lash, or Fortunes Wheel,</l>
     <l n="252">That settled Glory shall for ever dwell</l>
     <l n="253">Above the Rowling Orbs, and common Sky,</l>
     <l n="254">Where nothing comes that e're shall Die.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="255">Where Roves the Muse? Where thoughtless to return</l>
     <l n="256">Is her short liv'd Vessel Born,</l>
     <l n="257">By Potent Winds too subject to be tost?</l>
     <l n="258">And in the Sea of  Praises lost?</l>
     <l n="259">Nor let her tempt that Deep, nor make the Shore</l>
     <l n="260">Where our abandon'd Youth She sees</l>
     <l n="261">Shipwrackt in Luxury, and lost in Ease;</l>
     <l n="262">Whom nor  Danger can alarm,</l>
     <l n="263">Nor  Exemplary Virtue warm:</l>
     <l n="264">Tell 'em howe'er the King can yet Forgive</l>
     <l n="265">Their Guilty Sloath, their Homage yet Receive,</l>
     <l n="266">And let their wounded Honour live:</l>
     <l n="267">But sure and sudden be their just Remorse;</l>
     <l n="268">Swift be their Virtues rise, and strong its Course;</l>
     <l n="269">For though for certain Years and destin'd Times,</l>
     <l n="270">Merit has lain confus'd with Crimes;</l>
     <l n="271">Though  seem'd Negligent of human Cares,</l>
     <l n="272">Nor Scourg'd our Follies, nor return'd our Prayers.</l>
     <l n="273">His Justice now Demands the equal Scales,</l>
     <l n="274">Sedition is Supprest, and Truth Prevails:</l>
     <l n="275">Fate it's great Ends by slow Degrees Attains,</l>
     <l n="276">And  is Redeem'd, and  Reigns.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>