<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>All is Vanity.</title>
    <author>Anne Finch (née Kingsmill), countess of Winchilsea</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">7</measure>
    <measure unit="line">301</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Anne Finch (née Kingsmill), countess of Winchilsea_all-is-vanity</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>All is Vanity.</title>
     <author>Anne Finch (née Kingsmill), countess of Winchilsea</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>All is Vanity.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">HOW vain is  which rightly we compare</l>
     <l n="2">To flying  that haste away;</l>
     <l n="3">To  that fade with the declining Day;</l>
     <l n="4">To  that sail amidst the yielding Air;</l>
     <l n="5">Till by Extention into that they flow,</l>
     <l n="6">Or, scatt'ring on the World below,</l>
     <l n="7">Are lost and gone, ere we can say they were;</l>
     <l n="8">To  which every Wind can chace;</l>
     <l n="9">To rising  on the Waters Face;</l>
     <l n="10">To fleeting  that will not stay,</l>
     <l n="11">Nor in th' abused Fancy dance,</l>
     <l n="12">When the returning Rays of Light,</l>
     <l n="13">Resuming their alternate Right,</l>
     <l n="14">Break on th' ill-order'd Scene on the fantastick Trance:</l>
     <l n="15">As weak is  whilst Tenant to the Earth;</l>
     <l n="16">As frail and as uncertain all his Ways,</l>
     <l n="17">From the first moment of his weeping Birth,</l>
     <l n="18">Down to the last and best of his few restless Days;</l>
     <l n="19">When to the Land of Darkness he retires</l>
     <l n="20">From disappointed Hopes, and frustrated Desires;</l>
     <l n="21">Reaping no other Fruit of all his Pain</l>
     <l n="22">Bestow'd whilst in the vale of Tears below,</l>
     <l n="23">But this unhappy Truth, at last to know,</l>
     <l n="24" />
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="25">If past the hazard of his tendrest Years,</l>
     <l n="26">Neither in thoughtless Sleep opprest,</l>
     <l n="27">Nor poison'd with a tainted Breast,</l>
     <l n="28">Loos'd from the infant Bands and female Cares,</l>
     <l n="29">A  advanc'd beyond his Age,</l>
     <l n="30">Wastes the dim Lamp, and turns the restless Page;</l>
     <l n="31">For some lov'd Book prevents the rising Day,</l>
     <l n="32">And on it, stoln aside, bestows the Hours of Play;</l>
     <l n="33">Him the observing Master do's design</l>
     <l n="34">For search of darkned Truths, and Mysteries Divine;</l>
     <l n="35">Bids him with unremitted Labour trace</l>
     <l n="36">The Rise of Empires, and their various Fates,</l>
     <l n="37">The several Tyrants o'er the several States,</l>
     <l n="38">To  lofty Towers, and warlike  Race;</l>
     <l n="39">Bids him in Paradice the Bank survey,</l>
     <l n="40">Where Man, new-moulded from the temper'd Clay,</l>
     <l n="41">(Till fir'd with Breath Divine) a helpless Figure lay:</l>
     <l n="42">Could he be led thus far — What were the Boast,</l>
     <l n="43">What the Reward of all the Toil it cost,</l>
     <l n="44">What from that Land of ever-blooming Spring,</l>
     <l n="45">For our Instruction could he bring,</l>
     <l n="46">Unless, that having Humane Nature found</l>
     <l n="47">Unseparated from its Parent Ground,</l>
     <l n="48">(Howe'er we vaunt our Elevated Birth)</l>
     <l n="49">The Epicure in soft Array,</l>
     <l n="50">The lothsome Beggar, that before</l>
     <l n="51">His rude unhospitable Door,</l>
     <l n="52">Unpity'd but by Brutes, a broken Carcass lay,</l>
     <l n="53">Were both alike deriv'd from the same common Earth?</l>
     <l n="54">But ere the Child can to these Heights attain,</l>
     <l n="55">Ere he can in the Learned Sphere arise;</l>
     <l n="56">A guiding Star, attracting to the Skies,</l>
     <l n="57">A Fever, seizing the o'er-labour'd Brain,</l>
     <l n="58">Sends him, perhaps, to Death's concealing Shade;</l>
     <l n="59">Where, in the Marble Tomb now silent laid,</l>
     <l n="60">He better do's that useful Doctrine show,</l>
     <l n="61">(Which all the sad Assistants ought to know,</l>
     <l n="62">Who round the Grave his short continuance mourn)</l>
     <l n="63" />
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="64">A  grown capable of Arms,</l>
     <l n="65">courts with her prevailing Charms;</l>
     <l n="66">Bids th' inchanting Trumpet sound,</l>
     <l n="67">Loud as Triumph, soft as Love,</l>
     <l n="68">Striking now the Poles above,</l>
     <l n="69">'Then descending from the Skies,</l>
     <l n="70">Soften every falling Note;</l>
     <l n="71">As the harmonious  that sings and flies,</l>
     <l n="72">When near the Earth, contracts her narrow Throat,</l>
     <l n="73">And warbles on the Ground:</l>
     <l n="74">Shews the proud Steed, impatient of the Check,</l>
     <l n="75">'Gainst the loudest Terrors Proof,</l>
     <l n="76">Pawing the Valley with his steeled Hoof,</l>
     <l n="77">With Lightning arm'd his Eyes, with Thunder cloth'd his Neck;</l>
     <l n="78">Who on th' advanced Foe, (the Signal giv'n)</l>
     <l n="79">Flies, like a rushing Storm by mighty Whirlwinds driv'n;</l>
     <l n="80">Lays open the Records of Fame,</l>
     <l n="81">No glorious Deed omits, no Man of mighty Name;</l>
     <l n="82">Their Stratagems, their Tempers she'll repeat,</l>
     <l n="83">From , (truly stil'd the GREAT)</l>
     <l n="84">From  on the World's Imperial Seat,</l>
     <l n="85">To  Conduct, and to  Heat.</l>
     <l n="86">'Tis done! and now th' ambitious Youth disdains</l>
     <l n="87">The safe, but harder Labours of the Gown,</l>
     <l n="88">The softer Pleasures of the Courtly Town,</l>
     <l n="89">The once lov'd rural Sports, and Chaces on the Plains;</l>
     <l n="90">Does with the Soldier's Life the Garb assume,</l>
     <l n="91">The gold Embroid'ries, and the graceful Plume;</l>
     <l n="92">Walks haughty in a Coat of Scarlet Die,</l>
     <l n="93">A Colour well contriv'd to cheat the Eye,</l>
     <l n="94">Where richer Blood, alas! may undistinguisht lye.</l>
     <l n="95">And oh! too near that wretched Fate attends;</l>
     <l n="96">Hear it ye Parents, all ye weeping Friends!</l>
     <l n="97">Thou fonder Maid! won by those gaudy Charms,</l>
     <l n="98">(The destin'd Prize of his Victorious Arms)</l>
     <l n="99">Now sainting Dye upon the mournful Sound,</l>
     <l n="100">That speaks his hasty Death, and paints the fatal Wound!</l>
     <l n="101">Trail all your Pikes, dispirit every Drum,</l>
     <l n="102">March in a slow Procession from afar,</l>
     <l n="103">Ye silent, ye dejected Men of War!</l>
     <l n="104">Be still the Hautboys, and the Flute be dumb!</l>
     <l n="105">Display no more, in vain, the lofty Banner;</l>
     <l n="106">For see! where on the Bier before ye lies</l>
     <l n="107">The pale, the fall'n, th' untimely Sacrifice</l>
     <l n="108">To your mistaken Shrine, to your false Idol Honour!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="109">As Vain is  and as short her Power;</l>
     <l n="110">Tho' in its proud, and transitory Sway,</l>
     <l n="111">The coldest Hearts and wisest Heads obey</l>
     <l n="112">That gay fantastick Tyrant of an Hour.</l>
     <l n="113">On  Charms, (altho' a Father's Right,</l>
     <l n="114">Tho' grave  to thy Royal Side</l>
     <l n="115">By holy Vows fair  be ty'd)</l>
     <l n="116">With anxious Joy, with dangerous Delight,</l>
     <l n="117">Too often gazes thy unwary Son,</l>
     <l n="118">Till past all Hopes, expiring and undone,</l>
     <l n="119">A speaking Pulse the secret Cause impart;</l>
     <l n="120">The only time, when the Physician's Art</l>
     <l n="121">Could ease that lab'ring Grief, or heal a Lover's Smart.</l>
     <l n="122">See Great  now impatient stand,</l>
     <l n="123">Expecting, with mistaken Pride,</l>
     <l n="124">On  crowded Shore, on  fatal Strand,</l>
     <l n="125">A  at his Tribunal to be try'd,</l>
     <l n="126">A  that arm'd in Beauty, shall deride</l>
     <l n="127">His feeble Rage, and his whole Fate command:</l>
     <l n="128">O'er the still Waves her burnisht Galley moves,</l>
     <l n="129">Row'd by the Graces, whilst officious Loves</l>
     <l n="130">To silken Cords their busie Hands apply,</l>
     <l n="131">Or gathering all the gentle Gales that fly,</l>
     <l n="132">To their fair Mistress with those Spoils repair,</l>
     <l n="133">And from their purple Wings disperse the balmy Air.</l>
     <l n="134">Hov'ring Perfumes ascend in od'rous Clouds,</l>
     <l n="135">Curl o'er the Barque, and play among the Shrouds;</l>
     <l n="136">Whilst gently dashing every Silver Oar,</l>
     <l n="137">Guided by the Rules of Art,</l>
     <l n="138">With tuneful Instruments design'd</l>
     <l n="139">To soften, and subdue the stubborn Mind,</l>
     <l n="140">A strangely pleasing and harmonious Part</l>
     <l n="141">In equal Measures bore.</l>
     <l n="142">Like a new  on her native Sea,</l>
     <l n="143">In midst of the transporting Scene,</l>
     <l n="144">(Which Pen or Pencil imitates in vain)</l>
     <l n="145">On a resplendent and conspicuous Bed,</l>
     <l n="146">With all the Pride of  loosely spread,</l>
     <l n="147">The lovely  lay.</l>
     <l n="148">Which but discern'd from the yet distant Shore,</l>
     <l n="149">Th' amazed Emperor could hate no more;</l>
     <l n="150">No more a baffled Vengeance could pursue;</l>
     <l n="151">But yielding still, still as she nearer drew,</l>
     <l n="152">When  anchor'd in the Bay,</l>
     <l n="153">Where every Charm cou'd all its Force display,</l>
     <l n="154">Like his own  stood, and gaz'd the  away.</l>
     <l n="155">Where ends alas! this Pageantry and State;</l>
     <l n="156">Where end the Triumphs of this conqu'ring Face,</l>
     <l n="157">Envy'd of  Wives, and all the Female Race?</l>
     <l n="158">Oh swift Vicissitude of Beauty's Fate!</l>
     <l n="159">Now in her Tomb withdrawn from publick Sight,</l>
     <l n="160">From near Captivity and Shame,</l>
     <l n="161">The vanquish'd, the abandon'd Dame</l>
     <l n="162">Proffers the Arm, that held another's Right,</l>
     <l n="163">To the destructive Snake's more just Embrace,</l>
     <l n="164">And courts deforming  to mend his Leaden Pace.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="165">But  shall last (the vaunting  cries)</l>
     <l n="166">Th' immortal Streams that from  flow,</l>
     <l n="167">Shall make his never-fading Lawrels grow,</l>
     <l n="168">Above this mouldring Earth to flourish in the Skies:</l>
     <l n="169">"And when his Body falls in Funeral Fire,</l>
     <l n="170">When late revolving Ages shall consume</l>
     <l n="171">The very Pillars, that support his Tomb,</l>
     <l n="172">"His Name shall live, and his best Part aspire.</l>
     <l n="173">Deluded Wretch! grasping at future Praise,</l>
     <l n="174">Now planting, with mistaken Care,</l>
     <l n="175">Round thy enchanted Palace in the Air,</l>
     <l n="176">A Grove, which in thy Fancy time shall raise,</l>
     <l n="177">A Grove of soaring Palms, and everlasting Bays;</l>
     <l n="178">Could'st Thou alas! to such Renown arrive,</l>
     <l n="179">As thy Imaginations wou'd contrive;</l>
     <l n="180">Should numerous Cities, in a vain contest,</l>
     <l n="181">Struggle for thy famous Birth;</l>
     <l n="182">Should the sole Monarch of the conquer'd Earth,</l>
     <l n="183">His wreathed Head upon thy Volume rest;</l>
     <l n="184">Like  could'st thou justly claim,</l>
     <l n="185">Amongst th' inspired tuneful Race,</l>
     <l n="186">The highest Room, the undisputed Place;</l>
     <l n="187">And after near Two Thousand Years of Fame,</l>
     <l n="188">Have thy proud Work to a new People shown;</l>
     <l n="189">Th' unequal'd Poems made their own,</l>
     <l n="190">In such a Dress, in such a perfect Stile</l>
     <l n="191">As on his Labours  now bestows,</l>
     <l n="192">As now from  just Improvement flows,</l>
     <l n="193">In every polish'd Verse throughout the  Isle;</l>
     <l n="194">What Benefit alas! would to thee grow?</l>
     <l n="195">What Sense of Pleasure wou'dst thou know?</l>
     <l n="196">What swelling Joy? what Pride? what Glory have,</l>
     <l n="197">When in the Darkness of the abject Grave,</l>
     <l n="198">Insensible, and  laid below,</l>
     <l n="199">No Atom of thy Heap, no Dust wou'd move,</l>
     <l n="200">For all the airy Breath that form'd thy Praise above?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="201">True, says the Man to  inclin'd;</l>
     <l n="202">Without the Study of uncertain Art,</l>
     <l n="203">Without much Labour of the Mind,</l>
     <l n="204">Meer uninstructed Nature will impart,</l>
     <l n="205" />
     <l n="206">Sieze then, my Friends, (he cries) the present Hour;</l>
     <l n="207">The Pleasure which to that belongs,</l>
     <l n="208">The Feasts, th' o'erflowing Bowls, the Mirth, the Songs,</l>
     <l n="209">The Orange-Bloom, that with such Sweetness blows,</l>
     <l n="210">celebrated Rose,</l>
     <l n="211">The Hyacinth, with every beauteous Flower,</l>
     <l n="212">Which just this happy Moment shall disclose,</l>
     <l n="213">Are out of Fortune's reach, and all within our Power.</l>
     <l n="214">Such costly Garments let our Slaves prepare,</l>
     <l n="215">As for the gay  were design'd;</l>
     <l n="216">Where a new Sun of radiant Diamonds shin'd,</l>
     <l n="217">Where the enamel'd Earth, and scarce-discerned Air,</l>
     <l n="218">With a transparent Sea were seen,</l>
     <l n="219">A Sea composed of the Em'rald's Green,</l>
     <l n="220">And with a golden Shore encompass'd round;</l>
     <l n="221">Where every Orient Shell, of wondrous shape was found.</l>
     <l n="222">The whole Creation on his Shoulders hung,</l>
     <l n="223">The whole Creation with his Wish comply'd,</l>
     <l n="224">Did swiftly, for each Appetite provide,</l>
     <l n="225">And fed them all when Young.</l>
     <l n="226">No less, th'  Prince enjoy'd,</l>
     <l n="227">Of Bliss too soon depriv'd, but never cloy'd.</l>
     <l n="228">Whose Counsel let us still pursue,</l>
     <l n="229">Whose Monument, did this Inscription shew</l>
     <l n="230">To every Passenger, that trod the way,</l>
     <l n="231">Where, with a slighting Hand, and scornful Smile</l>
     <l n="232">The proud Effigies, on th' instructive Pile,</l>
     <l n="233">A great Example lay.</l>
     <l n="234" />
     <l n="235" />
     <l n="236" />
     <l n="237" />
     <l n="238" />
     <l n="239" />
     <l n="240">Thus! talks the Fool, whom no Restraint can bound,</l>
     <l n="241">When now the Glass has gone a frequent round;</l>
     <l n="242">When soaring Fancy lightly swims,</l>
     <l n="243">Fancy, that keeps above, and dances o'er the Brims;</l>
     <l n="244">Whilst weighty Reason sinks, and in the bottom's drown'd:</l>
     <l n="245">Adds to his Own, an artificial Fire,</l>
     <l n="246">Doubling ev'ry hot Desire,</l>
     <l n="247">Till th' auxiliary Spirits, in a Flame,</l>
     <l n="248">The Stomach's Magazine defy,</l>
     <l n="249">That standing Pool, that helpless Moisture nigh</l>
     <l n="250">Thro' every Vital part impetuous fly,</l>
     <l n="251">And quite consume the Frame;</l>
     <l n="252">When to the Under world despis'd he goes,</l>
     <l n="253">A pamper'd Carcase on the Worms bestows,</l>
     <l n="254">Who rioting on the unusual Chear,</l>
     <l n="255">As good a Life enjoy, as he could boast of here.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="256">But hold my Muse! thy farther Flight restrain,</l>
     <l n="257">Exhaust not thy declining Force,</l>
     <l n="258">Nor in a long, pursu'd, and breathless Course,</l>
     <l n="259">Attempt, with slacken'd speed, to run</l>
     <l n="260">Through ev'ry Vanity beneath the Sun,</l>
     <l n="261">Lest thy o'erweary'd Reader, should complain,</l>
     <l n="262">That of all Vanities beside,</l>
     <l n="263">Which thine, or his Experience e'er have try'd,</l>
     <l n="264">Thou art, too tedious Muse, most frivolous and vain:</l>
     <l n="265">Yet, tell the Man, of an aspiring Thought,</l>
     <l n="266">Of an ambitious, restless Mind,</l>
     <l n="267">That can no Ease, no Satisfaction find,</l>
     <l n="268">Till neighb'ring States are to Subjection brought,</l>
     <l n="269">Till Universal Awe, enslav'd Mankind is taught;</l>
     <l n="270">That, should he lead an Army to the Field,</l>
     <l n="271">For whose still necessary Use,</l>
     <l n="272">Th' extended Earth cou'd not enough produce,</l>
     <l n="273">Nor Rivers to their Thirst a full Contentment yield;</l>
     <l n="274">Yet, must their dark Reverse of Fate</l>
     <l n="275">Roll round, within that Course of Years,</l>
     <l n="276">Within the short, the swift, and fleeting Date</l>
     <l n="277">Prescrib'd by  when his falling Tears</l>
     <l n="278">Bewail'd those Numbers, which his Sword employ'd,</l>
     <l n="279">And false, , lamented and destroy'd.</l>
     <l n="280">Tell Him, that does some stately Building raise,</l>
     <l n="281">A  or  erect,</l>
     <l n="282">And thorough all Posterity expect,</l>
     <l n="283">With its unshaken Base, a firm unshaken Praise;</l>
     <l n="284">Tell Him,  Temple is no more,</l>
     <l n="285">Upon whose Splendour, Thousands heretofore</l>
     <l n="286">Spent the astonish'd Hours, forgetful to Adore:</l>
     <l n="287">Tell him, into the Earth agen is hurl'd,</l>
     <l n="288">That most stupendious Wonder of the World,</l>
     <l n="289">Justly presiding o'er the boasted Seven,</l>
     <l n="290">By humane Art and Industry design'd,</l>
     <l n="291">This! the rich Draught of the Immortal Mind,</l>
     <l n="292">The Architect of Heaven.</l>
     <l n="293">Remember then, to fix thy Aim on High,</l>
     <l n="294">Project, and build on t'other side the Sky,</l>
     <l n="295">For, after all thy vain Expence below,</l>
     <l n="296">Thou canst no Fame, no lasting Pleasure know;</l>
     <l n="297">No Good, that shall not thy Embraces fly,</l>
     <l n="298">Or thou from that be in a Moment caught,</l>
     <l n="299">Thy Spirit to new Claims, new Int'rests brought,</l>
     <l n="300">Whilst unconcern'd thy secret Ashes lye,</l>
     <l n="301">Or stray about the Globe,</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>