<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>A Pindarick Poem Upon the Hurricane in November 1703, referring to this Text in Psalm 148. ver. 8. Winds and Storms fulfilling his Word.</title>
    <author>Anne Finch (née Kingsmill), countess of Winchilsea</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">11</measure>
    <measure unit="line">303</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Anne Finch (née Kingsmill), countess of Winchilsea_a-pindarick-poem-upon-the-hurr</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>A Pindarick Poem Upon the Hurricane in November 1703, referring to this Text in Psalm 148. ver. 8. Winds and Storms fulfilling his Word.</title>
     <author>Anne Finch (née Kingsmill), countess of Winchilsea</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>A Pindarick Poem Upon the Hurricane in November 1703, referring to this Text in Psalm 148. ver. 8. Winds and Storms fulfilling his Word.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">YOU have obey'd, you WINDS, that must fulfill</l>
     <l n="2">The Great Disposer's righteous Will;</l>
     <l n="3">Throughout the Land, unlimited you flew,</l>
     <l n="4">Nor sought, as heretofore, with Friendly Aid</l>
     <l n="5">Only, new Motion to bestow</l>
     <l n="6">Upon the sluggish Vapours, bred below,</l>
     <l n="7">Condensing into Mists, and melancholy Shade.</l>
     <l n="8">No more such gentle Methods you pursue,</l>
     <l n="9">But marching now in terrible Array,</l>
     <l n="10">Undistinguish'd was your Prey:</l>
     <l n="11">In vain the  with lowly Bent,</l>
     <l n="12">Sought their Destruction to prevent;</l>
     <l n="13">The  in vain, with out-stretch'd Arms,</l>
     <l n="14">Deprecates th' approaching Harms;</l>
     <l n="15">In vain the  (so often storm'd)</l>
     <l n="16">Rely'd upon that native Force,</l>
     <l n="17">By which already was perform'd</l>
     <l n="18">So much of his appointed Course,</l>
     <l n="19">As made him, fearless of Decay,</l>
     <l n="20">Wait but the accomplish'd Time</l>
     <l n="21">Of his long-wish'd and useful Prime,</l>
     <l n="22">To be remov'd, with Honour, to the Sea.</l>
     <l n="23">The strait and ornamental</l>
     <l n="24">Did in the like Ambition joyn,</l>
     <l n="25">And thought his Fame shou'd ever last,</l>
     <l n="26">When in some Royal Ship he stood the planted Mast.</l>
     <l n="27">And shou'd again his Length of Timber rear</l>
     <l n="28">And new engrafted Branches wear</l>
     <l n="29">Of fibrous Cordage and impending Shrouds,</l>
     <l n="30">Still trimm'd with human Care, and water'd by the Clouds</l>
     <l n="31">But oh, you  who solitary stood;</l>
     <l n="32">Or you, whose Numbers form'd a Wood;</l>
     <l n="33">You, who on Mountains chose to rise,</l>
     <l n="34">And drew them nearer to the Skies;</l>
     <l n="35">Or you, whom Valleys late did hold</l>
     <l n="36">In flexible and lighter Mould;</l>
     <l n="37">You num'rous Brethren of the Leafy Kind,</l>
     <l n="38">To whatsoever Use design'd,</l>
     <l n="39">Now, vain you found it to contend</l>
     <l n="40">With not, alas! one Element; your Friend</l>
     <l n="41">Your Mother Earth, thro' long preceding Rains,</l>
     <l n="42">(Which undermining sink below)</l>
     <l n="43">No more her wonted Strength retains;</l>
     <l n="44">Nor you so fix'd within her Bosom grow,</l>
     <l n="45">That for your sakes she can resolve to bear</l>
     <l n="46">These furious Shocks of hurrying Air;</l>
     <l n="47">But finding All you Ruin did conspire,</l>
     <l n="48">She soon her beauteous Progeny resign'd</l>
     <l n="49">To this destructive, this imperious Wind,</l>
     <l n="50">That check'd your nobler Aims, and gives you to the Fire.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="51">Thus! have thy Cedars,  been struck</l>
     <l n="52">As the lythe Oziers twisted round;</l>
     <l n="53">Thus!  has thy Wilderness been shook,</l>
     <l n="54">When the apalling, and tremendous Sound</l>
     <l n="55">Of rattl'ing Tempests o'er you broke,</l>
     <l n="56">And made your stubborn Glories bow,</l>
     <l n="57">When in such Whirlwinds the  spoke,</l>
     <l n="58">Warning  then, as our  now.</l>
     <l n="59">Yet these were the remoter Harms,</l>
     <l n="60">Foreign the Care, and distant the Alarms:</l>
     <l n="61">Whilst but sheltring Trees alone,</l>
     <l n="62">Master'd soon, and soon o'erthrown,</l>
     <l n="63">Felt those Gusts, which since prevail,</l>
     <l n="64">And loftier Palaces assail;</l>
     <l n="65">Whose shaken Turrets now give way,</l>
     <l n="66">With vain Inscriptions, which the Freeze has born;</l>
     <l n="67">Through Ages past, t'extol and to adorn,</l>
     <l n="68">And to our latter Times convey;</l>
     <l n="69">Who did the Structures deep Foundation lay,</l>
     <l n="70">Forcing his Praise upon the gazing Croud,</l>
     <l n="71">And, whilst he moulders in a scanty Shroud,</l>
     <l n="72">Telling both Earth and Skies, he when alive was proud</l>
     <l n="73">Now down at once comes the superfluous Load</l>
     <l n="74">The costly Fret-work with it yields,</l>
     <l n="75">Whose imitated Fruits and Flow'rs are strew'd</l>
     <l n="76">Like those of real Growth o'er the Autumn Fields.</l>
     <l n="77">The present Owner lifts his Eyes,</l>
     <l n="78">And the swift Change with sad Affrightment spies:</l>
     <l n="79">The Cieling gone, that late the Roof conceal'd;</l>
     <l n="80">The Roof untyl'd, thro' which the Heav'ns reveal'd,</l>
     <l n="81">Exposes now his Head, when all Defence has fail'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="82">What alas, is to be done!</l>
     <l n="83">Those, who in Cities wou'd from Dangers run,</l>
     <l n="84">Do but encreasing Dangers meet,</l>
     <l n="85">And Death, in various shapes, attending in the Street;</l>
     <l n="86">While some, too tardy in their Flight,</l>
     <l n="87">O'ertaken by a worse Mischance,</l>
     <l n="88">Their upward Parts do scarce advance,</l>
     <l n="89">When on their following Limbs th' extending Ruins light,</l>
     <l n="90">One half's interr'd, the other yet survives,</l>
     <l n="91">And for Release with fainting Vigour strives;</l>
     <l n="92">Implores the Aid of absent Friends in vain;</l>
     <l n="93">With fault'ring Speech, and dying Wishes call,</l>
     <l n="94">Those, whom perhaps, their own Domestick Wall,</l>
     <l n="95">By parallel Distress, or swifter Death retains.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="96">O  thy Bishop's Mansion we lament,</l>
     <l n="97">So tragical the Fall, so dire th' Event!</l>
     <l n="98">But let no daring Thought presume</l>
     <l n="99">To point a Cause for that oppressive Doom.</l>
     <l n="100">Yet strictly pious  had'st Thou been there.</l>
     <l n="101">This Fate, we think, had not become thy share,</l>
     <l n="102">Nor had that awful Fabrick bow'd,</l>
     <l n="103">Sliding from its loosen'd Bands;</l>
     <l n="104">Nor yielding Timbers been allow'd</l>
     <l n="105">To crush thy ever-lifted Hands,</l>
     <l n="106">Or interrupt thy Pray'r.</l>
     <l n="107">Those Orizons, that nightly Watches keep,</l>
     <l n="108">Had call'd thee from thy Bed, or there secur'd thy Sleep.</l>
     <l n="109">Whilst you, bold Winds and Storms! his Word obey'd,</l>
     <l n="110">Whilst you his Scourge the Great  made,</l>
     <l n="111">And into ruin'd Heaps our Edifices laid.</l>
     <l n="112">You  and  the Tragedy began,</l>
     <l n="113">As, with disorder'd haste, you o'er the Surface ran;</l>
     <l n="114">Forgetting, that you were design'd</l>
     <l n="115">(Chiefly thou  thou softest Wind!)</l>
     <l n="116">Only our Heats, when sultry, to allay,</l>
     <l n="117">And chafe the od'rous Gums by your dispersing Play.</l>
     <l n="118">Now, by new Orders and Decrees,</l>
     <l n="119">For our Chastisement issu'd forth,</l>
     <l n="120">You on his Confines the alarmed</l>
     <l n="121">With equal Fury sees,</l>
     <l n="122">And summons swiftly to his Aid</l>
     <l n="123">his Confederate made,</l>
     <l n="124">His eager Second in th' opposing Fight,</l>
     <l n="125">That even the Winds may keep the Balance right,</l>
     <l n="126">Nor yield increase of Sway to arbitrary Might.</l>
     <l n="127">Meeting now, they all contend,</l>
     <l n="128">Those assail, while These defend;</l>
     <l n="129">Fierce and turbulent the War,</l>
     <l n="130">And in the loud tumultuous Jar</l>
     <l n="131">Winds their own Fifes, and Clarions are.</l>
     <l n="132">Each Cavity, which Art or Nature leaves,</l>
     <l n="133">Their Inspiration hastily receives;</l>
     <l n="134">Whence, from their various Forms and Size,</l>
     <l n="135">As various Symphonies arise,</l>
     <l n="136">Their Trumpet ev'ry hollow Tube is made,</l>
     <l n="137">And, when more solid Bodies they invade,</l>
     <l n="138">Enrag'd, they can no farther come,</l>
     <l n="139">The beaten Flatt, whilst it repels the Noise,</l>
     <l n="140">Resembles but with more outrageous Voice</l>
     <l n="141">The Soldier's threatning Drum:</l>
     <l n="142">And when they compass thus our World around,</l>
     <l n="143">When they our Rocks and Mountains rend,</l>
     <l n="144">When they our Sacred Piles to their Foundations send,</l>
     <l n="145">No wonder if our ecchoing Caves rebound;</l>
     <l n="146">No wonder if our list'ning Sense they wound,</l>
     <l n="147">When arm'd with so much Force, and usher'd with such Sound.</l>
     <l n="148">Nor scarce, amidst the Terrors of that Night,</l>
     <l n="149">When you, fierce Winds, such Desolations wrought,</l>
     <l n="150">When you from out his Stores the Great Commander brought,</l>
     <l n="151">Cou'd the most Righteous stand upright;</l>
     <l n="152">Scarcely the Holiest Man performs</l>
     <l n="153">The Service, that becomes it best,</l>
     <l n="154">By ardent Vows, or solemn Pray'rs addrest;</l>
     <l n="155">Nor finds the Calm, so usual to his Breast,</l>
     <l n="156">Full Proof against such Storms.</l>
     <l n="157">How shou'd the Guilty then be found,</l>
     <l n="158">The Men in Wine, or looser Pleasures drown'd,</l>
     <l n="159">To six a stedfast Hope, or to maintain their Ground!</l>
     <l n="160">When at his Glass the late Companion feels,</l>
     <l n="161">That Giddy, like himself, the tott'ring Mansion reels!</l>
     <l n="162">The Miser, who with many a Chest</l>
     <l n="163">His gloomy Tenement opprest,</l>
     <l n="164">Now fears the over-burthen'd Floor,</l>
     <l n="165">And trembles for his Life, but for his Treasure more.</l>
     <l n="166">What shall he do, or to what Pow'rs apply?</l>
     <l n="167">To those, which threaten from on High,</l>
     <l n="168">By him ne'er call'd upon before,</l>
     <l n="169">Who also will suggest th' impossible Restore?</l>
     <l n="170">No;  to thy Laws he will be true,</l>
     <l n="171">And, rather than his Wealth, will bid the World adieu.</l>
     <l n="172">The Rafters sink, and bury'd with his Coin</l>
     <l n="173">That Fate does with his living Thoughts combine;</l>
     <l n="174">For still his Heart's inclos'd within a Golden Mine.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="175">Contention with its angry Brawls</l>
     <l n="176">By Storms o'er-clamour'd, shrinks and falls;</l>
     <l n="177">Nor WHIG, nor TORY now the rash Contender calls.</l>
     <l n="178">Those, who but Vanity allow'd,</l>
     <l n="179">Nor thought, it reach'd the Name of Sin,</l>
     <l n="180">To be of their Perfections proud,</l>
     <l n="181">Too much adorn'd without, or too much rais'd within,</l>
     <l n="182">Now find, that even the lightest Things,</l>
     <l n="183">As the minuter parts of Air,</l>
     <l n="184">When Number to their Weight addition brings,</l>
     <l n="185">Can, like the small, but numerous Insects Stings,</l>
     <l n="186">Can, like th' assembl'd Winds, urge Ruin and Despair.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="187">Thus You've obey'd, you Winds, that must fulfill</l>
     <l n="188">The Great disposer's Righteous Will:</l>
     <l n="189">Thus did your Breath a strict Enquiry make,</l>
     <l n="190">Thus did you our most secret Sins awake,</l>
     <l n="191">And thus chastis'd their Ill.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="192">Whilst vainly Those, of a rapacious Mind,</l>
     <l n="193">Fields to other Fields had laid,</l>
     <l n="194">By Force, or by injurious Bargains join'd,</l>
     <l n="195">With Fences for their Guard impenetrable made;</l>
     <l n="196">The juster Tempest mocks the wrong,</l>
     <l n="197">And sweeps, in its directed Flight,</l>
     <l n="198">Th' Inclosures of another's Right,</l>
     <l n="199">Driving at once the Bounds, and licens'd Herds along.</l>
     <l n="200">The Earth agen one general Scene appears;</l>
     <l n="201">No regular distinction now,</l>
     <l n="202">Betwixt the Grounds for Pasture, or the Plough,</l>
     <l n="203">The Face of Nature wears.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="204">Free as the Men, who wild Confusion love,</l>
     <l n="205">And lawless Liberty approve,</l>
     <l n="206">Their Fellow-Brutes pursue their way,</l>
     <l n="207">To their own Loss, and disadvantage stray,</l>
     <l n="208">As wretched in their Choice, as unadvis'd as They.</l>
     <l n="209">The tim'rous  whilst he forsakes the Park,</l>
     <l n="210">And wanders on, in the misguiding Dark,</l>
     <l n="211">Believes, a Foe from ev'ry unknown Bush</l>
     <l n="212">Will on his trembling Body rush,</l>
     <l n="213">Taking the Winds, that vary in their Notes,</l>
     <l n="214">For hot pursuing Hounds with deeply bellowing Throats.</l>
     <l n="215">Th' awaken'd  shook from their nightly Seats,</l>
     <l n="216">Their unavailing Pinions ply,</l>
     <l n="217">Repuls'd, as they attempt to fly</l>
     <l n="218">In hopes they might attain to more secure Retreats.</l>
     <l n="219">But, Where ye wilder'd Fowls wou'd You repair?</l>
     <l n="220">When this your happy Portion given,</l>
     <l n="221">Your upward Lot, your Firmament of Heaven,</l>
     <l n="222">Your unentail'd, your undivided Air,</l>
     <l n="223">Where no Proprietor was ever known,</l>
     <l n="224">Where no litigious Suits have ever grown,</l>
     <l n="225">Whilst none from Star to Star cou'd call the space his Own;</l>
     <l n="226">When this no more your middle Flights can bear,</l>
     <l n="227">But some rough Blast too far above conveighs,</l>
     <l n="228">Or to unquitted Earth confines your weak Essays.</l>
     <l n="229">Nor You, nor wiser Man cou'd find Repose,</l>
     <l n="230">Nor cou'd our Industry produce</l>
     <l n="231">Expedients of the smallest Use,</l>
     <l n="232">To ward our greater Cares, or mitigate your Woes.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="233">Ye  that pity'd our Distress,</l>
     <l n="234">And by your pacifying Showers</l>
     <l n="235">(The soft and usual methods of Success)</l>
     <l n="236">Kindly assay'd to make this Tempest less;</l>
     <l n="237">Vainly your Aid was now alas! employ'd,</l>
     <l n="238">In vain you wept o'er those destructive Hours,</l>
     <l n="239">In which the Winds full Tyranny enjoy'd,</l>
     <l n="240">Nor wou'd allow you to prevail,</l>
     <l n="241">But drove your scorn'd, and scatter'd Tears to wail</l>
     <l n="242">The Land that lay destroy'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="243">Whilst You obey'd, you Winds! that must fulfill</l>
     <l n="244">The just Disposer's Righteous Will;</l>
     <l n="245">Whilst not the Earth alone, you disarray,</l>
     <l n="246">But to more ruin'd Seas wing'd your impetuous Way.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="247">Which to foreshew, the still portentous</l>
     <l n="248">Beamless, and pale of late, his Race begun,</l>
     <l n="249">Quenching the Rays, he had no Joy to keep,</l>
     <l n="250">In the obscure, and sadly threaten'd Deep.</l>
     <l n="251">Farther than we, that Eye of Heaven discerns,</l>
     <l n="252">And nearer plac'd to our malignant Stars,</l>
     <l n="253">Our brooding Tempests, and approaching Wars</l>
     <l n="254">Anticipating learns.</l>
     <l n="255">When now, too soon the dark Event</l>
     <l n="256">Shews what that faded Planet meant;</l>
     <l n="257">Whilst more the liquid Empire undergoes,</l>
     <l n="258">More she resigns of her entrusted Stores,</l>
     <l n="259">The Wealth, the Strength, the Pride of diff'rent Shores</l>
     <l n="260">In one Devoted, one Recorded Night,</l>
     <l n="261">Than Years had known destroy'd by generous Fight,</l>
     <l n="262">Or Privateering Foes.</l>
     <l n="263">All Rules of Conduct laid aside,</l>
     <l n="264">No more the baffl'd  steers,</l>
     <l n="265">Or knows an Art, when it each moment veers,</l>
     <l n="266">To vary with the Winds, or stem th'unusual Tide.</l>
     <l n="267">Dispers'd and loose, the shatter'd Vessels stray,</l>
     <l n="268">Some perish within sight of Shore,</l>
     <l n="269">Some, happier thought, obtain a wider Sea,</l>
     <l n="270">But never to return, or cast an Anchor more!</l>
     <l n="271">Some on the  Coasts are thrown,</l>
     <l n="272">And by congealing Surges compass'd round,</l>
     <l n="273">To fixt and certain Ruin bound,</l>
     <l n="274">Immoveable are grown:</l>
     <l n="275">The fatal  swallows All that come</l>
     <l n="276">Within the Limits of that dangerous Sand,</l>
     <l n="277">Amphibious in its kind, nor Sea nor Land;</l>
     <l n="278">Yet kin to both, a false and faithless Strand,</l>
     <l n="279">Known only to our Cost for a devouring Tomb.</l>
     <l n="280">Nor seem'd the HURRICANE content,</l>
     <l n="281">Whilst only Ships were wreckt, and Tackle rent;</l>
     <l n="282">The Sailors too must fall a Prey,</l>
     <l n="283">Those that Command, with those that did Obey;</l>
     <l n="284">The best Supporters of thy pompous Stile,</l>
     <l n="285">Thou far Renown'd, thou pow'rful BRITISH Isle!</l>
     <l n="286">Foremost in Naval Strength, and Sov'reign of the Sea!</l>
     <l n="287">These from thy Aid that wrathful Night divides,</l>
     <l n="288">Plung'd in those Waves, o'er which this Title rides.</l>
     <l n="289">What art thou, envy'd  at the best,</l>
     <l n="290">In thy deluding Splendors drest?</l>
     <l n="291">What are thy glorious Titles, and thy Forms?</l>
     <l n="292">Which cannot give Security, or Rest</l>
     <l n="293">To favour'd Men, or Kingdoms that contest</l>
     <l n="294">With Popular Assaults, or Providential Storms!</l>
     <l n="295">Whilst on th'Omnipotent our Fate depends,</l>
     <l n="296">And They are only safe, whom He alone defends.</l>
     <l n="297">Then let to Heaven our general Praise be sent,</l>
     <l n="298">Which did our farther Loss, our total Wreck prevent.</l>
     <l n="299">And as our Aspirations do ascend,</l>
     <l n="300">Let every Thing be summon'd to attend;</l>
     <l n="301">And let the Poet</l>
     <l n="302">Direct our Skill in that sublimer part,</l>
     <l n="303">And our weak Numbers mend!</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>