<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>KYMBER: A MONODY.</title>
    <author>Robert Potter</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">20</measure>
    <measure unit="line">360</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Robert Potter_kymber-a-monody</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>KYMBER: A MONODY.</title>
     <author>Robert Potter</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>KYMBER: A MONODY.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">YET once more ye lov'd poplars, and once more</l>
     <l n="2">My silver Yare, your hallow'd haunts I tread,</l>
     <l n="3">The bough-inwoven bank, the damaskt mead,</l>
     <l n="4">And seek the sweet shade of the woodbine bower,</l>
     <l n="5">If haply here the British Muse abide:</l>
     <l n="6">For not on Isis' academic side,</l>
     <l n="7">Nor where proud Thamis rolls his royal waves</l>
     <l n="8">Thro' forest brown or sunny meadow fair,</l>
     <l n="9">Her rapture-breathing voice enchants the ear:</l>
     <l n="10">Nor in those fields that honoured Camus laves;</l>
     <l n="11">He, reverend sire, the sacred groves beneath</l>
     <l n="12">Oft deckt with laureat wreath,</l>
     <l n="13">Thro' the still valleys winds his pensive way</l>
     <l n="14">Without the sweet note of one warbled song;</l>
     <l n="15">Save ever and anon some plaintive lay</l>
     <l n="16">Pours its soft airs, the rustic tombs among,</l>
     <l n="17">To the low winds that thro' his osiers breathe,</l>
     <l n="18">And murmur to the rustling reeds beneath.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="19">Does she o'er Cambria's rugged mountains stray,</l>
     <l n="20">Snowdon's rude cliffs, or huge Plinlimmon's height?</l>
     <l n="21">Or in rough Conway's foaming floods delight,</l>
     <l n="22">That down the steep rocks urge their headlong way?</l>
     <l n="23">There chaunts the raptur'd bard in solemn strain</l>
     <l n="24">Malgo's strong lance, Cadwallin's puissant reign,</l>
     <l n="25">High deeds recorded yet in druid songs:</l>
     <l n="26">Or swells his woe-wild notes, of power to spread</l>
     <l n="27">Chill horror round the ruthless tyrant's head,</l>
     <l n="28">For Urien's fate, for bleeding Modred's wrongs,</l>
     <l n="29">And smites the harp in dreadful harmony.</l>
     <l n="30">Or does she love to lie</l>
     <l n="31">In the mild shade of Hulla's softer groves,</l>
     <l n="32">And twine the vermeil wreath to grace the youth,</l>
     <l n="33">Whose rapt breast glows, as o'er the beach he roves,</l>
     <l n="34">Touch'd with the sacred flame of star-bright truth;</l>
     <l n="35">Whilst to her lore his manly measure flows,</l>
     <l n="36">"And wakes old Humber from his deep repose."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="37">Yet deign, if not to dwell, thy presence deign</l>
     <l n="38">Here, heavenly visitant; and with thee bring</l>
     <l n="39">The loftiest note that swell'd the sounding string,</l>
     <l n="40">When stern Tyrtaeus rais'd the heroic strain;</l>
     <l n="41">To arms the warrior poet smote his lyre,</l>
     <l n="42">And all Laconia caught the martial fire.</l>
     <l n="43">Thee too, harmonious Maid, the strings obey;</l>
     <l n="44">Strike them, and bid the inspiring numbers slow,</l>
     <l n="45">Bid Britain's sons with Sparta's spirit glow,</l>
     <l n="46">And rouze old Albion with thy awful lay.</l>
     <l n="47">Thy lay shall well-born WODEHOUSE deign to hear,</l>
     <l n="48">As now with generous care</l>
     <l n="49">From Honour's fount th' enlivening streams he brings</l>
     <l n="50">To visit as they flow, that silver bower,</l>
     <l n="51">Where the fair plant of publick virtue springs,</l>
     <l n="52">And breathes pure fragrance from each glowing flower;</l>
     <l n="53">Like heaven's own amarant th' immortal tree</l>
     <l n="54">Shoots, blooms, and bears; the growth of KIMBERLEY.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="55">Hast thou no verse then, heavenly Virgin say,</l>
     <l n="56">By Truth attun'd on Fancy's fairy plain;</l>
     <l n="57">No solemn air, no hymn of higher vein,</l>
     <l n="58">To hail the blessed morn's auspicious ray,</l>
     <l n="59">When, these tall towers rejoicing to behold,</l>
     <l n="60">Forth walk'd the orient sun, array'd in gold,</l>
     <l n="61">First on their glittering tops t' impress his beams;</l>
     <l n="62">Thence, glancing downwards, sparkled on the tide</l>
     <l n="63">That bends along yon hoar grove's moss-grown side,</l>
     <l n="64">And scattered crimson o'er its azure streams?</l>
     <l n="65">The Naiads, hasting from their coral caves</l>
     <l n="66">Beneath the chrystal waves,</l>
     <l n="67">(In pearled braids their amber tresses bound)</l>
     <l n="68">Thrice wav'd their hands, and hail'd the rising towers:</l>
     <l n="69">The wood-nymphs too, with florisht chaplets crown'd,</l>
     <l n="70">Forsook their groves, forsook their broidered bowers;</l>
     <l n="71">And thrice their hands they wav'd, and thrice they said,</l>
     <l n="72">"Raise, ye fair structures, raise your towery head!"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="73">Next KYMBER came, slow winding o'er the lea,</l>
     <l n="74">His beard and sedge-crown'd locks all silver'd o'er</l>
     <l n="75">With reverend eld, as winter breathing frore</l>
     <l n="76">Hangs on the bare boughs of the spangled tree:</l>
     <l n="77">His urn was silver fretted round with gold,</l>
     <l n="78">With Runic rhimes imbost, and figures old,</l>
     <l n="79">The illustrious monuments of British fame:</l>
     <l n="80">Here stout Tenantius draws his righteous sword</l>
     <l n="81">To crush the curs'd rule of a foreign lord,</l>
     <l n="82">And spreads unconquered Freedom's sacred flame:</l>
     <l n="83">There war-worn Kymbeline, by victor's power</l>
     <l n="84">Forth driven from princely bower,</l>
     <l n="85">To the thick shelter of these shades retir'd,</l>
     <l n="86">Feeding high thoughts and flames of vengeful war,</l>
     <l n="87">(Like a chac'd lion with fell fury fir'd)</l>
     <l n="88">Writhes on the lurking traitor's close-couch'd spear,</l>
     <l n="89">And bids the conscious grove, and bids the plain,</l>
     <l n="90">And kindred stream, his honoured name retain.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="91">High on her warlike car BONDUCA stands,</l>
     <l n="92">The plumed helmet glittering on her brow,</l>
     <l n="93">Whilst loose in streams of gold her tresses flow,</l>
     <l n="94">The bow and pointed javelin grace her hands;</l>
     <l n="95">Deliberate courage lightens in her eye,</l>
     <l n="96">And conscious worth, and inborn majesty;</l>
     <l n="97">Heroic empress! as thy virtues spread,</l>
     <l n="98">Rome's ravening eagle cow'rs his quivering wings,</l>
     <l n="99">Hope smiles, fair Liberty her blessings brings,</l>
     <l n="100">And heaven-born Glory rays thy sacred head.</l>
     <l n="101">Grac'd with these sculptur'd scenes of ancient fame</l>
     <l n="102">With stately step he came;</l>
     <l n="103">Nor wanted in his way melodious sound</l>
     <l n="104">From pipe or pastoral reed, or dulcet voice</l>
     <l n="105">Of Nymph or Naïad him enringing round,</l>
     <l n="106">Or quiring birds that in his shade rejoice,</l>
     <l n="107">Or gently warbling wind, or water's fall</l>
     <l n="108">Soft trickling from his urn in murmurs musical.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="109">Then on the stately structure's towery height</l>
     <l n="110">With conscious pride he fix'd his raptur'd eyes;</l>
     <l n="111">And as past scenes of ancient glory rise</l>
     <l n="112">Arrang'd on Fancy's field in order bright,</l>
     <l n="113">He paus'd; then graceful bow'd his reverend head,</l>
     <l n="114">And thus in lofty strain due homage paid.</l>
     <l n="115">"Ye strong-bas'd battlements, ye gorgeous walls,</l>
     <l n="116">" Ye princely structures, that with splendor crown'd,</l>
     <l n="117">"Shine o'er your wide dominion stretching round,</l>
     <l n="118">" To you with friendly voice your KYMBER calls,</l>
     <l n="119">"And bids you hail! thereto he adds your name</l>
     <l n="120">" Renown'd in ancient same,</l>
     <l n="121">"Hail Wodehouse-tower! To tell you with what pride,</l>
     <l n="122">" What triumph he your glittering state surveys,</l>
     <l n="123">"That dignifies his lilly-silver'd side,</l>
     <l n="124">" And wakes sweet memory of those glorious days,</l>
     <l n="125">"When full-plum'd Victory wav'd her golden wing,</l>
     <l n="126">" And deckt with trophies proud his honoured spring.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="127">"Yes, KYMBER! now thou may'st with joy retrace</l>
     <l n="128">" The long succession of thy patriot line;</l>
     <l n="129">"With joy behold the unclouded lustre shine</l>
     <l n="130">" Which Virtue beams around her favour'd race.</l>
     <l n="131">"Canst thou forget the Lord of Wodehouse-tower,</l>
     <l n="132">" Whose strong built bastions scorn'd the Norman's power?</l>
     <l n="133">"From Deva's banks (whose mystic waters glide</l>
     <l n="134">" By holy Whitchurch, thro' those pastur'd plains</l>
     <l n="135">"Long since the warlike Talbot's rich domains,</l>
     <l n="136">" When from Blackmere he brought his lovely bride,</l>
     <l n="137">"The fair L'Estrange) thou saw'st the stout knight lead</l>
     <l n="138">" To Silfield's happier mead</l>
     <l n="139">"His Saxon train. There Beauclerk's royal ray</l>
     <l n="140">" Shin'd on his battailous bold offspring, try'd</l>
     <l n="141">"In many a hard and chevalrous assay,</l>
     <l n="142">" When Neustria's fields with crimson gore he dy'd,</l>
     <l n="143">"Spread vengeful flames revolted Bayeux round,</l>
     <l n="144">" And dash'd the rampir'd pride of Caën to the ground.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="145">"Oft as Britannia's royal ensign wav'd,</l>
     <l n="146">" And the stern clarion call'd in field to fight,</l>
     <l n="147">"The warlike WODEHOUSE march'd with prowest might,</l>
     <l n="148">" And the rough front of deathful danger brav'd.</l>
     <l n="149">"Let Bara tell, and let Bodotria tell,</l>
     <l n="150">" Fort, lough, and river, mountain, wood, and dell,</l>
     <l n="151">"All that from southern Eiden's flowery lea</l>
     <l n="152">" Reaches to bleak Strathnavern's northern strand,</l>
     <l n="153">"Was his sword sheath'd, when Edward's iron hand</l>
     <l n="154">"Spread desolation wide from sea to sea?</l>
     <l n="155">" Or when the sable warrior's lifted lance</l>
     <l n="156">"Glar'd in the eyes of France,</l>
     <l n="157">" Was WODEHOUSE wanting to the hero's fame?</l>
     <l n="158">"Let Crecy tell, and Poictiers purple plain,</l>
     <l n="159">" And captive Valois' hallowed oriflame,</l>
     <l n="160">"His dreadless hardiment let Glequin's chain</l>
     <l n="161">"Record, and brave Dandrehen's froward fate,</l>
     <l n="162">"And poor Castilia's tyrant-wielded state.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="163">"Who has not heard of Somme's affrighted flood,</l>
     <l n="164">" How mournfully his cumber'd streams he roll'd</l>
     <l n="165">"O'er shining hauberks, shields, and helms of gold,</l>
     <l n="166">" His crystal current stain'd with prince's blood,</l>
     <l n="167">"When daring Delabreth in wanton pride</l>
     <l n="168">" The warlike Henry's way-worn troop defied?</l>
     <l n="169">"But all this gallant trim and rich array</l>
     <l n="170">" Lay soil'd in dust, when Bedford's burnisat spear</l>
     <l n="171">"Flam'd in their front, and thunder'd in their rear,</l>
     <l n="172">" And York's bright blade hew'd out his dreadful way.</l>
     <l n="173">"Rouze, royal England, rouze thy matchless might,</l>
     <l n="174">" And with a dragon's flight</l>
     <l n="175">"Sweep o'er th' ensanguin'd plains of Agincourt:</l>
     <l n="176">" And see thy WODEHOUSE, whose strong arm subdu'd</l>
     <l n="177">"The ruin'd bulwarks of yon aged fort,</l>
     <l n="178">" His golden chevron charg'd with drops of blood,</l>
     <l n="179">"Rests on the woodmen wild that bear his shield,</l>
     <l n="180">" And hails thee victor of the well fought field!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="181">"Can I forget how blythe my eddies roll'd</l>
     <l n="182">" And kiss'd their crisp'd banks, when to Tewksbury's plain</l>
     <l n="183">"My gallant son led his heroic train,</l>
     <l n="184">"Stout earls, and princely dukes, and barons bold?</l>
     <l n="185">" Yet, ah for pity! these fierce hostings cease,</l>
     <l n="186">"That maiden blossom wears the badge of peace,</l>
     <l n="187">" And will you dye her white leaves red in blood?</l>
     <l n="188">"But if your flaming courage pricks you forth,</l>
     <l n="189">" See where the prowling pilferers of the North</l>
     <l n="190">"With inroad foul o'er Tine's forbidden flood</l>
     <l n="191">" Rush from their bleak hills, lur'd with scent of prey:</l>
     <l n="192">"Brook they your firm array?</l>
     <l n="193">" Far humbler thoughts on Eske's embattail'd banks</l>
     <l n="194">"They learn'd, as Somerset's victorious spear</l>
     <l n="195">" With foul disorder broke their bleeding ranks:</l>
     <l n="196">"Whilst vengeful Wodehouse taught their proud hearts fear,</l>
     <l n="197">"And bade his thunders tell them, as they fled,</l>
     <l n="198">" The brother triumphs where the brother bled.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="199">"But not on camps and fighting fields alone</l>
     <l n="200">" My glory rests; when turtle-pennon'd Peace</l>
     <l n="201">"Hush'd War's harsh roar, and bade his fury cease,</l>
     <l n="202">" In these lov'd shades her softest lustre shone.</l>
     <l n="203">"Here heaven-rapt Piety delights to dwell,</l>
     <l n="204">" Train'd in monastic Flitcham's holy cell;</l>
     <l n="205">"Here plants her palm, whose hallowed branches spread</l>
     <l n="206">" O'er towered Richmond's consecrated shrine,</l>
     <l n="207">"And form'd the only wreath e'er taught to twine</l>
     <l n="208">" Round desolate Caernarvon's hapless head.</l>
     <l n="209">"E'en that strong arm, which stretching from a cloud</l>
     <l n="210">" Crests the atchievement proud</l>
     <l n="211">"Imprest with Agincourt's emblazon'd name,</l>
     <l n="212">" Among his laurels wove this sacred bough,</l>
     <l n="213">"Ennobling valour with Devotion's flame,</l>
     <l n="214">" And taught the warbled orison to flow,</l>
     <l n="215">"As 'midst the taper'd choir the solemn priest</l>
     <l n="216">" Chaunts to the victor saint high heaven's eternal rest.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="217">"Here the firm guardians of the publick weal,</l>
     <l n="218">" Inspir'd with Freedom's heaven-descended flame,</l>
     <l n="219">"Rose nobly faithful to their country's fame;</l>
     <l n="220">" In frequent senates pour'd their ardent zeal,</l>
     <l n="221">"Dash'd the base bribe from curs'd Corruption's hand,</l>
     <l n="222">" And sav'd from scepter'd Pride the sinking land.</l>
     <l n="223">"Or, prompt to answer bleeding Europe's call,</l>
     <l n="224">"To distant realms bore Britain's high behest,</l>
     <l n="225">" Bade the sword sleep, gave gasping nations rest,</l>
     <l n="226">"And taught the doubtful balance where to fall.</l>
     <l n="227">" But in the softer hour of social joy,</l>
     <l n="228">"When ceas'd the high employ,</l>
     <l n="229">" These woodland walks, these tufted dales among</l>
     <l n="230">"The silver-sounding Muses built their bower,</l>
     <l n="231">" Made vocal with the lute attemper'd song;</l>
     <l n="232">"Whilst blooming Courtesy's gold-spangled flower,</l>
     <l n="233">" Cull'd by the Graces, spread its brightest glow</l>
     <l n="234">"To deck unswerving Honour's manly brow.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="235">"And you, age-honoured oaks! whose solemn shades</l>
     <l n="236">" Inviron this fair mansion, proudly stand</l>
     <l n="237">"The sacred nourslings of Eliza's hand,</l>
     <l n="238">"When she with sovereign glory grac'd your glades,</l>
     <l n="239">" And pleas'd beheld her Boleyn's kindred line</l>
     <l n="240">"Ennobled with your trophied honours shine.</l>
     <l n="241">" Spring crestless cravens from such roots as these?</l>
     <l n="242">"Ask the pale Groyne, ask Tayo's trembling tide,</l>
     <l n="243">"Ask Cadiz weeping o'er her ruin'd pride,</l>
     <l n="244">" And Austria scourg'd o'er all the subject seas.</l>
     <l n="245">"From this deep root my blooming branches spread,</l>
     <l n="246">" And rais'd their florisht head,</l>
     <l n="247">"Chear'd with the princely Henry's orient ray;</l>
     <l n="248">"Till, rising on the morn, importune Night</l>
     <l n="249">" Spreads her black veil, and blots his golden day;</l>
     <l n="250">"Darkness ensues, dark deeds, and impious might;</l>
     <l n="251">" Whilst Discord, mounted on his iron car,</l>
     <l n="252">"Cries havock, and lets slip the dogs of war.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="253">"What then could virtue, 'fall'n on evil days,</l>
     <l n="254">" On evil days thus fall'n, and evil tongues,</l>
     <l n="255">"With dangers compast, 'and opprest with wrongs,</l>
     <l n="256">" Save to the wild woods breathe her plaintive lays,</l>
     <l n="257">"And charm the shades, and teach the streams to flow</l>
     <l n="258">" With all the melting melody of woe?</l>
     <l n="259">"But what avail'd or voice, or tuneful hand,</l>
     <l n="260">" When hell bred Faction, rear'd on baleful wings,</l>
     <l n="261">"Stain'd with the blood of nobles and of kings,</l>
     <l n="262">" Spread total desolation o'er the land?</l>
     <l n="263">"Ah KYMBER! where was then thy princely state?</l>
     <l n="264">" Sunk in the general fate;</l>
     <l n="265">"Thy rich roofs sunk, o'er golden pendents spread;</l>
     <l n="266">" Fastolff's white croslet mouldered from the wall,</l>
     <l n="267">"And Hamo's lion dropt his gold crown'd head;</l>
     <l n="268">" The sacred chapel sunk, the festive hall;</l>
     <l n="269">"E'en thy tall towers, majestic in decay,</l>
     <l n="270">" Like thy lost monarch, low in ruins lay.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="271">"Thus Britain sunk, and thus sunk Wodehouse tower;</l>
     <l n="272">" So sinks the sun, as o'er the turbid skies</l>
     <l n="273">"Sudden the storm-engendering clouds arise,</l>
     <l n="274">" And vex with uproar wild Night's fearful hour;</l>
     <l n="275">"That past, his bright beams resalute the day,</l>
     <l n="276">" And heighten'd splendors crown his orient ray:</l>
     <l n="277">"So Britain rose, so rose my princely state.</l>
     <l n="278">" But not the swelling column massy proof,</l>
     <l n="279">"The moulded pediment, the fretted roof,</l>
     <l n="280">" Not this fair fabric proudly elevate,</l>
     <l n="281">"Tho' fix'd by Prowse's just palladian hand</l>
     <l n="282">" Its towred honours stand;</l>
     <l n="283">"Not this clear lake, whose waving crystal spreads</l>
     <l n="284">" Round yon hoar isle with awful shades imbrown'd:</l>
     <l n="285">"Not these pure streams that vein the envermeil'd meads:</l>
     <l n="286">" Nor those age-honoured oaks wide waving round;</l>
     <l n="287">"Exterior glories these, of humbler fame,</l>
     <l n="288">" Beam not that splendent ray which dignifies my name.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
     <l n="289">"The spark of honour kindling glorious thought,</l>
     <l n="290">" The soul by warm benevolence refin'd,</l>
     <l n="291">"The aethereal glow that melts th' empassion'd mind,</l>
     <l n="292">" And Virtue's work to fair perfection brought,</l>
     <l n="293">"Be these my glories. And thou, Power benign!</l>
     <l n="294">" Whose living splendors round the patriot shine,</l>
     <l n="295">"Immortal Genius of this far-fam'd land,</l>
     <l n="296">" This scepter'd isle thron'd midst the circling sea,</l>
     <l n="297">"Seat of the brave, and fortress of the tree,</l>
     <l n="298">" Oft hast thou deign'd to take thy hallow'd stand,</l>
     <l n="299">"These shades among; at Virtue's radiant shrine</l>
     <l n="300">" Oft caught the flame divine,</l>
     <l n="301">"When dark Corruption dim'd thy sovereign light;</l>
     <l n="302">" Thence beam'd thy solemn soul-ennobling ray,</l>
     <l n="303">"To gild these groves with all thy lustre bright,</l>
     <l n="304">" Where nobly thoughtful Mordaunt loves to stray,</l>
     <l n="305">"And manly Prowse with every science crown'd,</l>
     <l n="306">" In Freedom's rustic seat the polish'd Graces thron'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18">
     <l n="307">"And thou, to whom thy KYMBER tunes this strain,</l>
     <l n="308">" If strain like this may reach thy nicer ear,</l>
     <l n="309">"O deign in mine thy country's voice to hear,</l>
     <l n="310">" Which never to a WODEHOUSE call'd in vain!</l>
     <l n="311">"By the proud honours of thy martial crest,</l>
     <l n="312">" The trophied tombs where thy fam'd fathers rest,</l>
     <l n="313">"By Lacy's, Clervaux' , Hunsdon's, Armine's name,</l>
     <l n="314">" By Manhood's, Glory's, Freedom's, Virtue's praise,</l>
     <l n="315">"Wake the high thought, the lofty spirit raise,</l>
     <l n="316">" And blazon thy hereditary fame.</l>
     <l n="317">"That fame shall live, whilst Pride's unrighteous power,</l>
     <l n="318">" The pageant of an hour,</l>
     <l n="319">"Fades from the guilty scene, and sinks in night:</l>
     <l n="320">" That fame shall live, and spread its constant rays,</l>
     <l n="321">"Warm like the blessed sun with genial light;</l>
     <l n="322">" Whilst Vice and Folly spend their baleful blaze,</l>
     <l n="323">"As meteors, glaring o'er a troubled sky,</l>
     <l n="324">" Shoot their pernicious fires, amaze, and die. "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19">
     <l n="325">He ceas'd his gratulation: the high strain</l>
     <l n="326">Pierc'd the thick gloom where Britain's Genius lay</l>
     <l n="327">Cover'd with charmed cloud from view of day:</l>
     <l n="328">He heard, and bursting thro' the falsed train,</l>
     <l n="329">In all the majesty of empire rose,</l>
     <l n="330">And issued stern to quell his vaunting foes.</l>
     <l n="331">The Naïads saw, and swell'd their surging floods;</l>
     <l n="332">Old KYMBER saw, and smil'd; the burnish'd glades</l>
     <l n="333">Rejoic'd; the groves wav'd their exulting shades;</l>
     <l n="334">And lofty Feorhou bow'd with all his woods!</l>
     <l n="335">The lordly lion ramping by his side,</l>
     <l n="336">He march'd in martial pride,</l>
     <l n="337">And pour'd his flaming spirit o'er the land;</l>
     <l n="338">The kindling hamlets rouz'd with war's alarms,</l>
     <l n="339">Snatch the bright faulchion from the hireling hand,</l>
     <l n="340">And bravely train their free-born youth to arms;</l>
     <l n="341">Whilst Liberty her glittering ensign waves,</l>
     <l n="342">And bids each generous son disdain an host of slaves.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="20">
     <l n="343">Then royally on the ocean wave enthron'd,</l>
     <l n="344">With all his terrors arm'd, he rode sublime,</l>
     <l n="345">And roll'd his thunders o'er each hostile clime:</l>
     <l n="346">Seine's silken vassals trembled at the sound;</l>
     <l n="347">The cloud-wrapt promontory shook, and all</l>
     <l n="348">Its rock-bas'd rampires nodded to their fall.</l>
     <l n="349">Reign ever thus, unconquer'd Britain, reign;</l>
     <l n="350">Whilst thy free sons in firm battalions stand,</l>
     <l n="351">And guard with lion-ramp their native land:</l>
     <l n="352">Thus fix thy throne, thus rule the subject main!</l>
     <l n="353">So shall bright Victory o'er thy laurel'd head</l>
     <l n="354">Her eagle-pennons spread;</l>
     <l n="355">Whilst soft-ey'd Peace, quitting at thy command</l>
     <l n="356">Her radiant orb in yon empyreal plain,</l>
     <l n="357">Waves o'er the willing world her myrtle wand:</l>
     <l n="358">So shall the Muse her Doric oat disdain,</l>
     <l n="359">And touch'd with sphere-born Rapture's hallow'd fire,</l>
     <l n="360">Swell her triumphal notes, and sweep the golden lyre.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>