<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Against ILL-NATURE.</title>
    <author>Christopher Smart</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">4</measure>
    <measure unit="line">60</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Christopher Smart_against-ill-nature</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>Against ILL-NATURE.</title>
     <author>Christopher Smart</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>Against ILL-NATURE.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">OFSPRING of folly and of pride,</l>
     <l n="2">To all that's odious, all that's base allied;</l>
     <l n="3">Nurs'd up by vice, by pravity missed,</l>
     <l n="4">By pedant affectation taught and bred:</l>
     <l n="5">Away, thou hideous hell-born spright,</l>
     <l n="6">Go, with thy looks of dark design,</l>
     <l n="7">Sullen, sour, and saturnine;</l>
     <l n="8">Fly to some gloomy shade, nor blot the goodly light.</l>
     <l n="9">Thy planet was remote, when I was born;</l>
     <l n="10">'Twas Mercury that rul'd my natal morn,</l>
     <l n="11">What time the sun exerts his genial ray,</l>
     <l n="12">And ripens for enjoyment every growing day;</l>
     <l n="13">When to exist is but to love and sing,</l>
     <l n="14">And sprightly Aries smiles upon the spring.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="15">There in yon lonesome heath,</l>
     <l n="16">Which Flora, or Sylvanus never knew,</l>
     <l n="17">Where never vegetable drank the dew,</l>
     <l n="18">Or beast, or fowl attempts to breathe;</l>
     <l n="19">Where Nature's pencil has no colours laid;</l>
     <l n="20">But all is blank, and universal shade;</l>
     <l n="21">Contrast to figure, motion, life and light,</l>
     <l n="22">There may'st thou vent thy spight,</l>
     <l n="23">For ever cursing, and for ever curs'd,</l>
     <l n="24">Of all th' infernal crew the worst;</l>
     <l n="25">The worst in genius, measure and degree;</l>
     <l n="26">For envy, hatred, malice, are but parts of thee.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="27">Or woud'st thou change the scene, and quit thy den,</l>
     <l n="28">Behold the heav'n-deserted fen,</l>
     <l n="29">Where spleen, by vapours dense begot and bred,</l>
     <l n="30">Hardness of heart, and heaviness of head,</l>
     <l n="31">Have rais'd their darksome walls, and plac'd their thorny bed;</l>
     <l n="32">There may'st thou all thy bitterness unload,</l>
     <l n="33">There may'st thou croak, in concert with the toad,</l>
     <l n="34">With thee the hollow howling winds shall join,</l>
     <l n="35">Nor shall the bittern her base throat deny,</l>
     <l n="36">The querulous frogs shall mix their dirge with thine,</l>
     <l n="37">Th' ear-piercing hern, and plover screaming high,</l>
     <l n="38">While million humming gnats fit oestrum shall supply.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="39">Away — away — behold an hideous band</l>
     <l n="40">An herd of all thy minions are at hand,</l>
     <l n="41">Suspicion first with jealous caution stalks,</l>
     <l n="42">And ever looks around her as she walks,</l>
     <l n="43">With bibulous ear imperfect sounds to catch,</l>
     <l n="44">And prompt to listen at her neighbours latch.</l>
     <l n="45">Next Scandal's meagre shade,</l>
     <l n="46">Foe to the virgins, and the poet's fame,</l>
     <l n="47">A wither'd, time-deflow'red old maid,</l>
     <l n="48">That ne'er enjoy'd love's ever sacred flame.</l>
     <l n="49">Hypocrisy succeeds with saint-like look,</l>
     <l n="50">And elevates her hands and plods upon her book.</l>
     <l n="51">Next comes illiberal scrambling Avarice,</l>
     <l n="52">Then Vanity and Affectation nice —</l>
     <l n="53">See, she salutes her shadow with a bow</l>
     <l n="54">As in short Gallic trips she minces by,</l>
     <l n="55">Starting antipathy is in her eye,</l>
     <l n="56">And squeamishly she knits her scornful brow.</l>
     <l n="57">To thee, Ill-Nature, all the numerous group</l>
     <l n="58">With lowly reverence stoop —</l>
     <l n="59">They wait thy call, and mourn thy long delay,</l>
     <l n="60">Away — thou art infectious — haste away.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>