<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>To the reverend and learned Dr. WEBSTER, Occasioned by his Dialogues on ANGER and FORGIVENESS. ODE VIII.</title>
    <author>Christopher Smart</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">6</measure>
    <measure unit="line">61</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Christopher Smart_to-the-reverend-and-learned-dr</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>To the reverend and learned Dr. WEBSTER, Occasioned by his Dialogues on ANGER and FORGIVENESS. ODE VIII.</title>
     <author>Christopher Smart</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>To the reverend and learned Dr. WEBSTER, Occasioned by his Dialogues on ANGER and FORGIVENESS. ODE VIII.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">'TWAS when th' omniscient creative pow'r</l>
     <l n="2">Display'd his wonders by a mortal's hand,</l>
     <l n="3">And, delegated at th' appointed hour,</l>
     <l n="4">Great Moses led away his chosen band;</l>
     <l n="5">When Israel's host, with all their stores,</l>
     <l n="6">Past thro' the ruby-tinctur'd crystal shores,</l>
     <l n="7">The wilderness of waters and of land:</l>
     <l n="8">Then persecution rag'd in heav'n's own cause,</l>
     <l n="9">And right on neighbouring kingdoms to infringe,</l>
     <l n="10">Strict justice for the breach of nature's laws,</l>
     <l n="11">Strict justice, who's full-sister to revenge:</l>
     <l n="12">The legislator held the scythe of fate,</l>
     <l n="13">Where'er his legions chanc'd to stray,</l>
     <l n="14">Death and destruction mark'd their bloody way;</l>
     <l n="15">Immoderate was their rage, for mortal was their hate.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="16">But when the king of righteousness arose,</l>
     <l n="17">And on the illumin'd East serenely smil'd,</l>
     <l n="18">He shone with meekest mercy on his foes,</l>
     <l n="19">Bright as the sun, but as the moon-beams mild;</l>
     <l n="20">From anger, fell revenge, and discord free,</l>
     <l n="21">He bad war's hellish clangor cease,</l>
     <l n="22">In pastoral simplicity and peace,</l>
     <l n="23">And shew'd to men that face, which Moses could not see.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="24">Well hast thou, WEBSTER, pictur'd christian love,</l>
     <l n="25">And copied our great master's fair design,</l>
     <l n="26">But livid Envy would the light remove,</l>
     <l n="27">Or croud thy portrait in a nook malign —</l>
     <l n="28">The Muse shall hold it up to popular view —</l>
     <l n="29">Where the more candid and judicious few</l>
     <l n="30">Shall think the bright original they see,</l>
     <l n="31">The likeness nobly lost in the identity.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="32">Oh hadst thou liv'd in better days than these,</l>
     <l n="33">E'er to excel by all was deem'd a shame!</l>
     <l n="34">Alas! thou hast no modern arts to please,</l>
     <l n="35">And to deserve is all thy empty claim.</l>
     <l n="36">Else thou'dst been plac'd, by learning, and by wit,</l>
     <l n="37">There, where thy dignify'd inferiors sit —</l>
     <l n="38">Oh  are in their generation wise,</l>
     <l n="39">Each path of interest  have sagely trod, —</l>
     <l n="40">To live — to thrive — to rise — and still to rise —</l>
     <l n="41">Better to bow to men, than kneel to God.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="42">Behold! — where poor unmansion'd Merit stands,</l>
     <l n="43">All cold, and crampt with penury and pain;</l>
     <l n="44">Speechless thro' want, she rears th' imploring hands,</l>
     <l n="45">And begs a little bread, but begs in vain;</l>
     <l n="46">While Bribery and Dulness, passing by,</l>
     <l n="47">Bid her, in sounds barbarian, starve and die.</l>
     <l n="48">"Away (they cry (we never saw thy name)</l>
     <l n="49">" Or in Preferment's List, or that of Fame;</l>
     <l n="50">"Away — nor here the fate thou earn'st bewail,</l>
     <l n="51">" Who canst not buy a vote, nor hast a soul for sale.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="52">Oh Indignation, wherefore wert thou given,</l>
     <l n="53">If drowsy Patience deaden all thy rage? —</l>
     <l n="54">Yet we must  such is the will of heaven;</l>
     <l n="55">And, WEBSTER, so prescribes thy candid page.</l>
     <l n="56">Then let us hear thee preach seraphic love,</l>
     <l n="57">Guide our disgusted thoughts to things above;</l>
     <l n="58">So our free souls, fed with divine repast,</l>
     <l n="59">(Unmindful of low mortals mean employ)</l>
     <l n="60">Shall taste the present, recollect the past,</l>
     <l n="61">And strongly hope for every future joy.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>