<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>MONODY TO THE MEMORY OF A YOUNG LADY.</title>
    <author>Cuthbert Shaw</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">15</measure>
    <measure unit="line">269</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Cuthbert Shaw_monody-to-the-memory-of-a-youn</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>MONODY TO THE MEMORY OF A YOUNG LADY.</title>
     <author>Cuthbert Shaw</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>MONODY TO THE MEMORY OF A YOUNG LADY.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">YET do I live! O how shall I sustain</l>
     <l n="2">This vast unutterable weight of woe?</l>
     <l n="3">This worse than hunger, poverty, or pain,</l>
     <l n="4">Or all the complicated ills below —</l>
     <l n="5">She, in whose life my hopes were treasur'd all,</l>
     <l n="6">Is gone — for ever fled —</l>
     <l n="7">My dearest EMMA's dead;</l>
     <l n="8">These eyes, these tear-swoln eyes beheld her fall:</l>
     <l n="9">Ah no — she lives on some far happier shore,</l>
     <l n="10">She lives — but (cruel thought!) she lives for me no more.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="11">I, who the tedious absence of a day</l>
     <l n="12">Remov'd, wou'd languish for my charmer's sight,</l>
     <l n="13">Wou'd chide the lingering moments for delay,</l>
     <l n="14">And fondly blame the slow return of night;</l>
     <l n="15">How, how shall I endure</l>
     <l n="16">(O misery past a cure!)</l>
     <l n="17">Hours, days and years successively to roll,</l>
     <l n="18">Nor ever more behold the comfort of my soul?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="19">Was she not all my fondest wish could frame?</l>
     <l n="20">Did ever Mind so much of Heaven partake?</l>
     <l n="21">Did she not love me with the purest flame,</l>
     <l n="22">And give up friends and fortune for my sake?</l>
     <l n="23">Though mild as evening skies,</l>
     <l n="24">With downcast, streaming eyes,</l>
     <l n="25">Stood the stern frown of supercilious brows,</l>
     <l n="26">Deaf to their brutal threats, and faithful to her vows.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="27">Come, then, some Muse, the saddest of the train,</l>
     <l n="28">(No more your bard shall dwell on idle lays)</l>
     <l n="29">Teach me each moving melancholy strain,</l>
     <l n="30">And O discard the pageantry of phrase:</l>
     <l n="31">Ill suit the flowers of speech with woes like mine!</l>
     <l n="32">Thus, haply, as I paint</l>
     <l n="33">The source of my complaint,</l>
     <l n="34">My soul may own the impassion'd line;</l>
     <l n="35">A flood of tears may gush to my relief,</l>
     <l n="36">And from my swelling heart discharge this load of grief.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="37">Forbear, my fond officious friends, forbear</l>
     <l n="38">To wound my ears with the sad tales you tell;</l>
     <l n="39">"How good she was, how gentle, and how fair!"</l>
     <l n="40">In pity cease — alas! I know too well:</l>
     <l n="41">How, in her sweet, expressive face</l>
     <l n="42">Beam'd forth the beauties of her mind,</l>
     <l n="43">Yet heighten'd by exterior grace</l>
     <l n="44">Of manners most engaging, most refin'd:</l>
     <l n="45">No piteous object could she see,</l>
     <l n="46">But her soft bosom shar'd the woe,</l>
     <l n="47">Whilst smiles of affability</l>
     <l n="48">Endear'd whatever boon she might bestow.</l>
     <l n="49">Whate'er the emotions of her heart,</l>
     <l n="50">Still shone conspicuous in her eyes,</l>
     <l n="51">Stranger to every female art,</l>
     <l n="52">Alike to feign, or to disguise:</l>
     <l n="53">And O the boast how rare!</l>
     <l n="54">The secret in her faithful breast repos'd,</l>
     <l n="55">She ne'er with lawless tongue disclos'd,</l>
     <l n="56">In sacred silence lodg'd inviolate there.</l>
     <l n="57">O feeble words — unable to express</l>
     <l n="58">Her matchless virtues, or my own distress!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="59">Relentless Death! that, steel'd to human woe,</l>
     <l n="60">With murderous hands deals havock on mankind,</l>
     <l n="61">Why (cruel!) strike this deprecated blow,</l>
     <l n="62">And leave such wretched multitudes behind!</l>
     <l n="63">Hark! Groans come wing'd on every breeze!</l>
     <l n="64">The sons of Grief prefer their ardent vow;</l>
     <l n="65">Oppress'd with sorrow, want, or dire disease,</l>
     <l n="66">And supplicate thy aid, as I do now:</l>
     <l n="67">In vain — Perverse, still on the unweeting head</l>
     <l n="68">'Tis thine thy vengeful darts to shed;</l>
     <l n="69">Hope's infant blossoms to destroy,</l>
     <l n="70">And drench in tears the face of joy.</l>
     <l n="71">But oh! fell tyrant! yet expect the hour</l>
     <l n="72">When Virtue shall renounce thy power;</l>
     <l n="73">When thou no more shalt blot the face of day,</l>
     <l n="74">Nor mortals tremble at thy rigid sway.</l>
     <l n="75">Alas! the day — where-e'er I turn my eyes,</l>
     <l n="76">Some sad memento of my loss appears;</l>
     <l n="77">I fly the fatal house — suppress my sighs,</l>
     <l n="78">Resolv'd to dry my unavailing tears:</l>
     <l n="79">But, ah! In vain — no change of time or place</l>
     <l n="80">The memory can efface</l>
     <l n="81">Of all that sweetness, that enchanting air,</l>
     <l n="82">Now lost; and nought remains but anguish and despair.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="83">Where wer the delegates of Heaven, oh where!</l>
     <l n="84">Appointed Virtue's children safe to keep!</l>
     <l n="85">Had Innocence or Virtue been their care,</l>
     <l n="86">She had not dy'd, nor had I liv'd to weep:</l>
     <l n="87">Mov'd by my tears, and by her patience mov'd,</l>
     <l n="88">To see her force the endearing smile,</l>
     <l n="89">My sorrows to beguile,</l>
     <l n="90">When Torture's keenest rage she prov'd;</l>
     <l n="91">Sure they had warded that untimely dart,</l>
     <l n="92">Which broke her thread of life, and rent a husband's heart.</l>
     <l n="93">How shall I e'er forget that dreadful hour,</l>
     <l n="94">When feeling Death's resistless power,</l>
     <l n="95">My hand she press'd, wet with her falling tears,</l>
     <l n="96">And thus, in faultering accents, spoke her fears!</l>
     <l n="97">"Ah, my lov'd lord, the transient scene is o'er,</l>
     <l n="98">" And we must part (alas!) to meet no more!</l>
     <l n="99">"But oh! if e'er thy EMMA's name was dear,</l>
     <l n="100">" If e'er thy vows have charm'd my ravish'd ear;</l>
     <l n="101">"If, from thy lov'd embrace my heart to gain,</l>
     <l n="102">" Proud friends have frown'd, and Fortune smil'd in vain,</l>
     <l n="103">"If it has been my sole endeavour, still</l>
     <l n="104">" To act in all, obsequious to thy will;</l>
     <l n="105">"To watch thy very smiles, thy wish to know,</l>
     <l n="106">" Then only truly blest when thou wert so:</l>
     <l n="107">"If I have doated with that fond excess,</l>
     <l n="108">" Nor Love could add, nor Fortune make it less;</l>
     <l n="109">"If this I've done, and more — oh then be kind</l>
     <l n="110">" To the dear lovely babe I leave behind.</l>
     <l n="111">"When time my once-lov'd memory shall efface,</l>
     <l n="112">" Some happier maid may take thy EMMA's place,</l>
     <l n="113">"With envious eyes thy partial fondness see,</l>
     <l n="114">" And hate it for the love thou bore to me:</l>
     <l n="115">"My dearest S—, forgive a woman's fears,</l>
     <l n="116">" But one word more (I cannot bear thy tears)</l>
     <l n="117">"Promise — and I will trust thy faithful vow,</l>
     <l n="118">" (Oft have I try'd, and ever sound thee true)</l>
     <l n="119">"That to some distant spot thou wilt remove</l>
     <l n="120">" This fatal pledge of hapless EMMA's love,</l>
     <l n="121">"Where safe, thy blandishments it may partake,</l>
     <l n="122">" And oh! be tender for its mother's sake.</l>
     <l n="123">"Wilt thou? —</l>
     <l n="124">" I know thou wilt — sad silence speaks assent,</l>
     <l n="125">"And in that pleasing hope thy EMMA dies content."</l>
     <l n="126">I, who with more than manly strength have bore</l>
     <l n="127">The various ills impos'd by cruel Fate,</l>
     <l n="128">Sustain the firmness of my soul no more,</l>
     <l n="129">But sink beneath the weight:</l>
     <l n="130">Just Heaven (I cry'd) from Memory's earliest day</l>
     <l n="131">No comfort has thy wretched suppliant known,</l>
     <l n="132">Misfortune still with unrelenting sway</l>
     <l n="133">Has claim'd me for her own.</l>
     <l n="134">But O — in pity to my grief, restore</l>
     <l n="135">This only source of bliss; I ask — I ask no more —</l>
     <l n="136">Vain hope — th' irrevocable doom is past,</l>
     <l n="137">Ev'n now she looks — she sighs her last —</l>
     <l n="138">Vainly I strive to stay her fleeting breath,</l>
     <l n="139">And, with rebellious heart, protest against her death.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="140">When the stern tyrant clos'd her lovely eyes,</l>
     <l n="141">How did I rave, untaught to bear the blow!</l>
     <l n="142">With impious wish to tear her from the skies;</l>
     <l n="143">How curse my fate in bitterness of woe!</l>
     <l n="144">But whither would this dreadful frenzy lead?</l>
     <l n="145">Fond man, forbear,</l>
     <l n="146">Thy fruitless sorrow spare,</l>
     <l n="147">Dare not to task what Heaven's high will decreed;</l>
     <l n="148">In humble reverence kiss th' afflictive rod,</l>
     <l n="149">And prostrate bow to an offended God.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="150">Perhaps kind Heaven in mercy dealt the blow,</l>
     <l n="151">Some saving truth thy roving soul to teach;</l>
     <l n="152">To wean thy heart from groveling views below,</l>
     <l n="153">And point out bliss beyond Misfortune's reach:</l>
     <l n="154">To shew that all the flattering schemes of joy,</l>
     <l n="155">Which towering Hope so fondly builds in air,</l>
     <l n="156">One fatal moment can destroy,</l>
     <l n="157">And plunge th' exulting Maniac in despair.</l>
     <l n="158">Then O! with pious fortitude sustain</l>
     <l n="159">Thy present loss — haply, thy future gain;</l>
     <l n="160">Nor let thy EMMA die in vain;</l>
     <l n="161">Time shall administer its wonted balm,</l>
     <l n="162">And hush this storm of grief to no unpleasing calm.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="163">Thus the poor bird, by some disastrous fate</l>
     <l n="164">Caught and imprison'd in a lonely cage,</l>
     <l n="165">Torn from its native fields, and dearer mate,</l>
     <l n="166">Flutters awhile, and spends its little rage:</l>
     <l n="167">But, finding all its efforts weak and vain,</l>
     <l n="168">No more it pants and rages for the plain;</l>
     <l n="169">Moping awhile, in sullen mood</l>
     <l n="170">Droops the sweet mourner — but, ere long,</l>
     <l n="171">Prunes its light wings, and pecks its food,</l>
     <l n="172">And meditates the song:</l>
     <l n="173">Serenely sorrowing, breathes its piteous case,</l>
     <l n="174">And with its plaintive warblings saddens all the place.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="175">Forgive me, Heaven — yet — yet the tears will flow,</l>
     <l n="176">To think how soon my scene of bliss is past!</l>
     <l n="177">My budding joys just promising to blow,</l>
     <l n="178">All nipt and wither'd by one envious blast!</l>
     <l n="179">My hours, that laughing wont to fleet away,</l>
     <l n="180">Move heavily along;</l>
     <l n="181">Where's now the sprightly jest, the jocund song;</l>
     <l n="182">Time creeps unconscious of delight:</l>
     <l n="183">How shall I cheat the tedious day?</l>
     <l n="184">And O — the joyless night!</l>
     <l n="185">Where shall I rest my weary head?</l>
     <l n="186">How shall I find repose on a sad widow'd bed?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="187">Come, Theban drug, the wretch's only aid,</l>
     <l n="188">To my torn heart its former peace restore;</l>
     <l n="189">Thy votary wrapp'd in thy Lethean shade,</l>
     <l n="190">Awhile shall cease his sorrows to deplore:</l>
     <l n="191">Haply when lock'd in Sleep's embrace,</l>
     <l n="192">Again I shall behold my EMMA's face;</l>
     <l n="193">Again with transport hear</l>
     <l n="194">Her voice soft whispering in my ear;</l>
     <l n="195">May steal once more a balmy kiss,</l>
     <l n="196">And taste at least of visionary bliss.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="197">But ah! the unwelcome morn's obtruding light</l>
     <l n="198">Will all my shadowy schemes of bliss depose,</l>
     <l n="199">Will tear the dear illusion from my sight,</l>
     <l n="200">And wake me to the sense of all my woes:</l>
     <l n="201">If to the verdant fields I stray,</l>
     <l n="202">Alas! what pleasures now can these convey?</l>
     <l n="203">Her lovely form pursues where-e'er I go,</l>
     <l n="204">And darkens all the scene with woe.</l>
     <l n="205">By Nature's lavish bounties chear'd no more,</l>
     <l n="206">Sorrowing I rove</l>
     <l n="207">Thro' valley, grot, and grove;</l>
     <l n="208">Nought can their beauties or my loss restore;</l>
     <l n="209">No herb, no plant, can medicine my disease,</l>
     <l n="210">And my sad sighs are borne on every passing breeze.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="211">Sickness and sorrow hovering round my bed,</l>
     <l n="212">Who now with anxious haste shall bring relief,</l>
     <l n="213">With lenient hand support my drooping head,</l>
     <l n="214">Asswage my pains, and mitigate my grief?</l>
     <l n="215">Should worldly business call away,</l>
     <l n="216">Who now shall in my absence fondly mourn,</l>
     <l n="217">Count every minute of the loitering day,</l>
     <l n="218">Impatient for my quick return?</l>
     <l n="219">Should aught my bosom discompose,</l>
     <l n="220">Who now with sweet complacent air,</l>
     <l n="221">Shall smooth the rugged brow of Care,</l>
     <l n="222">And soften all my woes?</l>
     <l n="223">Too faithful Memory — Cease, O cease —</l>
     <l n="224">How shall I e'er regain my peace?</l>
     <l n="225">(O to forget her) — but how vain each art,</l>
     <l n="226">Whilst every virtue lives imprinted on my heart.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="227">And thou, my little cherub, left behind,</l>
     <l n="228">To hear a father's plaints, to share his woes,</l>
     <l n="229">When Reason's dawn informs thy infant mind,</l>
     <l n="230">And thy sweet-lisping tongue shall ask the cause,</l>
     <l n="231">How oft with sorrow shall mine eyes run o'er,</l>
     <l n="232">When, twining round my knees, I trace</l>
     <l n="233">Thy mother's smile upon thy face?</l>
     <l n="234">How oft to my full heart shalt thou restore</l>
     <l n="235">Sad memory of my joys — ah now no more!</l>
     <l n="236">By blessings once enjoy'd now more distrest,</l>
     <l n="237">More beggar by the riches once possest.</l>
     <l n="238">My little darling! — dearer to me grown</l>
     <l n="239">By all the tears thou'st caus'd — (O strange to hear!)</l>
     <l n="240">Bought with a life yet dearer than thy own,</l>
     <l n="241">Thy cradle purchas'd with thy mother's bier:</l>
     <l n="242">Who now shall seek with fond delight,</l>
     <l n="243">Thy infant steps to guide aright?</l>
     <l n="244">She, who with doating eyes, would gaze</l>
     <l n="245">On all thy little artless ways,</l>
     <l n="246">By all thy soft endearments blest,</l>
     <l n="247">And clasp thee oft with transport to her breast,</l>
     <l n="248">Alas! is gone — Yet shalt thou prove</l>
     <l n="249">A father's dearest, tenderest love:</l>
     <l n="250">And O! sweet senseless smiler (envied state!)</l>
     <l n="251">As yet unconscious of thy hapless fate,</l>
     <l n="252">When years thy judgment shall mature,</l>
     <l n="253">And Reason shews those ills it cannot cure,</l>
     <l n="254">Wilt thou, a father's grief to asswage,</l>
     <l n="255">For virtue prove the Phoenix of the earth?</l>
     <l n="256">(Like her, thy mother dy'd to give thee birth)</l>
     <l n="257">And be the comfort of my age!</l>
     <l n="258">When sick and languishing I lie,</l>
     <l n="259">Wilt thou my EMMA's wonted care supply?</l>
     <l n="260">And oft, as, to thy listening ear,</l>
     <l n="261">Thy mother's virtues and her fate I tell,</l>
     <l n="262">Say, wilt thou drop the tender tear,</l>
     <l n="263">Whilst on the mournful theme I dwell?</l>
     <l n="264">Then, fondly stealing to thy father's side,</l>
     <l n="265">Whene'er thou seest the soft distress,</l>
     <l n="266">Which I would vainly seek to hide,</l>
     <l n="267">Say, wilt thou strive to make it less?</l>
     <l n="268">To sooth my sorrows all thy cares employ,</l>
     <l n="269">And in my cup of grief infuse one drop of joy?</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>