<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>AN EVENING ADDRESS TO A NIGHTINGALE.</title>
    <author>Cuthbert Shaw</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">6</measure>
    <measure unit="line">108</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Cuthbert Shaw_an-evening-address-to-a-nighti</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>AN EVENING ADDRESS TO A NIGHTINGALE.</title>
     <author>Cuthbert Shaw</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>AN EVENING ADDRESS TO A NIGHTINGALE.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">SWEET bird! that kindly perching near,</l>
     <l n="2">Pourest thy plaints melodious in mine ear,</l>
     <l n="3">Not, like base worldlings, tutor'd to forego</l>
     <l n="4">The melancholy haunts of Woe,</l>
     <l n="5">Thanks for thy sorrow-soothing strain: —</l>
     <l n="6">For surely, thou hast known to prove,</l>
     <l n="7">Like me, the pangs of hapless love,</l>
     <l n="8">Else why so feelingly complain,</l>
     <l n="9">And with thy piteous notes thus sadden all the grove?</l>
     <l n="10">Say, dost thou mourn thy ravish'd mate,</l>
     <l n="11">That oft enamour'd on thy strains has hung?</l>
     <l n="12">Or has the cruel hand of Fate</l>
     <l n="13">Bereft thee of thy darling young?</l>
     <l n="14">Alas, for BOTH, I weep —</l>
     <l n="15">In all the pride of youthful charms,</l>
     <l n="16">A beauteous bride torn from my circling arms!</l>
     <l n="17">A lovely babe that should have liv'd to bless,</l>
     <l n="18">And fill my doating eyes with frequent tears,</l>
     <l n="19">At once the source of rapture and distress,</l>
     <l n="20">The flattering prop of my declining years!</l>
     <l n="21">In vain from death to rescue I essay'd,</l>
     <l n="22">By every art that Science could devise,</l>
     <l n="23">Alas! it languish'd for a mother's aid,</l>
     <l n="24">And wing'd its flight to seek her in the skies —</l>
     <l n="25">Then O our comforts be the same,</l>
     <l n="26">At evening's peaceful hour,</l>
     <l n="27">To shun the noisy paths of wealth and fame,</l>
     <l n="28">And breathe our sorrows in this lonely bower.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="29">But why alas! to thee complain!</l>
     <l n="30">To thee — unconscious of my pain!</l>
     <l n="31">Soon shalt THOU cease to mourn thy lot severe,</l>
     <l n="32">And hail the dawning of a happier year:</l>
     <l n="33">The genial warmth of joy-renewing spring</l>
     <l n="34">Again shall plume thy shatter'd wing;</l>
     <l n="35">Again thy little heart shall transport prove,</l>
     <l n="36">Again shall slow thy notes responsive to thy love:</l>
     <l n="37">But O for ME in vain may seasons roll,</l>
     <l n="38">Nought can dry up the fountain of my tears,</l>
     <l n="39">Deploring still the COMFORT OF MY SOUL,</l>
     <l n="40">I count my sorrows by encreasing years.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="41">Tell me, thou Syren Hope, deceiver, say,</l>
     <l n="42">Where is the promis'd period of my woes?</l>
     <l n="43">Full three long, lingering years have roll'd away,</l>
     <l n="44">And yet I weep, a stranger to repose:</l>
     <l n="45">O what delusion did thy tongue employ!</l>
     <l n="46">"That EMMA's fatal pledge of love,</l>
     <l n="47">" Her last bequest — with all a mother's care,</l>
     <l n="48">"The bitterness of sorrow should remove,</l>
     <l n="49">" Soften the horrors of despair,</l>
     <l n="50">"And chear a heart long lost to joy!"</l>
     <l n="51">How oft, when fondling in mine arms,</l>
     <l n="52">Gazing enraptur'd on its angel-face,</l>
     <l n="53">My soul the maze of Fate would vainly trace,</l>
     <l n="54">And burn with all a father's fond alarms!</l>
     <l n="55">And O what flattering scenes had Fancy feign'd,</l>
     <l n="56">How did I rave of blessings yet in store!</l>
     <l n="57">Till every aching sense was sweetly pain'd,</l>
     <l n="58">And my full heart could bear, nor tongue could utter more. —</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="59">"Just Heaven, I cry'd" — with recent hopes elate,</l>
     <l n="60">"Yet I will live — will live, tho' EMMA's dead —</l>
     <l n="61">" So long bow'd down beneath the storms of Fate,</l>
     <l n="62">"Yet will I raise my woe-dejected head!</l>
     <l n="63">" My little EMMA, now my ALL,</l>
     <l n="64">"Will want a father's care,</l>
     <l n="65">" Her looks, her wants my rash resolves recal,</l>
     <l n="66">"And for her sake the ills of life I'll bear:</l>
     <l n="67">" And oft together we'll complain,</l>
     <l n="68">"Complaint, the only bliss my soul can know,</l>
     <l n="69">" From me, my child shall learn the mournful strain,</l>
     <l n="70">"And prattle tales of woe;</l>
     <l n="71">" And O in that auspicious hour,</l>
     <l n="72">"When Fate resigns her persecuting power,</l>
     <l n="73">" With duteous zeal her hand shall close,</l>
     <l n="74">"No more to weep — my sorrow-streaming eyes,</l>
     <l n="75">" When death gives misery repose,</l>
     <l n="76">"And opes a glorious passage to the skies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="77">Vain thought! it must not be — She too is dead —</l>
     <l n="78">The flattering scene is o'er —</l>
     <l n="79">My hopes for ever — ever fled —</l>
     <l n="80">And vengeance can no more —</l>
     <l n="81">Crush'd by misfortune — blasted by disease —</l>
     <l n="82">And none — none left to bear a friendly part!</l>
     <l n="83">To meditate my welfare, health, or ease,</l>
     <l n="84">Or sooth the anguish of an aching heart!</l>
     <l n="85">Now all one gloomy scene, till welcome death,</l>
     <l n="86">With lenient hand (O falsly deem'd severe)</l>
     <l n="87">Shall kindly stop my grief-exhausted breath,</l>
     <l n="88">And dry up every tear:</l>
     <l n="89">Perhaps, obsequious to my will,</l>
     <l n="90">But ah! from my affections far remov'd!</l>
     <l n="91">The last sad office strangers may fulfil,</l>
     <l n="92">As if I ne'er had been belov'd;</l>
     <l n="93">As if, unconscious of poetic fire,</l>
     <l n="94">I ne'er had touch'd the trembling lyre,</l>
     <l n="95">As if my niggard hand ne'er dealt relief,</l>
     <l n="96">Nor my heart melted at another's grief.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="97">Yet — while this weary life shall last,</l>
     <l n="98">While yet my tongue can form the impassion'd strain,</l>
     <l n="99">In piteous accents shall the Muse complain,</l>
     <l n="100">And dwell with fond delay on blessings past:</l>
     <l n="101">For O how grateful to a wounded heart,</l>
     <l n="102">The tale of misery to impart!</l>
     <l n="103">From others' eyes bid artless sorrows flow,</l>
     <l n="104">And raise esteem upon the base of woe!</l>
     <l n="105">Even HE, the noblest of the tuneful throng,</l>
     <l n="106">Shall deign my love lorn tale to hear,</l>
     <l n="107">Shall catch the soft contagion of my song,</l>
     <l n="108">And pay my pensive Muse the tribute of a tear.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>