<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>THE LOVE OF GAIN.</title>
    <author>Matthew Gregory Lewis</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">33</measure>
    <measure unit="line">469</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Matthew Gregory Lewis_the-love-of-gain</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>THE LOVE OF GAIN.</title>
     <author>Matthew Gregory Lewis</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>THE LOVE OF GAIN.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="1">THOUGH oft the heart, when raging passions storm,</l>
     <l n="2">To Vice we kneel, and fain would veil her form,</l>
     <l n="3">Her native darkness ever mocks disguise,</l>
     <l n="4">And crimes look foul, e'en in their author's eyes.</l>
     <l n="5">Here the first mark of heav'nly vengeance view;</l>
     <l n="6">Vice, false to others, to herself is true!</l>
     <l n="7">When the pack'd jury, and the quibbled flaw</l>
     <l n="8">Delude the eye, and lame the arm of law;</l>
     <l n="9">When Erskine's wit the culprit-client saves,</l>
     <l n="10">And fraud unscourged offended justice braves;</l>
     <l n="11">Still is the wretch in private doom'd to hear</l>
     <l n="12">From his own heart a verdict more severe.</l>
     <l n="13">There dwells a judge, whose voice no bribe can pay,</l>
     <l n="14">No party silence, and no flattery sway;</l>
     <l n="15">The sinner shrinks, before himself arraign'd,</l>
     <l n="16">And almost sorrows, that his cause is gain'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="17">Nor does his guilt himself alone disgust;</l>
     <l n="18">The world condemns, for here the world is just:</l>
     <l n="19">Unpunish'd crimes still shock the public ear,</l>
     <l n="20">And crimes unpunish'd doubly foul appear.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="21">Then why, Emilius, thus in furious strain</l>
     <l n="22">Of broken faith, and laws corrupt complain?</l>
     <l n="23">Less warmth, my testy friend; more justly sound</l>
     <l n="24">Your injury's depth, nor call your scratch a wound.</l>
     <l n="25">With plenteous store by Fortune's bounty blest,</l>
     <l n="26">Of bonds, and stock, and fertile lands possest,</l>
     <l n="27">Your loss is trifling, and so trite your case,</l>
     <l n="28">Scarce in the public prints 'twill find a place.</l>
     <l n="29">While, then, we mark your breast with passion rise,</l>
     <l n="30">Your trembling lips, clench'd hands, and flashing eyes,</l>
     <l n="31">When ask'd the cause, how poor the answer sounds,</l>
     <l n="32">"A friend is false! I've lost a thousand pounds. " —</l>
     <l n="33">A friend is false? Does that amaze the eye</l>
     <l n="34">Which lately saw its sixtieth year go by?</l>
     <l n="35">Has age then bleach'd your raven locks in vain,</l>
     <l n="36">Impair'd your limbs, and not matur'd your brain?</l>
     <l n="37">Oh! mourn your dross no more: with tears lament</l>
     <l n="38">Your mind unfurnish'd, and your time mispent.</l>
     <l n="39">Blest is the man, whom philosophic lore</l>
     <l n="40">Beyond proud Fortune's reach has taught to soar;</l>
     <l n="41">Who, when she frowns, her falshood not reviles,</l>
     <l n="42">Nor boasts her favour when the harlot smiles.</l>
     <l n="43">Nor him less happy count, whose years have bought</l>
     <l n="44">Precious experience, and deep-searching thought,</l>
     <l n="45">Wisdom to know all bliss is insecure,</l>
     <l n="46">Courage to hope, and patience to endure.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="47">Say, loud complainant, does the rolling year</l>
     <l n="48">Present one day from fraud or knavery clear,</l>
     <l n="49">Whose spotless White no thefts, no murders stain,</l>
     <l n="50">Writing in blood man's damning lust for gain?</l>
     <l n="51">In vain you search: — yet still the search pursue,</l>
     <l n="52">Examine men, and find of good how few!</l>
     <l n="53">So few, alas! that if that guilt to fly</l>
     <l n="54">Which daily, hourly, here disgusts the eye,</l>
     <l n="55">The just resolv'd to leave the British strand,</l>
     <l n="56">And seek some distant less polluted land,</l>
     <l n="57">The whole fair troop away with ease might bear</l>
     <l n="58">My lord-mayor's barge, and still have room to spare.</l>
     <l n="59">Now let the iron age no more be blam'd;</l>
     <l n="60">Blest should its memory be, when ours is nam'd,</l>
     <l n="61">For which no bard can find in nature's page</l>
     <l n="62">So base a metal as would mark the age!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="63">Yet though ourselves still sin, not less we blame</l>
     <l n="64">Our neighbour's sin, and, when  errs, exclaim</l>
     <l n="65">Louder than fishwives scold, or asses bray,</l>
     <l n="66">Or Vapid puffs his own dry dull damn'd play!</l>
     <l n="67">All-hail, mouth-virtue! at your altar bend</l>
     <l n="68">Each canting hypocrite, and perjur'd friend;</l>
     <l n="69">Spare Lovegold sees his houshold god in you,</l>
     <l n="70">Who cost no sixpence, and who seem Peru!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="71">Boy-witted Elder! must thou still be told,</l>
     <l n="72">No sorcerer's spell can witch an heart like gold?</l>
     <l n="73">That in each guinea conqu'ring Cupids swarm,</l>
     <l n="74">And Venus less than good King George can charm?</l>
     <l n="75">Hear you not, how the rude but wiser crowd</l>
     <l n="76">Mock your simplicity with laughter loud,</l>
     <l n="77">When raving about faith, and virtuous dread,</l>
     <l n="78">And lightnings destin'd for each perjur'd head,</l>
     <l n="79">You hope the traitor (by your threats dismay'd)</l>
     <l n="80">keep the promise, which he  evade?</l>
     <l n="81">If such things were, 'twas sure ere Adam fell,</l>
     <l n="82">Or Eve lost Eden for a nonpareil!</l>
     <l n="83">But now a debt if some strange man should own,</l>
     <l n="84">When neither bond or witness prove the loan,</l>
     <l n="85">To mark an act so just, and truth so rare,</l>
     <l n="86">His marble form should grace some public square,</l>
     <l n="87">And his name blazon'd in the historic page,</l>
     <l n="88">Attest that one good man adorn'd our age.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="89">For me, whene'er such acts of faith I hear,</l>
     <l n="90">Lost in amaze, and trusting scarce mine ear,</l>
     <l n="91">"Let all," I cry, "to view this wonder run,</l>
     <l n="92">" And Pidcock own his rarities outdone.</l>
     <l n="93">"Mourn, hapless Pidcock, mourn! your reign is o'er;</l>
     <l n="94">" In vain your eagles scream, and tigers roar;</l>
     <l n="95">"The crowds, who erst to view your monsters ran,</l>
     <l n="96">" Now seek a rarer sight, an honest man!</l>
     <l n="97">"What drinks, what eats he? for I ne'er can think,</l>
     <l n="98">" Like common mortals he can eat or drink.</l>
     <l n="99">"How speaks, how walks he? ere I sleep to-night,</l>
     <l n="100">" On this rare creature I must feast my sight. "</l>
     <l n="101">And when, at length, this wonder I behold,</l>
     <l n="102">Amaz'd to find him cast in human mould,</l>
     <l n="103">I'm vex'd that like ourselves on earth he treads,</l>
     <l n="104">And scarce believe he hasn't got two heads.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="105">But say, Emilius, if a wrong thus slight</l>
     <l n="106">So wounds thy feelings and disgusts thy sight,</l>
     <l n="107">How wouldst thou rave, if Fraud's glib tongue had found</l>
     <l n="108">The means to 'reave thee of thy last poor pound;</l>
     <l n="109">Or how support a friend's more guilty stealth,</l>
     <l n="110">When loss of freedom follows loss of wealth?</l>
     <l n="111">Turn to yon prison! list yon captive's tale,</l>
     <l n="112">Who rashly stood his smooth-tongu'd brother's bail:</l>
     <l n="113">Pent in those walls, the wretch all hope resigns,</l>
     <l n="114">Now wildly raves, and now dejected pines;</l>
     <l n="115">While his free life abroad the debtor spends,</l>
     <l n="116">Enjoys new pleasure, and defrauds new friends.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="117">Oh! but  wretch so wondrous well deceiv'd,</l>
     <l n="118">Suspicion's self had sure his faith believ'd!</l>
     <l n="119">He swore such oaths! .....</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="120">He swore! did that prevail,</l>
     <l n="121">And wert thou blinded by a trick so stale?</l>
     <l n="122">Oaths now are trifles few refuse to take,</l>
     <l n="123">Easy to form, and easier still to break;</l>
     <l n="124">Their perjur'd vows but few with horror scan;</l>
     <l n="125">But few fear heavenly wrath, if safe from man,</l>
     <l n="126">Or shuddering think, their guilt that angels know,</l>
     <l n="127">The secret sin a secret still below.</l>
     <l n="128">Mark'd you, when late your cause in court was tried,</l>
     <l n="129">And your false friend his lawful debt denied,</l>
     <l n="130">One slight convulsion, or one transient blush</l>
     <l n="131">Bid his lip quiver, or his forehead flush?</l>
     <l n="132">Falter'd his tongue, when, lost all sacred fear,</l>
     <l n="133">On God he call'd to prove his words sincere;</l>
     <l n="134">And wish'd, if just your charge, to curse his sin</l>
     <l n="135">Flames might consume himself and all his kin?</l>
     <l n="136">No! such his earnest air, and changeless face,</l>
     <l n="137">Each word, each look such candour seem'd to grace,</l>
     <l n="138">So firm his voice, so bold and clear his eye,</l>
     <l n="139">Yourself could scarce believe his tale a lye!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="140">'Tis true! 'tis true! with horror struck I heard</l>
     <l n="141">The unblushing villain speak the damning word.</l>
     <l n="142">Gods! how can man thus brave celestial ire,</l>
     <l n="143">While heaven has justice, and while hell has fire!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="144">Alas! my friend, an awful truth to tell,</l>
     <l n="145">There are, who scorn that heaven, and mock that hell.</l>
     <l n="146">In vain for these alternate seasons reign,</l>
     <l n="147">Spring robes the fields, and Autumn swells the grain;</l>
     <l n="148">In vain the moon now gilds the brow of night,</l>
     <l n="149">And now the sun pours floods of glorious light:</l>
     <l n="150">"'Twas chance," they cry, "to those fair orbs gave birth,</l>
     <l n="151">" And chance alone with produce bless'd the earth! "</l>
     <l n="152">Then boldly on the sacred book they lay</l>
     <l n="153">Their lips to swear some good man's wealth away,</l>
     <l n="154">And while his spoils their ravish'd eyes bewitch,</l>
     <l n="155">Laugh at poor rogues, less impious and less rich.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="156">Others, whom timid guilt forbids to climb</l>
     <l n="157">Those dreadful heights where Atheists soar sublime,</l>
     <l n="158">Own that a Power Supreme exists on high,</l>
     <l n="159">But while they own a power, that power defy.</l>
     <l n="160">To these the priest inspir'd describes in vain</l>
     <l n="161">Each promis'd pleasure, and each threaten'd pain:</l>
     <l n="162">Heaven's future joys their notice scarce seem worth,</l>
     <l n="163">Wealth in  world, their present heaven on earth,</l>
     <l n="164">Nor fear they to deserve the Eternal's curse,</l>
     <l n="165">Hell bad, 'tis true, but want of money worse!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="166">"Let wrath divine," thus Gripe in transport cries,</l>
     <l n="167">"Curse every limb, and quench my blasted eyes,</l>
     <l n="168">" If still harmonious sounds mine ears may drink,</l>
     <l n="169">"While in yon chest my counted guineas chink,</l>
     <l n="170">" And still my palsied hands have power to hold,</l>
     <l n="171">"Close to my heart, this bag of darling gold!</l>
     <l n="172">" What! shall I fear, indignant Heaven to see</l>
     <l n="173">"Its magazine of plagues exhaust on me?</l>
     <l n="174">" What! shall I mourn the bargain made, if wealth</l>
     <l n="175">"I buy with loss of fame, and loss of health?</l>
     <l n="176">" No, still with glad content my heart shall beat,</l>
     <l n="177">"Though tortures rack my hands, my eyes, my feet,</l>
     <l n="178">" If hoards of gold my bursting coffers fill,</l>
     <l n="179">"Gold, which can soothe each pang, each fear can still,</l>
     <l n="180">" Comfort for every care, and balm for every ill!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="181">"Yet why these fears? Celestial wrath, we know,</l>
     <l n="182">" Though just, is merciful; though fierce, is slow:</l>
     <l n="183">"Perhaps too, when arrives the avenging hour,</l>
     <l n="184">" Repentant prayers may calm Heaven's angry power;</l>
     <l n="185">"Nor always in the world's vast book we find</l>
     <l n="186">" To equal sin an equal doom assigned.</l>
     <l n="187">"Here see with honours crown'd, there'whelm'd with grief,</l>
     <l n="188">" The Indian spoiler, and the English thief;</l>
     <l n="189">"And mark, what varying fates their plunders stop</l>
     <l n="190">" Who robb'd a nation, and who robb'd a shop.</l>
     <l n="191">"Rascals alike, by Fortune's wayward sport</l>
     <l n="192">" One goes to Tyburn, t'other goes to Court;</l>
     <l n="193">"And while this rogue is doom'd in air to swing,</l>
     <l n="194">" That for a peerage kneels to thank the King. "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="195">The sophist's fears thus calm'd, the legal war</l>
     <l n="196">No more he dreads, but dauntless seeks the bar,</l>
     <l n="197">Arrives before you, wonders why you stay,</l>
     <l n="198">And cries — "Sure conscience makes the wretch delay!"</l>
     <l n="199">Caught by his tranquil air and front of brass,</l>
     <l n="200">(Oft does for innocence assurance pass)</l>
     <l n="201">The judge declares your charge must groundless be,</l>
     <l n="202">Its malice blames, and sets the prisoner free;</l>
     <l n="203">While you with fiercer rage assert your cause,</l>
     <l n="204">And term the judge corrupt, unjust the laws,</l>
     <l n="205">Than Sappho felt when Drury damn'd her work,</l>
     <l n="206">Or Gallia's struggles rais'd in zealous Burke!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="207">Yet now, Emilius, let my prayers assuage</l>
     <l n="208">Awhile this flood of grief, this storm of rage,</l>
     <l n="209">Nor scorn my counsel, though from one it flows,</l>
     <l n="210">Whose life few years, whose brain small judgment knows:</l>
     <l n="211">lack of temper suits  lack of wit,</l>
     <l n="212">And boyish griefs with boyish counsels fit.</l>
     <l n="213">When amputation risques a patient's life,</l>
     <l n="214">Some skilful hand should guide the surgeon's knife;</l>
     <l n="215">But who to bleed him Farquhar need retain,</l>
     <l n="216">When the next barber's boy could breathe the vein?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="217">Mark then! — If what you mourn, were some dire ill</l>
     <l n="218">No partner suffer'd, and no time could still;</l>
     <l n="219">If some strange curse, some plague to nature new,</l>
     <l n="220">On  had fall'n, and fall'n on none but you,</l>
     <l n="221">No word of mine should mock your publish'd pain,</l>
     <l n="222">Or strive to bind your wrath in reason's chain.</l>
     <l n="223">Who knows the human heart, must also know</l>
     <l n="224">How keen the pangs which make your sorrows flow:</l>
     <l n="225">Not with those sighs, which heave the nephew's heart,</l>
     <l n="226">Who sees his hoarding uncle's life depart;</l>
     <l n="227">Not with those tears, which custom bids be shed</l>
     <l n="228">By youthful widows for old husbands dead;</l>
     <l n="229">Grieve they, who dear departing wealth behold,</l>
     <l n="230">And mourn, not loss of friends, but loss of gold.</l>
     <l n="231">No forc'd affliction bids  sorrows rise;</l>
     <l n="232">need no onion to provoke their eyes;</l>
     <l n="233">No! — Lost that idol most adored and dear,</l>
     <l n="234">Heart-felt despair, wild rage, and grief sincere</l>
     <l n="235">Burst in each bitter sigh, gush in each scalding tear.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="236">Yet sure, my friend, 'tis wrong, unusual rage</l>
     <l n="237">To feel at crimes so usual in this age,</l>
     <l n="238">Unless your lot by fate you hoped design'd</l>
     <l n="239">Free from all crosses common to mankind.</l>
     <l n="240">Alas! ere beat your breast, ere rent your hair,</l>
     <l n="241">Weigh, what you bear yourself, what others bear.</l>
     <l n="242">No pangs are yours past man's, past Heaven's relief,</l>
     <l n="243">No mighty mischiefs move this mighty grief;</l>
     <l n="244">Search but the world, then own your wrongs how small</l>
     <l n="245">Placed near those wrongs on other heads which fall.</l>
     <l n="246">Must I attest the fact? To prove how Vice</l>
     <l n="247">Reigns sovereign  one house can well suffice.</l>
     <l n="248">To Bow-street turn! —</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="20" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="249">Ye giddy, gay, and proud,</l>
     <l n="250">Who swell great London's ever-bustling crowd,</l>
     <l n="251">London, where all extremes together meet,</l>
     <l n="252">Folly's chief throne, and Wisdom's gravest seat;</l>
     <l n="253">Where disagreements in agreement lie,</l>
     <l n="254">Our close-knit mass of contrariety;</l>
     <l n="255">Where throng the rich and poor, the fool and knave,</l>
     <l n="256">Where statesmen juggle, and where patriots rave;</l>
     <l n="257">Where balls for advocates prepare their work,</l>
     <l n="258">And embryo law-suits in a whisper lurk;</l>
     <l n="259">Where Cupid pays in specie for his wiles,</l>
     <l n="260">And judges frown whene'er a lady smiles;</l>
     <l n="261">Where equal farce continual sport affords</l>
     <l n="262">At Covent-Garden, or the House of Lords;</l>
     <l n="263">Where beggars with feigned tears and ready smiles,</l>
     <l n="264">Cringe to St. James, or blubber to St. Giles;</l>
     <l n="265">Ye who confusedly sail in motley trim</l>
     <l n="266">Down this full flood of pleasure, business, whim,</l>
     <l n="267">Whether you frame smooth, glib, and specious lies</l>
     <l n="268">To cheat a tradesman, or to raise supplies,</l>
     <l n="269">With private or with public misery sport,</l>
     <l n="270">Cheats upon 'Change, or Parasites at Court,</l>
     <l n="271">Now pause awhile! — For one reflecting hour</l>
     <l n="272">Forego your hopes of gain, your dreams of power,</l>
     <l n="273">And hark, while tells the Muse what monstrous crimes,</l>
     <l n="274">What new-found sins reserv'd for our strange times,</l>
     <l n="275">Their hideous forms to Addington betray,</l>
     <l n="276">From morn's first languish to the death of day.</l>
     <l n="277">Here mark the thankless child, the unnatural sire,</l>
     <l n="278">The Pandar slave who lets his spouse for hire,</l>
     <l n="279">The adulterous friend, the trusted wanton wife,</l>
     <l n="280">The brother aiming at the brother's life,</l>
     <l n="281">The rake who cools in beauty's arms his heat,</l>
     <l n="282">Then lets her starve, or ply for bread the street,</l>
     <l n="283">And that dark train of foes to moral rules,</l>
     <l n="284">Thieves, Bawds, Assassins, Gamblers, Knaves, and Fools,</l>
     <l n="285">Fools, who would fain  knaves ...... No more I'll write,</l>
     <l n="286">Hence, odious forms, nor longer shock my sight!</l>
     <l n="287">Else by disgust and scorn to madness driven,</l>
     <l n="288">Bursting those chains which bind my soul to Heaven,</l>
     <l n="289">I shall disdain to breathe such tainted air,</l>
     <l n="290">Shall blush an human form like these to wear,</l>
     <l n="291">For present ease shall barter future bliss,</l>
     <l n="292">And sure no world can be more black than this,</l>
     <l n="293">Deep in my swelling heart shall plunge the knife,</l>
     <l n="294">And cry, while flies my soul from mortal strife,</l>
     <l n="295">"Heaven bless my father, though he gave me life!"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="21" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="296">Cease, wild enthusiast! end thy angry tale,</l>
     <l n="297">O'er human frailties drop compassion's veil;</l>
     <l n="298">View them with grief, not rage, nor dare to scan</l>
     <l n="299">With censure too severe thy fellow-man!</l>
     <l n="300">Think, had no parent watch'd thy pliant youth,</l>
     <l n="301">Curb'd thy wild passions, turn'd thy steps to Truth,</l>
     <l n="302">And taught thee by her radiant light to know</l>
     <l n="303">That bliss is virtue, and that guilt is woe,</l>
     <l n="304">Spurning restraint, and scorn'd each sacred vow,</l>
     <l n="305">Haply thyself had been what these are now;</l>
     <l n="306">These, who by headstrong passions forc'd away,</l>
     <l n="307">Or pressing want, or strong example's sway,</l>
     <l n="308">Strangers to love of man, or fear of God,</l>
     <l n="309">But trod perhaps those paths their parents trod,</l>
     <l n="310">While ignorance led them to that whirlpool's brink,</l>
     <l n="311">Where long they struggled, and where now they sink!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="22" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="312">Oh! view  lot, my soul, nor more repine</l>
     <l n="313">To bear those evils Fate has fix'd on mine;</l>
     <l n="314">Content, though many a grief my bosom wrings,</l>
     <l n="315">If still that bosom owns no conscious stings,</l>
     <l n="316">If still I know for others wounds to feel,</l>
     <l n="317">With pity view them, and with pleasure heal,</l>
     <l n="318">And still those pangs which cause so keen a smart,</l>
     <l n="319">Nor sour my temper, nor deprave my heart.</l>
     <l n="320">Yes! though by fate with heaviest sorrows curst,</l>
     <l n="321">From my pale lips no murmuring breath should burst,</l>
     <l n="322">If still my hand had power to raise the opprest,</l>
     <l n="323">And, though unblest myself, make others blest!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="23" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="324">That power, Emilius, still is yours! — Then why</l>
     <l n="325">Thus pants your bosom, and thus flames your eye?</l>
     <l n="326">Your gold, though lost .....</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="24" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="327">...... Nay, 'tis not gold which makes</l>
     <l n="328">This fury tear me; but my bile it shakes,</l>
     <l n="329">That still my lawful suit in vain I urge,</l>
     <l n="330">And still yon caitiff mocks the avenging scourge!</l>
     <l n="331">Could I but once his well-earn'd sufferings see! ....</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="25" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="332">And would his sufferings then bring wealth to thee?</l>
     <l n="333">Would with his blood gold to thy coffers run,</l>
     <l n="334">Or all his groans repay thee one pound one?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="26" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="335">Not so; but vengeance .....</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="27" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="336">...... Hush! — To mention fear</l>
     <l n="337">What thou must shame to speak, I shame to hear!</l>
     <l n="338">Base minds alone delight in vengeance find,</l>
     <l n="339">That low vile passion of a low vile mind!</l>
     <l n="340">Oh! think, when summoned to the throne of Heaven,</l>
     <l n="341">As thou forgav'st, so thou shalt be forgiven!</l>
     <l n="342">And think, what pangs would rack each throbbing nerve,</l>
     <l n="343">If God should judge us, as our faults deserve!</l>
     <l n="344">Say, at this moment should the perjur'd wretch,</l>
     <l n="345">Stung with remorse, his hands imploring stretch</l>
     <l n="346">Tow'rds thee for pardon, while with tears and groans</l>
     <l n="347">Thy foot he kisses, and his guilt he owns,</l>
     <l n="348">Should that foot spurn him? Would'st thou frown, and cry</l>
     <l n="349">"Back, sinner, to the flames thou fain would'st fly!"</l>
     <l n="350">'Twere nobler far, thy thirst of vengeance o'er,</l>
     <l n="351">To bid the sinner rise, and sin no more;</l>
     <l n="352">'Twere nobler far to play the Christian's part,</l>
     <l n="353">Aid struggling Conscience to secure his heart,</l>
     <l n="354">Confirm his faith, with hope inspire his breast,</l>
     <l n="355">And make him virtuous now, hereafter blest.</l>
     <l n="356">Then, when thou died'st, the transport thine would be</l>
     <l n="357">Proudly to boast — "God owes a soul to me!"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="28" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="358">But if revenge alone can please you, know,</l>
     <l n="359">E'en now, though law was blind, though justice slow,</l>
     <l n="360">More pangs he feels, his heart by conscience rent,</l>
     <l n="361">Than you could name, or mortal brain invent.</l>
     <l n="362">True, from his lips no 'plaints inform the crowd</l>
     <l n="363">What pains are his — deep are his groans, not loud;</l>
     <l n="364">True, from his eyes no streams of anguish roll,</l>
     <l n="365">His burning tears fall inwards on his soul:</l>
     <l n="366">There brood thy vipers, Conscious Guilt, and dart</l>
     <l n="367">With ceaseless spite their fangs into his heart;</l>
     <l n="368">There prints with bloodless stroke thy silent steel</l>
     <l n="369">Wounds, that no balm can ease, no time can heal!</l>
     <l n="370">Not all the pangs which Dante's visions swell,</l>
     <l n="371">No freezing limbo, and no fiery hell,</l>
     <l n="372">Surpass his torments, who still bears unblest</l>
     <l n="373">A self-accuser in his own sad breast.</l>
     <l n="374">Disgust, and ceaseless Care, and anxious Fear</l>
     <l n="375">Still share his bed, and at his board appear.</l>
     <l n="376">In vain his Cooks their various arts combine</l>
     <l n="377">Each dish to season, and each sauce refine;</l>
     <l n="378">Champagne's rich grape in vain, to chear his soul,</l>
     <l n="379">With brilliant bubbles fills his chrystal bowl:</l>
     <l n="380">The harpy Conscience pounces on her prey,</l>
     <l n="381">Tears from his hand the untasted food away,</l>
     <l n="382">And, ere the wine his pallid lips can pass,</l>
     <l n="383">Her gall-fraught tongue drops poison in his glass.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="29" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="384">Next mark, my friend, his slumbers! — If Repose</l>
     <l n="385">Lists to his suit, and bids his eye-lids close,</l>
     <l n="386">Mark what convulsions heave his martyr'd breast,</l>
     <l n="387">And frequent starts, and heart-drawn sighs attest,</l>
     <l n="388">Though Nature grants him sleep, that Guilt denies him rest.</l>
     <l n="389">Now groans of tortur'd ghosts his ear affright;</l>
     <l n="390">Now ghastly phantoms dance before his sight;</l>
     <l n="391">And now he sees (and screams in frantic fear)</l>
     <l n="392">To size gigantic swell'd thy angry shade appear!</l>
     <l n="393">Swift at thy summons rush with hideous yell</l>
     <l n="394">Their prey to seize the Denizens of hell!</l>
     <l n="395">Headlong they hurl him on some ice-rock's point,</l>
     <l n="396">Mangle each limb, and dislocate each joint;</l>
     <l n="397">Or plunge him deep in blue sulphureous lakes;</l>
     <l n="398">Or lash his quivering flesh with twisted snakes;</l>
     <l n="399">Or in his brain their burning talons dart;</l>
     <l n="400">Or from his bosom rend his panting heart</l>
     <l n="401">To bathe their fiery lips in guilty gore! —</l>
     <l n="402">Then starts he from his couch, while dews of horror pour</l>
     <l n="403">Down his dank forehead — wrings his hands, and prays to sleep no more.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="30" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="404">Hark! the Storm-daemon shrieks! — It thunders! — Lo!</l>
     <l n="405">How pale his cheeks, how wild his eye-balls grow,</l>
     <l n="406">Heard the first murmur; while he waits the crash,</l>
     <l n="407">And dreads to see the etherial meteors flash.</l>
     <l n="408">No shock of clouds, he thinks, no casual hand</l>
     <l n="409">Rolls the red bolt, or darts th' avenging brand;</l>
     <l n="410">'Tis Heaven's own voice in thunder bids him die,</l>
     <l n="411">And 'tis to blast him yon blue lightnings fly!</l>
     <l n="412">His fears were vain; the storm disperses; — true,</l>
     <l n="413">But who can answer what the next may do?</l>
     <l n="414">Though now sweet nature sleeps, and skies are fair,</l>
     <l n="415">Soon gathering clouds again may gloom the air;</l>
     <l n="416">Soon shafts divine, winged by celestial breath,</l>
     <l n="417">Again may glare, and the next shaft brings death!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="31" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="418">With ceaseless fears and conscious pangs opprest</l>
     <l n="419">By day, by night unknown one hour of rest,</l>
     <l n="420">Wasted his limbs, his strength and spirits fled,</l>
     <l n="421">Disease now chains him on her thorny bed.</l>
     <l n="422">The couch in crowds though Galen's sons surround,</l>
     <l n="423">His dire complaints deride their skill profound;</l>
     <l n="424">No med'cine brings relief, no pang is eas'd,</l>
     <l n="425">For who can medicine to a mind diseas'd?</l>
     <l n="426">Heaven's Lord alone! — "And shall I dare invoke</l>
     <l n="427">" With prayers that Power, whose holiest law I broke?</l>
     <l n="428">"In heaven still fresh my violated vow,</l>
     <l n="429">" Will angels heed my forced repentance now?</l>
     <l n="430">"Hence, idle thought! no prayers can now obtain</l>
     <l n="431">" Aid from insulted Heaven, and man's is vain! "</l>
     <l n="432">Thus cries the wretch, distraction in his eye,</l>
     <l n="433">Hopeless to live, yet unprepared to die;</l>
     <l n="434">By fear his soul, by pain his body vext,</l>
     <l n="435">By conscience tortured, and by doubt perplext,</l>
     <l n="436">Loathing this world, and shuddering at the next.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="32" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="437">Yet though his old offence thus brands with shame</l>
     <l n="438">His conscious forehead, and unmans his frame,</l>
     <l n="439">When some new sin excites his impious zeal,</l>
     <l n="440">His heart is adamant, his nerves are steel:</l>
     <l n="441">Nor think, your perjur'd friend, reform'd by time,</l>
     <l n="442">Will bound his forfeits to this single crime.</l>
     <l n="443">The rose of innocence, once rent away,</l>
     <l n="444">No more shall grace his brow. And who can say,</l>
     <l n="445">"One step, and then no further?" — This first sin</l>
     <l n="446">Crown'd with success, ere long his feet shall win</l>
     <l n="447">To loftier heights of vice, and urge his fate</l>
     <l n="448">From bad to worse, from little crimes to great,</l>
     <l n="449">Till his broad guilt for public vengeance calls,</l>
     <l n="450">And to the laws his life a victim falls.</l>
     <l n="451">Then shalt thou own (and blush at thy mistrust),</l>
     <l n="452">Crimes still are punish'd, and God still is just!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="33" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="453">Here break we off! — Speed thou to Lombard-street,</l>
     <l n="454">Or plod the gambling 'Change with busy feet,</l>
     <l n="455">'Midst Bulls and Bears some false report to spread,</l>
     <l n="456">Of Prussia armed, or Buonaparte dead,</l>
     <l n="457">From specious lies an  gain to draw,</l>
     <l n="458">And spoil some wretch in forms allowed by law;</l>
     <l n="459">More dupes to find, more knavish tricks to learn,</l>
     <l n="460">And fooled thyself, fool others in thy turn:</l>
     <l n="461">While I, sequestered in some favourite nook,</l>
     <l n="462">Or guide the pencil, or explore the book,</l>
     <l n="463">Blest, if still free from mad Ambition's dreams,</l>
     <l n="464">Youth's vain rash hopes, and Interest's fordid schemes,</l>
     <l n="465">I sometimes hear, to chear my lonely hours,</l>
     <l n="466">The Muse awake her lute's harmonious powers,</l>
     <l n="467">And still can boast (when down life's vale I bend</l>
     <l n="468">My steps, nor grieved, nor glad my days to end),</l>
     <l n="469">A feeling heart, an open hand, content, and one true friend.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>