<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>A MONODY On the DEATH of Queen CAROLINE.</title>
    <author>Richard West</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">8</measure>
    <measure unit="line">137</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Richard West_a-monody-on-the-death-of-queen</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>A MONODY On the DEATH of Queen CAROLINE.</title>
     <author>Richard West</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>A MONODY On the DEATH of Queen CAROLINE.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">SING we no more of HYMENEAL lays,</l>
     <l n="2">Nor strew the land with myrtles and with bays:</l>
     <l n="3">The voice of joy is fled the BRITISH shore,</l>
     <l n="4">For CAROLINE'S no more:</l>
     <l n="5">And now our sorrows ask a sadder string;</l>
     <l n="6">Come, plaintive goddess of the Cyrrhan spring,</l>
     <l n="7">Pour thy deep note, and shed thy tuneful tear,</l>
     <l n="8">And, while we lose the memory of pain</l>
     <l n="9">In thy oblivious strain,</l>
     <l n="10">— Ah! drop thy cypress on yon mournful bier!</l>
     <l n="11">Begin: nor more delay</l>
     <l n="12">The sacred meed of gratitude to pay:</l>
     <l n="13">Begin: whate'er immortal song can do,</l>
     <l n="14">To the dear name of CAROLINE is due:</l>
     <l n="15">Who loves the Muse, deserves the Muse's love:</l>
     <l n="16">Then raise thy numbers high,</l>
     <l n="17">Sound out her glory to the throne of Jove,</l>
     <l n="18">Spread the glad voice thro' all the ambient sky,</l>
     <l n="19">From the dull marble vindicate her praise,</l>
     <l n="20">And waft it down to lighten future days.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="21">Ye bards to come, the song of truth attend:</l>
     <l n="22">This, this is she, the Muse's judge and friend!</l>
     <l n="23">The royal female! whose benignant hand</l>
     <l n="24">Throughout fair ALBION'S land</l>
     <l n="25">Dealt every useful, every decent part,</l>
     <l n="26">Each MEMPHIAN science, and each ATTICK art:</l>
     <l n="27">Within the Muse's bower</l>
     <l n="28">She oft was wont to lose the vacant hour,</l>
     <l n="29">Or underneath the sapient grot reclin'd,</l>
     <l n="30">Her soul to contemplation she resign'd,</l>
     <l n="31">And for awhile laid down</l>
     <l n="32">The painful, envied burthen of a crown:</l>
     <l n="33">Mean time thy rural ditty was not mute,</l>
     <l n="34">Sweet bard of MERLIN'S cave!</l>
     <l n="35">Tho' rude, thy ditty was of her, who gave</l>
     <l n="36">Thy voice to sing, and tun'd thy oaten flute</l>
     <l n="37">In strains unwonted to the ear of swain:</l>
     <l n="38">As when the lark, ambitious of the skies,</l>
     <l n="39">Quits the low harvest of the golden plain,</l>
     <l n="40">Taught by the sun's inspiring warmth to rise,</l>
     <l n="41">Sublime in air he spreads his dappled wings,</l>
     <l n="42">Mounts the blue aether, and in mounting sings.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="43">But whither wanders the licentious song?</l>
     <l n="44">Such joyous notes to happier days belong!</l>
     <l n="45">Ah me! our happier days are now no more: —</l>
     <l n="46">Return, sad Muse: see pale BRITANNIA weep,</l>
     <l n="47">See all the sisters of the subject deep</l>
     <l n="48">Their sovereign's loss deplore!</l>
     <l n="49">See fond IERNE gives her sorrows vent,</l>
     <l n="50">And as she tunes her brazen lyre to woe,</l>
     <l n="51">Indulge her grief to flow! —</l>
     <l n="52">See even the northern ORCADES lament!</l>
     <l n="53">Nor ends the wailing here:</l>
     <l n="54">Where-e'er beneath our flag wild Ocean roars,</l>
     <l n="55">From farthest ORIENT to HESPERIA'S shores,</l>
     <l n="56">From torrid AFFRICK to the world's cold end,</l>
     <l n="57">The BRITISH woes extend:</l>
     <l n="58">And every colony has dropt a tear.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="59">O honour'd flood! with reeds Pierian crown'd,</l>
     <l n="60">ISIS! whose argent waters glide along</l>
     <l n="61">Fair BELLOSITE'S Lycaean shades renown'd,</l>
     <l n="62">Now aid my feeble song;</l>
     <l n="63">And call thy chosen sons, and bid them bring</l>
     <l n="64">Their lays of DORICK air,</l>
     <l n="65">With lenient sounds to steal awhile from care</l>
     <l n="66">Th' inconsolable King:</l>
     <l n="67">O! sooth his anguish, and compose his pains</l>
     <l n="68">With artful unimaginable strains,</l>
     <l n="69">According sweetly to the golden lyre,</l>
     <l n="70">Such as might half inspire</l>
     <l n="71">The iron breast of HADES to resign</l>
     <l n="72">Our lost, lov'd CAROLINE.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="73">These are thy glorious deeds, almighty Death!</l>
     <l n="74">These are thy triumphs o'er the sons of men,</l>
     <l n="75">That now receive the miserable breath,</l>
     <l n="76">Which the next moment they resign again!</l>
     <l n="77">Ah me! what boots us all our boasted power,</l>
     <l n="78">Our golden treasure, and our purpled state?</l>
     <l n="79">They cannot ward th' inevitable hour,</l>
     <l n="80">Nor stay the fearful violence of Fate:</l>
     <l n="81">— Virtue herself shall fail:</l>
     <l n="82">Else now, if virtue ever could prevail,</l>
     <l n="83">Death had not dar'd to violate the throne,</l>
     <l n="84">Nor had BRITANNIA heard her sovereign groan.</l>
     <l n="85">— Ye nymphs! recall the song:</l>
     <l n="86">For heaven-born virtue does to heaven belong,</l>
     <l n="87">And scorns the meanest of her sons should die,</l>
     <l n="88">But opens him a passage to the sky;</l>
     <l n="89">Her rod ay-pointing to th' eternal goal,</l>
     <l n="90">From the brute earth she frees the ardent soul;</l>
     <l n="91">Swift from the vulgar herd aloft she springs,</l>
     <l n="92">Spurns the moist clay, and soars on azure wings,</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="93">Then hence with sorrows vain:</l>
     <l n="94">Ye Theban Muses! elevate the strain:</l>
     <l n="95">Search o'er the records of immortal fame,</l>
     <l n="96">And high refulgent on the female line,</l>
     <l n="97">Imblaze in starry characters the name</l>
     <l n="98">Of BRITISH CAROLINE:</l>
     <l n="99">While sacred story rings with SHEBA'S praise,</l>
     <l n="100">While BERENICE'S virtues still inspire</l>
     <l n="101">The CYRENEAN lyre,</l>
     <l n="102">And GLORIANA blooms in SPENSER'S lays;</l>
     <l n="103">Thy name, great Queen, shall glow in every page,</l>
     <l n="104">Shall dwell in every clime, and live in every age.</l>
     <l n="105">When GEORGE shall go, where WILLIAM went before,</l>
     <l n="106">And all the present world shall be no more;</l>
     <l n="107">When the fond factions of unjust mankind,</l>
     <l n="108">The mean, the mad, the envious, and the blind,</l>
     <l n="109">Shall turn to worms and dust;</l>
     <l n="110">Then Time, impartial judge, that states the price</l>
     <l n="111">Of each man's virtue, and of each man's vice,</l>
     <l n="112">From thy bright fame shall clear the cank'ring rust;</l>
     <l n="113">And O! the Muses ever shall be just.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="114">But lo! what sudden radiance gilds the skies?</l>
     <l n="115">'Tis Gratitude descending from above,</l>
     <l n="116">Known by the sweetness of her dove-like eyes,</l>
     <l n="117">Daughter of truth and universal love!</l>
     <l n="118">To HENRY'S sacred dome she wafts along,</l>
     <l n="119">And on thy tomb she pours</l>
     <l n="120">Celestial sweets and aramanthine flowers:</l>
     <l n="121">The old, the young, the rich, the wretched crowd</l>
     <l n="122">Numerous around her, and with accents loud</l>
     <l n="123">Raise the mix'd voice, and pour the grateful song:</l>
     <l n="124">"Hail Queen adorn'd by nature and by art!</l>
     <l n="125">"Thine was each virtue of the head and heart;</l>
     <l n="126">"Thy people blest thee, and thy children lov'd,</l>
     <l n="127">"And thy King honour'd, and thy God approv'd, "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="128">But here my labours cease:</l>
     <l n="129">'Tis time the foaming courser to release.</l>
     <l n="130">And thou, O royal shade,</l>
     <l n="131">Forgive the Muse that these vain honours paid;</l>
     <l n="132">A Muse as yet unheeded and unknown;</l>
     <l n="133">That dares to sacrifice to truth alone,</l>
     <l n="134">Not prone to blame, not hasty to commend,</l>
     <l n="135">No foe unjust, no mercenary friend,</l>
     <l n="136">No sensual bosom, no ungenerous mind,</l>
     <l n="137">And tho' not virtuous, virtuously inclin'd.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>