<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The FOX-CHACE. A Favourite Hunting Song, Sung at the grand Hunts of England.</title>
    <author>John O'Keeffe</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">4</measure>
    <measure unit="line">48</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>John O'Keeffe_the-fox-chace-a-favourite-hunt</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>The FOX-CHACE. A Favourite Hunting Song, Sung at the grand Hunts of England.</title>
     <author>John O'Keeffe</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>The FOX-CHACE. A Favourite Hunting Song, Sung at the grand Hunts of England.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="twelve-line">
     <l n="1">SOUTHERLY wind and a cloudy sky,</l>
     <l n="2">Proclaims a Hunting Morning,</l>
     <l n="3">Before the sun rises, we nimbly fly,</l>
     <l n="4">Dull sleep, and a downy-bed scorning,</l>
     <l n="5">To Horse my Boys, to Horse away;</l>
     <l n="6">The Chace admits of no delay,</l>
     <l n="7">On Horseback we're got, together we'll trot,</l>
     <l n="8">On Horseback we're got, together we trot,</l>
     <l n="9">Leave of your chat see the cover appear;</l>
     <l n="10">The Hound that strikes first cheer him without fear,</l>
     <l n="11">Drag on him! Ah wind him my steady good hounds</l>
     <l n="12">Drag on him! Ah wind him, the cover resounds.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2" stanza_type="twelve-line">
     <l n="13">How compleatly the Cover and Furz they draw,</l>
     <l n="14">Who talks of Barry or Meynell,</l>
     <l n="15">Young Lasher he flourishes now thro' the shaw;</l>
     <l n="16">And Saucebox roars out in his kennel,</l>
     <l n="17">Away we fly as quick as thought,</l>
     <l n="18">The new sown ground, soon makes them fault,</l>
     <l n="19">Cast round the sheeps train, cast round cast round,</l>
     <l n="20">Try back the deep lane, try back try back,</l>
     <l n="21">Hark I hear some hounds challenge in yonder spring sedge,</l>
     <l n="22">Comfort Bitch hits it off in that old thick hedge,</l>
     <l n="23">Hark forward hark forward have at him my Boys,</l>
     <l n="24">Hark forward, hark forward, zounds, don't make a noise.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3" stanza_type="twelve-line">
     <l n="25">A stormy sky overcharged with rain,</l>
     <l n="26">Both Hounds and Hunstman opposes,</l>
     <l n="27">In vain on your mettle you try boys in vain,</l>
     <l n="28">But down ye must to your noses,</l>
     <l n="29">Each moment now the sky grows worse,</l>
     <l n="30">Enough to make a Parson curse,</l>
     <l n="31">Pick through the plow'd grounds, pick through, pick through,</l>
     <l n="32">Well hunted good Hounds well hunted, well hunted,</l>
     <l n="33">If we can but get on, we shall soon make him quake</l>
     <l n="34">Hark I hear some hounds challenge in the midst of the brake,</l>
     <l n="35">Talio, Talio there across the green plain,</l>
     <l n="36">Talio, Talio, Boys have at him again.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4" stanza_type="twelve-line">
     <l n="37">Thus we ride whip and spur for a two hours Chace,</l>
     <l n="38">Our Horses go panting and sobbbing,</l>
     <l n="39">Young Madcap and Riot begin now race,</l>
     <l n="40">Ride on Sir and give him some mobbing,</l>
     <l n="41">But hold alass you'll spoil our sport,</l>
     <l n="42">For thro' the Hounds you'll head him short,</l>
     <l n="43">Clap round him dear Jack, clap round, clap round,</l>
     <l n="44">Hark Drummer hark back, hark back, hark back,</l>
     <l n="45">He's Jumping and dodging in every bush,</l>
     <l n="46">Little Riot has fastened her Teeth in his brush,</l>
     <l n="47">Whoo' hoop, whoo' hoop he's fairly run down,</l>
     <l n="48">Whoo' hoop, whoo' hoop he's fairly run down.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>