<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>THE INVITATION. TO TWO SISTERS.</title>
    <author>Susanna Blamire</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">1</measure>
    <measure unit="line">64</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Susanna Blamire_the-invitation-to-two-sisters</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>THE INVITATION. TO TWO SISTERS.</title>
     <author>Susanna Blamire</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>THE INVITATION. TO TWO SISTERS.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="quatrain">
     <l n="1" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">THOUGH low is my cot, and the scene all around</l>
     <l n="2" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Unconscious that Art with rude Nature can play,</l>
     <l n="3" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Yet here, even here, it is thought, may be found</l>
     <l n="4" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Some fugitive pleasures that happen to stray.</l>
     <l n="5" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When Aurora walks forth, and collects her perfume,</l>
     <l n="6" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And scatters her sweets on each innocent flower,</l>
     <l n="7" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Her eye can look down just as fond to illume</l>
     <l n="8" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The low gliding stream as the high gilded tower:</l>
     <l n="9" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">All nature beholding, she smiles as she sees</l>
     <l n="10" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The gay tinkling rill, as it plays through the mead; —</l>
     <l n="11" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As she looks at the lustre that darts through the trees,</l>
     <l n="12" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And rears into notice the low trodden weed.</l>
     <l n="13" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">If such things to observe, while beneath the dark oak,</l>
     <l n="14" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Can delight Nature's child, bid her daughters come here;</l>
     <l n="15" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Bid them haste while the Dryads the songsters invoke,</l>
     <l n="16" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And wave their green arms round her children so dear.</l>
     <l n="17" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For as yet the rude catch from the briar may be borne,</l>
     <l n="18" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Since the rose that it bears can still blush for th' offence,</l>
     <l n="19" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Since we yet can remember the harsh wounding thorn</l>
     <l n="20" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Yielded sweets that stray'd softly around every sense.</l>
     <l n="21" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But soon yellow Autumn the green leaves shall stain,</l>
     <l n="22" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And gold gilding-tincture the meadows pervade;</l>
     <l n="23" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Though now whetting scythes the gay season proclaim,</l>
     <l n="24" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And weary scorch'd haymakers long for the shade.</l>
     <l n="25" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Yet Nature, still changing, that season shall bring,</l>
     <l n="26" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When the meads become wither'd and chill turn the groves,</l>
     <l n="27" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When the gadding gay woodbine no longer shall cling</l>
     <l n="28" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">To hang up her garland on boughs that she loves.</l>
     <l n="29" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">With YOU, I must own, should the glow of the plain</l>
     <l n="30" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Be chill'd by a breath, and the sun haste away;</l>
     <l n="31" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Though fond of the scene, I no more would complain,</l>
     <l n="32" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For FRIENDS yield a prospect more charming than May.</l>
     <l n="33" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And without them, how oft have I sigh'd as I view'd</l>
     <l n="34" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The wood-hanging bank, and the cottage so still;</l>
     <l n="35" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Thy regrets, silly heart, were too fondly renew'd</l>
     <l n="36" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As I listen'd and heard the soft clack of the mill.</l>
     <l n="37" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">What joy, would I say, can these beauties bestow,</l>
     <l n="38" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Unless some dear friends had the pleasure to share;</l>
     <l n="39" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Though Nature shed incense wherever I go,</l>
     <l n="40" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Her gifts and her offerings for them I would spare.</l>
     <l n="41" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For, ah! I have found in the bosom alone</l>
     <l n="42" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Is the mansion of Peace; and, wherever we stray,</l>
     <l n="43" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">If we make not this cell-living Goddess our own,</l>
     <l n="44" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">It matters not what is the scene or the day.</l>
     <l n="45" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For Fancy, that fairy, will darken the glade,</l>
     <l n="46" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And change every object that dances around, —</l>
     <l n="47" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Will heighten or lessen the falling cascade,</l>
     <l n="48" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Till horror or grandeur exists in the sound.</l>
     <l n="49" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Yet still there's a Nymph with as magical powers,</l>
     <l n="50" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Who only exhibits things just as they are;</l>
     <l n="51" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And she, even she, can hand round the dull hours,</l>
     <l n="52" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Nor in search of amusement needs wander afar.</l>
     <l n="53" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">What though she is rural, and best loves the grove,</l>
     <l n="54" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Though scenes of retirement delight her the most,</l>
     <l n="55" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Yet not to one spot does she fasten her love,</l>
     <l n="56" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For easily pleas'd, not one pleasure is lost.</l>
     <l n="57" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">She rambles about, and I meet her at eve;</l>
     <l n="58" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">With Aurora I find her ascending the hill;</l>
     <l n="59" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">At noon in the shade help her chaplets to weave,</l>
     <l n="60" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">All day mark her steps, and am near to her still.</l>
     <l n="61" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">To such favour I've got, that my friends she will guide,</l>
     <l n="62" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">With promises firm, that they shall not repent; —</l>
     <l n="63" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">That they shall not be weary when set by my side,</l>
     <l n="64" met="-+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">She promises this — and her name is CONTENT.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>