<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>THE AUTHOR'S ACCOUNT of his JOURNEY to IRELAND. To Mr. JOHN ELLIS.</title>
    <author>Moses Mendez</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">6</measure>
    <measure unit="line">172</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Moses Mendez_the-author-s-account-of-his-jo</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>THE AUTHOR'S ACCOUNT of his JOURNEY to IRELAND. To Mr. JOHN ELLIS.</title>
     <author>Moses Mendez</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>THE AUTHOR'S ACCOUNT of his JOURNEY to IRELAND. To Mr. JOHN ELLIS.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="1" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">BY the lyre of Apollo, the locks of the Muses,</l>
     <l n="2" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And the pure lucid stream Aganippe produces,</l>
     <l n="3" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">My Ellis, I love thee, then pay me in kind,</l>
     <l n="4" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Let the thought of a friend never slip from your mind;</l>
     <l n="5" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">So may fancy and judgment together combine,</l>
     <l n="6" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And the bosom be fill'd with an ardor divine;</l>
     <l n="7" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">That thy brows may the laurel with justice still claim,</l>
     <l n="8" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And the Temple of Liberty mount thee to fame.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="9" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">If it e'er can give pleasure to know my career,</l>
     <l n="10" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When proud London I left with intentions so queer,</l>
     <l n="11" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Accept it in verse. On the very first day</l>
     <l n="12" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When the queen of warm passions precedes the fair May,</l>
     <l n="13" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When, so custom prescribes, and to follow old rules,</l>
     <l n="14" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">One half of mankind makes the other half fools;</l>
     <l n="15" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">From the town I first breath'd in, I sally'd in haste</l>
     <l n="16" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Thro' Highgate and Finchley, and Barnet I pass'd:</l>
     <l n="17" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">At St. Alban's I din'd with a laughing gay crew,</l>
     <l n="18" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Not complete was the set without Tucker and you.</l>
     <l n="19" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Where the Eighth of our Harries deserted his mate,</l>
     <l n="20" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And procur'd a full sentence against his old Kate,</l>
     <l n="21" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Our brisk company supp'd, while our wine gave a spring,</l>
     <l n="22" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And tho' at the Crown, we ne'er thought of the King.</l>
     <l n="23" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The morrow succeeding I got from my bed,</l>
     <l n="24" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As a sheet all the roads were with snows overspread;</l>
     <l n="25" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But the gods, who will never abandon a poet,</l>
     <l n="26" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As oft has been said, condescended to show it,</l>
     <l n="27" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">In a coach and six horses the storm I defy'd;</l>
     <l n="28" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And, left by my friends, thro' the tempest I ride.</l>
     <l n="29" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Newport-Pannel receiv'd me, and gave me a dinner,</l>
     <l n="30" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And a bed at Northampton was press'd by a sinner:</l>
     <l n="31" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">No signs of fair weather, the West Chester coach</l>
     <l n="32" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">At nine the next morning, a welcome approach,</l>
     <l n="33" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Presents fresh example; I travell'd all day,</l>
     <l n="34" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">At Crick eat my dinner, at Coventry lay;</l>
     <l n="35" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">I tremble whene'er I reflect on the roads</l>
     <l n="36" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">That lead to those dirty worm-eaten abodes,</l>
     <l n="37" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Where a woman rode naked their taxes to clear,</l>
     <l n="38" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And a taylor for peeping paid damnably dear;</l>
     <l n="39" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For two parliaments fam'd, which intail a disgrace,</l>
     <l n="40" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And have left their foul manners to poison the place.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="41" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Next morning the fun, with a face of red hue,</l>
     <l n="42" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Had clear'd up th' expanse, and array'd it in blue,</l>
     <l n="43" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When I left the vile town, 'gainst which ever I'll rail,</l>
     <l n="44" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">While Meriden offers no humble regale;</l>
     <l n="45" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But near Mixal Park din'd at house of mean fame,</l>
     <l n="46" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And at night to the field of slain carcasses came;</l>
     <l n="47" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Tho' full old are thy tow'rs, yet receive my just praise,</l>
     <l n="48" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">May thy ale be recorded, and live in my lays:</l>
     <l n="49" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Thy Gothic cathedral new homage still claims,</l>
     <l n="50" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Nor refuse I thy due, tho' repair'd by king James.</l>
     <l n="51" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">I forgot to advise you, the sky being clear,</l>
     <l n="52" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">'Twas at Coventry first I ascended my chair;</l>
     <l n="53" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But, alas, on the morrow, how dismal the sight!</l>
     <l n="54" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For the day had assum'd all the horrors of night,</l>
     <l n="55" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The clouds their gay visage had chang'd to a frown,</l>
     <l n="56" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And in a white mantle cloath'd Litchfield's old town;</l>
     <l n="57" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But at noon all was o'er, when intrepid and bold</l>
     <l n="58" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As a train-band commander, or Falstaff of old,</l>
     <l n="59" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And proudly defying the wind and the snow,</l>
     <l n="60" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When the danger was pass'd, I determin'd to go.</l>
     <l n="61" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">At Stone I repos'd, but at Ousley I din'd,</l>
     <l n="62" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When our reck'ning was cheap and the landlord was kind:</l>
     <l n="63" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Next morning we sally'd, and Staffordshire lost;</l>
     <l n="64" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But not ill entertain'd by a Cestrian host.</l>
     <l n="65" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">On the banks of the Wever, at Namptwich renown'd</l>
     <l n="66" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For an excellent brine pit, our dinner we found;</l>
     <l n="67" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The wine was not bad, tho' the ale did displease,</l>
     <l n="68" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And an unctuous desert was serv'd up of old cheese;</l>
     <l n="69" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But as time will not tarry, our course we resume,</l>
     <l n="70" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And St. George's dragoons take their seats in our room:</l>
     <l n="71" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">So travelling onwards with pleasure we see</l>
     <l n="72" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Old Caerleon so famous o'er looking the Dee;</l>
     <l n="73" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Four days there we rested, and blithsome and gay</l>
     <l n="74" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Forgot the bad weather we met on the way;</l>
     <l n="75" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Then old Chester, farewel, till I see thee again,</l>
     <l n="76" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And can stroll thro' thy streets without dreading the rain;</l>
     <l n="77" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">May thy river still swell, better pleas'd with his charge</l>
     <l n="78" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Than when Edgar was row'd by eight kings in his barge;</l>
     <l n="79" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Be the maidens all virtuous who drink of thy tide,</l>
     <l n="80" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And each virgin in bloom be affianc'd a bride;</l>
     <l n="81" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">May the heart and the hand at the altar be join'd,</l>
     <l n="82" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And no matron complain that a husband's unkind;</l>
     <l n="83" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Let their bounty to strangers refound in each song,</l>
     <l n="84" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Be Barnstone their copy, they cannot go wrong.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="85" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">O'er the cuts of the river our tract we pursue,</l>
     <l n="86" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And old Flint in the prospect now rises to view;</l>
     <l n="87" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">How strange to behold, here our language is fled,</l>
     <l n="88" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">To converse with these people's to talk to the dead;</l>
     <l n="89" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And a Turk or Chinese is as well understood</l>
     <l n="90" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">By these Roisters, who boast of Cadwalladar's blood,</l>
     <l n="91" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As an Englishman here, who is certainly undone</l>
     <l n="92" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">If he thinks to make use of the language of London.</l>
     <l n="93" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">From Flint we depart with our landlord and guide,</l>
     <l n="94" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Who show'd us that kindness which courts never try'd,</l>
     <l n="95" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The castle where Richard his grandeur laid down,</l>
     <l n="96" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And betray'd his own life by surrend'ring the crown:</l>
     <l n="97" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Now the well we survey, where a virgin of old</l>
     <l n="98" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">To all flame but religion's was lifeless and cold,</l>
     <l n="99" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">When in vain princely Cradoc had offer'd his bed,</l>
     <l n="100" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The merciless heathen e'en chopp'd off her head:</l>
     <l n="101" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Hence the stones are distain'd with the colour of blood,</l>
     <l n="102" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And each cripple is cur'd who will bathe in the flood:</l>
     <l n="103" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Thus the rankest absurdity brain can conceive,</l>
     <l n="104" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Superstition imposes, and crowds will believe!</l>
     <l n="105" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Turn from legends and nonsense, to see a gay sight,</l>
     <l n="106" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Where the meadows of Clewyn the senses delight,</l>
     <l n="107" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And excuse that I aim not to point out the place</l>
     <l n="108" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Lest my numbers too lowly the landscape disgrace;</l>
     <l n="109" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">At Rhydland we dine, and a castle we view,</l>
     <l n="110" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Whose founder I'd name if the founder I knew;</l>
     <l n="111" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But our host gives the word, and we hurry away,</l>
     <l n="112" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Lest the length of the journey out-run the short day;</l>
     <l n="113" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Now ascend Penmenrose, oh! beware as you rise,</l>
     <l n="114" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">What a prospect of horror, what dreadful surprize!</l>
     <l n="115" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">See that height more sublime, which no footsteps e'er try'd,</l>
     <l n="116" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">There the ocean roars loudly, how awful his pride!</l>
     <l n="117" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">How narrow the path, observe where you tread,</l>
     <l n="118" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Nor stumble the feet, nor grow dizzy the head;</l>
     <l n="119" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">If you slip, not mankind can avert your sad doom,</l>
     <l n="120" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Dash'd against the rough rocks, and the sea for your tomb!</l>
     <l n="121" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The danger is past, and now Conway's broad beech,</l>
     <l n="122" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Fatigu'd and dismay'd, with great gladness we reach;</l>
     <l n="123" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">In a leaky old boat we were wafted safe o'er,</l>
     <l n="124" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">(Tho' two drunkards our steersmen) to th' opposite shore.</l>
     <l n="125" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Here the town and the river are both of a name,</l>
     <l n="126" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And boast the first Edward, who rais'd her to fame:</l>
     <l n="127" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">There a supper was order'd, which no one could touch,</l>
     <l n="128" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">This too little was boil'd, and that roasted too much;</l>
     <l n="129" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">To his chamber full hungry each pilgrim retreats,</l>
     <l n="130" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And forgets his lost meal 'twixt a pair of Welch sheets.</l>
     <l n="131" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">A castle hard by I with pleasure behold,</l>
     <l n="132" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Which Kings had long dwelt in, or giants of old;</l>
     <l n="133" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">But the daw, and each night-bird, now builds up her nest,</l>
     <l n="134" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And with clamours and shrieks the old mansion infest.</l>
     <l n="135" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">We waken'd at four, and our host left us here,</l>
     <l n="136" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As the worst ways were past, so but small was our fear;</l>
     <l n="137" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">We follow'd our route, and cross'd Penmenmaur'sside,</l>
     <l n="138" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Where the prudent will walk, but the bolder will ride.</l>
     <l n="139" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Still above us old rocks seem to threaten a fall,</l>
     <l n="140" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And present to spectators the form of a wall:</l>
     <l n="141" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Now Bangor we reach, oh, if e'er thou hadst fame,</l>
     <l n="142" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Tho' lawn sleeves thou bestow'st, on my life 'tis a shame;</l>
     <l n="143" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">There we cross o'er an arm of the sea, and carouse</l>
     <l n="144" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">On the opposite shore at an excellent house;</l>
     <l n="145" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Thro' Anglesea's island we rattle our chaise,</l>
     <l n="146" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">While the goats all in wonder seem on us to gaze;</l>
     <l n="147" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For be pleas'd to observe, and with diligence note,</l>
     <l n="148" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">That 'twas here first in Wales that I met with a goat.</l>
     <l n="149" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">O'er roads rough and craggy our journey we sped,</l>
     <l n="150" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Nor baited again 'till we reach'd Holyhead.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="151" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">The next day at noon in the Wyndham we sail,</l>
     <l n="152" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And the packet danc'd brisk with a prosperous gale.</l>
     <l n="153" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">We at ten past the Bar; in the wherry confin'd,</l>
     <l n="154" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Which swims on no water, and sails with no wind,</l>
     <l n="155" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">'Till near two we sate cursing, in vain they may row,</l>
     <l n="156" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Not a snail is so sluggish, nor tortoise so slow,</l>
     <l n="157" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">'Till a boat took us in, and at length set us down</l>
     <l n="158" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">At the quay of St. George in St. Patrick's chief town:</l>
     <l n="159" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Thence I wrote to my friend, nor believe what those say,</l>
     <l n="160" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Or too fond to find fault, or too wantonly gay,</l>
     <l n="161" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Who with taunts contumelious this island o'erload,</l>
     <l n="162" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As with bogs, and with blunders, and nonsense full stow'd;</l>
     <l n="163" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">For, believe me, they live not unbless'd with good air,</l>
     <l n="164" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And their daughters are beauteous, and sons debonair:</l>
     <l n="165" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Here tho' Bacchus too often displays his red face,</l>
     <l n="166" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Yet Minerva he holds in the strictest embrace;</l>
     <l n="167" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Nor the maiden is coy ev'ry charm to resign,</l>
     <l n="168" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">And the ivy and laurel peep forth from the vine.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6" stanza_type="couplet">
     <l n="169" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Thus I've told you in verse the whole progress I took,</l>
     <l n="170" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">As true as if sworn in full court on the book,</l>
     <l n="171" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">Let me know how in London you measure your time,</l>
     <l n="172" met="--+|--+|--+|--+" line_length="12">'Twill be welcome in prose, but twice welcome in rhyme.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>