<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>THELMON AND CARMEL; AN IRREGULAR POEM.</title>
    <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">44</measure>
    <measure unit="line">297</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Ann Batten Cristall_thelmon-and-carmel-an-irregula</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>THELMON AND CARMEL; AN IRREGULAR POEM.</title>
     <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>THELMON AND CARMEL; AN IRREGULAR POEM.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">IN THELMON'S breast contending passions rise,</l>
     <l n="2">While, with resentment stung, he proudly flies;</l>
     <l n="3">The harmonist divine, to madness fir'd,</l>
     <l n="4">Rashly to CARMEL'S youthful charms aspir'd;</l>
     <l n="5">But she, with Virtue's awful power possess'd,</l>
     <l n="6">Taught him to blush, and drove him from her breast.</l>
     <l n="7">First anger in his heated bosom rose,</l>
     <l n="8">With pride he burns, for speedy vengeance glows:</l>
     <l n="9">His instrument, of heaven-inspired sound,</l>
     <l n="10">Touch'd by dire discord wounds the air around;</l>
     <l n="11">Then vengeance dies, and fierce disdain succeeds;</l>
     <l n="12">He flies, while CARMEL'S heart with sorrow bleeds;</l>
     <l n="13">His agonies are chang'd to bitter scorn,</l>
     <l n="14">Nor can the lofty spirit stoop to mourn;</l>
     <l n="15">Disowning every tie that link'd the heart,</l>
     <l n="16">He lost in vice the racking sense of smart;</l>
     <l n="17">He gave a scope to all his mad desires.</l>
     <l n="18">(Perverted genius deepest crimes inspires)</l>
     <l n="19">The wanton chords he struck with loose delight,</l>
     <l n="20">And wit's strong flashes shed luxuriant light;</l>
     <l n="21">Till, satiate with the empty joys of sense,</l>
     <l n="22">And oft disgusted with their impotence,</l>
     <l n="23">Wearied of follies reap'd without controul,</l>
     <l n="24">With self-reproach he smarted to the soul;</l>
     <l n="25">With shame and scorn from noisy pleasures flew,</l>
     <l n="26">And to the calms of solitude withdrew;</l>
     <l n="27">Nature exploring, and with music fir'd,</l>
     <l n="28">Lost in research he wander'd as inspir'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="29">REMOV'D from man, and summer's tuneful groves,</l>
     <l n="30">Alone harmonious THELMON strays to muse;</l>
     <l n="31">O'er rugged hills, through long rough paths he roves,</l>
     <l n="32">To where, impell'd by winds, the ocean roars,</l>
     <l n="33">Heaves its vast surges on the echoing shores,</l>
     <l n="34">Foams 'mid the rocks, and dashes the thick ooze.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="35">Now on the sounding beech, sublime in thought,</l>
     <l n="36">He view'd the wonders of the horrid deep,</l>
     <l n="37">Which from the heavens the ponderous torrents caught,</l>
     <l n="38">While briny mountains brave the darken'd sky,</l>
     <l n="39">Where lowering clouds replete with waters fly,</l>
     <l n="40">And stormy winds the heavens and ocean sweep.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="41">Nor jarring elements untun'd his soul,</l>
     <l n="42">Each natural cause still tracing to its source,</l>
     <l n="43">While driven on winds the waves tremendous roll;</l>
     <l n="44">Curious to meditate on Nature's law,</l>
     <l n="45">The vast Creator in his works he saw,</l>
     <l n="46">And contemplation guides his wandering course.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="47">Humbled by youthful crimes and curb'd desires,</l>
     <l n="48">Abstracted through life's mazy paths he trod,</l>
     <l n="49">The love of science damp'd his former fires;</l>
     <l n="50">And with a heart form'd to converse with man,</l>
     <l n="51">A genius rais'd on Nature's noblest plan,</l>
     <l n="52">He inward drew his powers, and sought his GOD.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="53">Pond'ring on man's vain passions as he stood,</l>
     <l n="54">He heard the transports of the empty wind,</l>
     <l n="55">The vain contentions of the mighty flood,</l>
     <l n="56">Till the tir'd storm scowl'd cross the heaving main;</l>
     <l n="57">The spray no more flies o'er the distant plain,</l>
     <l n="58">And the faint sun through filmy vapours shin'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="59">Calm 'midst advancing shades dissolv'd the day,</l>
     <l n="60">The silenc'd winds scarce shook the showery leaves,</l>
     <l n="61">And through the heavens the watery vapours stray;</l>
     <l n="62">Then o'er the sea (tumultuous now no more)</l>
     <l n="63">Which beat the rocks, and gently dash'd the shore,</l>
     <l n="64">A solemn melody his spirit breathes.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="65">THELMON, whom passions now no more controul,</l>
     <l n="66">To science and to music gave his soul;</l>
     <l n="67">Fair CARMEL'S charms alone his love had fir'd,</l>
     <l n="68">Unmark'd the mind which every grace inspir'd,</l>
     <l n="69">With violence it flam'd, but soon expir'd.</l>
     <l n="70">His heedless wanderings fate or chance decides,</l>
     <l n="71">But now again near CARMEL'S dwelling guides;</l>
     <l n="72">Of which unmindful, still he rov'd the plains,</l>
     <l n="73">And to the setting sun pour'd forth sublime his strains.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="74">The grove is hush'd, the saffron-tinged clouds</l>
     <l n="75">Shoot down their softening colours to the west;</l>
     <l n="76">Advancing night the sable mountains shrouds,</l>
     <l n="77">And with her dewy feet are meads and flowrets press'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="78">Slowly the solemn moon its full orb rears,</l>
     <l n="79">And through the skies its lucid influence throws,</l>
     <l n="80">Each glittering star 'mid fleecy clouds appears,</l>
     <l n="81">And through th' immeasurable path of heaven</l>
     <l n="82">The high galaxy glows.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="83">The moon-beams glide serene across the lake,</l>
     <l n="84">Whose glassy bosom gloomy branches shade;</l>
     <l n="85">The dying gale the murmuring sedges shake,</l>
     <l n="86">While sounds melodious, pouring through the grove,</l>
     <l n="87">The solemn stillness of the night invade.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="88">Cool as the eve, mild as the lucid spheres,</l>
     <l n="89">Fair CARMEL wanders 'mid the nightly dew;</l>
     <l n="90">But wondering stood, as through her well-tun'd ears</l>
     <l n="91">She listening soft harmonious numbers drew.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="92">On the chaste moon she fix'd her crystal eyes,</l>
     <l n="93">Her ear attentive caught the trembling sounds;</l>
     <l n="94">Responsive her lone bosom utter'd sighs,</l>
     <l n="95">While the musician pours his lofty strains,</l>
     <l n="96">They fill the woods, they echo o'er the plains,</l>
     <l n="97">The distant air with heavenly notes resounds.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="98">"In the cool bosom of the solemn night</l>
     <l n="99">" With songs sublime I hail the Power Divine,</l>
     <l n="100">"As from yon orb the quivering beams of light</l>
     <l n="101">" Surround the shades, and through the ether bright</l>
     <l n="102">"Soften the scene, and o'er the trembling waters shine.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="103">"'Mid splendent day oft jarring passions war,</l>
     <l n="104">" But calm at eve I tread the silent grove,</l>
     <l n="105">"And feel delight from every brook and star:</l>
     <l n="106">" Each solemn scene I view with sacred awe,</l>
     <l n="107">"While from a mental glance of Nature's law</l>
     <l n="108">" I learn the wonders of almighty love.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="109">"Rude were the storms which deep through my sad breast</l>
     <l n="110">" Have striv'n the germs of virtue to expel;</l>
     <l n="111">"Rebellious passions robb'd my soul of rest:</l>
     <l n="112">" But in despondency's most baleful hour</l>
     <l n="113">"I felt within a renovating Power</l>
     <l n="114">" Strengthen my soul, and all at last is well.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
     <l n="115">"My mind, no more in boisterous transports drown'd,</l>
     <l n="116">" Reflective feels a bosom form'd for love,</l>
     <l n="117">"Senses which touch the strings of thought profound,</l>
     <l n="118">" And taste each bliss in Nature's calm retreats;</l>
     <l n="119">"While o'er this wilderness of thorny sweets</l>
     <l n="120">" Wandering, with harmony of soul I move. "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18">
     <l n="121">He ceas'd, and 'midst the thickets stray'd along.</l>
     <l n="122">The listening virgin's bosom swell'd with woe,</l>
     <l n="123">'Mid silent tears she heard the solemn song —</l>
     <l n="124">Well did her soul his heavenly accents know.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19">
     <l n="125">Re-kindled passions warm her heaving breast,</l>
     <l n="126">While memory teems with proofs of former love;</l>
     <l n="127">Deep in her heart each accent is impress'd,</l>
     <l n="128">Scarce can she quit the lake, or shadowy waving grove.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="20">
     <l n="129">Her fancy hears amidst the murmuring gale</l>
     <l n="130">Still the faint echoes of his music roll,</l>
     <l n="131">Homeward she bends at last, fatigu'd and pale,</l>
     <l n="132">And vainly strives to calm her trembling soul.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="21">
     <l n="133">THE moon is sunk, and heaven's resplendent stars</l>
     <l n="134">Glimmer 'mid nightly shades and morning grey,</l>
     <l n="135">O'er the low plains a whitish mist appears;</l>
     <l n="136">While slivering every eastern cloud, the dawn,</l>
     <l n="137">Infusing slow the promise of the morn,</l>
     <l n="138">Faint-ting'd the couch where CARMEL thoughtful lay.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="22">
     <l n="139">From her clear eyes large pearly drops descend,</l>
     <l n="140">Unusual fires thrill through her trembling veins:</l>
     <l n="141">As when the potent solar rays extend</l>
     <l n="142">O'er tracts where long congealing ice and snows</l>
     <l n="143">Like mountains rise, near polar circles froze,</l>
     <l n="144">And melting by its heat wild deluge the vast plains.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="23">
     <l n="145">Remembrance pour'd its influence through her soul;</l>
     <l n="146">Her aching bosom heav'd with bitter sighs,</l>
     <l n="147">Her agitated thoughts distracted roll;</l>
     <l n="148">And to her fev'rish fancy THELMON rose —</l>
     <l n="149">Now lofty verse in strains harmonious flows,</l>
     <l n="150">Now passion speaks in his all-potent eyes.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="24">
     <l n="151">Like an imperfect dream the past appears,</l>
     <l n="152">His errors fleet like a dissolving cloud;</l>
     <l n="153">His virtues shine like uneclipsed stars:</l>
     <l n="154">No more the sense of wrongs secures her heart,</l>
     <l n="155">Her bosom burns with unavailing smart,</l>
     <l n="156">And all within the hopeless flame avow'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="25">
     <l n="157">Restless she lay, till o'er the mantling skies</l>
     <l n="158">The dazzling radiance of the morning rose;</l>
     <l n="159">From the broad light she turn'd her weeping eyes,</l>
     <l n="160">And, spent with passion and the weight of thought,</l>
     <l n="161">The transient comfort of soft sleep she sought,</l>
     <l n="162">And listless sunk at length to half repose.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="26">
     <l n="163">Thus a sad prey to misery, CARMEL found</l>
     <l n="164">No kind resource to mitigate the wound;</l>
     <l n="165">Void of pursuits, her heart seeks no relief,</l>
     <l n="166">No active duty rouses her from grief:</l>
     <l n="167">Though calm she seem'd, within the poison wrought;</l>
     <l n="168">And her affections quite absorb'd each thought;</l>
     <l n="169">The light of day her sorrowing mind oppress'd;</l>
     <l n="170">Night was alone congenial to her breast;</l>
     <l n="171">Each eve she strays to soothe her joyless soul,</l>
     <l n="172">And pleas'd beholds the lengthening shadows roll.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="27">
     <l n="173">IN the mild west dissolv'd the blaze of day;</l>
     <l n="174">The rosy heavens rich varying tints o'erspread;</l>
     <l n="175">Bright shone the hills beneath the evening ray;</l>
     <l n="176">Amid the corn wild crimson poppies blow,</l>
     <l n="177">All nature wore a universal glow,</l>
     <l n="178">And joy was echo'd o'er th' illumin'd mead.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="28">
     <l n="179">Untouch'd by every accent of delight,</l>
     <l n="180">Amid the smiling harvest CARMEL stray'd;</l>
     <l n="181">Then climb'd a craggy hill of towering height,</l>
     <l n="182">Where hanging woods luxuriant foliage spread,</l>
     <l n="183">And wild blown flowers their spicy odours shed;</l>
     <l n="184">Thence she the grand extensive scene survey'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="29">
     <l n="185">Night did not yet possess its dark domain,</l>
     <l n="186">But gradual shades o'erspread the burning sky;</l>
     <l n="187">The solemn lake, the flower-enamell'd plain,</l>
     <l n="188">Catch the last rays of the descending orb,</l>
     <l n="189">Whose fiery blaze the distant seas absorb,</l>
     <l n="190">While through the western clouds the crimson glories fly.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="30">
     <l n="191">Nature in glowing plenty smil'd below,</l>
     <l n="192">Above the clouds incessant varying roll;</l>
     <l n="193">As CARMEL view'd the fertile landscape glow,</l>
     <l n="194">Touch'd by the view, the glorious work she prais'd,</l>
     <l n="195">And to the Universal Parent rais'd,</l>
     <l n="196">Fervent in prayer, her energetic soul.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="31">
     <l n="197">The fading landscape lessens on her sight,</l>
     <l n="198">Amid the ether stars celestial shine;</l>
     <l n="199">Some scatter'd clouds still catch the ebbing light,</l>
     <l n="200">And by the glimmering rays distinct she view'd</l>
     <l n="201">THELMON, who lost in contemplation stood,</l>
     <l n="202">As if in converse with the heavenly Nine.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="32">
     <l n="203">She strove to speak, but all her powers were bound:</l>
     <l n="204">O'er her fair breast fast flow'd a silent flood,</l>
     <l n="205">While he with musing pace was wandering round</l>
     <l n="206">The rugged path, and pass'd regardless by;</l>
     <l n="207">He saw her not, but drew unconscious nigh,</l>
     <l n="208">Then mingled in the umbrage of the wood.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="33">
     <l n="209">In vain again to calm her breast she tries,</l>
     <l n="210">Her livid eyes survey'd the ruthess heaven;</l>
     <l n="211">The briny showers she shed, the deep-felt sighs,</l>
     <l n="212">Which mix'd with prayers her wretched bosom heav'd,</l>
     <l n="213">Alike amid a friendless void were breath'd,</l>
     <l n="214">Or by the winds to neighbouring mountains driven.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="34">
     <l n="215">Now when the clouds roll'd heavy o'er the stars,</l>
     <l n="216">And chilling midnight spread a dreary gloom,</l>
     <l n="217">She dried the painful sluices of her tears;</l>
     <l n="218">Devoid of hope she wish'd not for its light,</l>
     <l n="219">And, thoughtless of the dangers of the night,</l>
     <l n="220">Restless return'd in silence to her home.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="35">
     <l n="221">THE shades of night and glimmering dawn are fled,</l>
     <l n="222">The rising sun the parting clouds has fir'd;</l>
     <l n="223">The purple hills illumin'd flame with red,</l>
     <l n="224">While THELMON, fraught with praise, forsakes his bed,</l>
     <l n="225">With love of Nature and her truths inspir'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="36">
     <l n="226">The waving corn, moist with the pearly dew,</l>
     <l n="227">Glitters beneath the sun's refulgent rays;</l>
     <l n="228">Luxuriant o'er each hedge wild roses grew,</l>
     <l n="229">And ripening fruits prolific greet his view —</l>
     <l n="230">All Nature smil'd a thousand various ways.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="37">
     <l n="231">Silent this morn was his melodious tongue,</l>
     <l n="232">And listening to the songsters of the grove,</l>
     <l n="233">He envied their sweet lays, as blythe they sung;</l>
     <l n="234">For with a transient pang his heart was wrung,</l>
     <l n="235">Reflecting on their pure and artless loves.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="38">
     <l n="236">Bitter remembrance deep pervades his soul,</l>
     <l n="237">The glistening lake, the high-grown trees he knew;</l>
     <l n="238">O'er the sweet plains his eyes rekindling roll,</l>
     <l n="239">"Here CARMEL'S virtues did his fires controul,"</l>
     <l n="240">Deeply he blush'd, and quick his eyes withdrew.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="39">
     <l n="241">Touch'd by her wrongs, his soul its guilt confess'd;</l>
     <l n="242">His breast, which heav'd with deep remorse and smart,</l>
     <l n="243">Mourning past crimes, an anxious wish possess'd,</l>
     <l n="244">A wish which no obtruding pride suppress'd,</l>
     <l n="245">To own the errors of his alter'd heart.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="40">
     <l n="246">CARMEL he seeks: the wandering maid he found,</l>
     <l n="247">And with each look inflicts a deeper wound;</l>
     <l n="248">She strove to veil her blushes from his sight,</l>
     <l n="249">And hide her terrors by a sudden flight;</l>
     <l n="250">Yet could not fly, nor scarce resolve to stay,</l>
     <l n="251">Her burning heart contending passions sway.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="41">
     <l n="252">Approaching her, with awe serene he spoke,</l>
     <l n="253">While from his eyes the light of virtue broke;</l>
     <l n="254">With humble dignity his crimes confess'd,</l>
     <l n="255">No rage against himself his words express'd:</l>
     <l n="256">Too well he knew, when swell'd by passion's tide,</l>
     <l n="257">How hard the task the throbbing heart to guide;</l>
     <l n="258">And penitence he felt, devoid of pride.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="42">
     <l n="259">He view'd her with surprize, for while he speaks,</l>
     <l n="260">Delight — not anger, flush'd her modest cheeks;</l>
     <l n="261">Th' emotions of her soul her eyes pourtray,</l>
     <l n="262">Where transient fires in vivid flashes play:</l>
     <l n="263">Rekindling transports as he gaz'd arise,</l>
     <l n="264">Which ting'd his lips, and fir'd his rapt'rous eyes;</l>
     <l n="265">New sympathies within his bosom sprung,</l>
     <l n="266">Which warm in hope impel his glowing tongue:</l>
     <l n="267">Pure and refin'd his passions now appear,</l>
     <l n="268">His virtues strengthen'd, and his heart sincere;</l>
     <l n="269">His voice sublime, his eyes alike inspire,</l>
     <l n="270">Pervade her soul, and fill her breast with fire:</l>
     <l n="271">Dubious no more, she seeks not to retreat,</l>
     <l n="272">Too strongly love did in her bosom beat;</l>
     <l n="273">Fast from her eyes the tears of transport flow,</l>
     <l n="274">Joy takes the language of her former woe;</l>
     <l n="275">Amid the shower a smile seraphic broke —</l>
     <l n="276">She gave her hand, and thus impassion'd spoke:</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="43">
     <l n="277">"I seek not to restrain my throbbing heart,</l>
     <l n="278">" Nor veil its candour with the show of art;</l>
     <l n="279">"Forgiveness beams upon thee from mine eyes,</l>
     <l n="280">" While all thy virtues to my memory rise.</l>
     <l n="281">"Within I feel such powerful sympathy,</l>
     <l n="282">" Such strong attraction of my soul to thee,</l>
     <l n="283">"That no false pride in this important hour</l>
     <l n="284">" Swerves my pure heart with its tyrannic power.</l>
     <l n="285">"With agony I saw excess controul</l>
     <l n="286">" A mind whose grandeur ever aw'd my soul;</l>
     <l n="287">"Thy wonderous songs, replete with genuine fire,</l>
     <l n="288">" The love of nature which those songs inspire,</l>
     <l n="289">"Were in my heart impress'd with power divine;</l>
     <l n="290">" In vain I strove thine image to resign,</l>
     <l n="291">"And mourn'd the fall of such a soul as thine:</l>
     <l n="292">" But now thy penitence o'erjoy'd I view,</l>
     <l n="293">"And yield my heart, as to thy virtue due."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="44">
     <l n="294">He heard, while joy redoubled in his breast,</l>
     <l n="295">And strong emotions every look express'd;</l>
     <l n="296">Sublime his soul its ardent love pourtray'd,</l>
     <l n="297">But most his future life his gratitude display'd.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>