<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>THE ENTHUSIAST.</title>
    <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">19</measure>
    <measure unit="line">183</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Ann Batten Cristall_the-enthusiast</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>THE ENTHUSIAST.</title>
     <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>THE ENTHUSIAST.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">THE pious sire of ARLA rear'd her youth</l>
     <l n="2">Strongly to feel the great Creator's power;</l>
     <l n="3">In her pure bosom sow'd the seeds of truth,</l>
     <l n="4">And open'd Nature's inexhaustless store:</l>
     <l n="5">Early he led her mind</l>
     <l n="6">To pure religion's unadultered stream;</l>
     <l n="7">The young musician caught th' extatic theme,</l>
     <l n="8">And sung GOD'S glories to the sounding wind.</l>
     <l n="9">Call'd by his king to war,</l>
     <l n="10">He left her young,</l>
     <l n="11">To those impressions which his tender care</l>
     <l n="12">Had on her pliant heart imprinted strong.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="13">Her lively senses music's influence found;</l>
     <l n="14">Her fingers struck the sacred organ's keys;</l>
     <l n="15">With pious hopes and heavenly extasies</l>
     <l n="16">Her soul flew upward, wing'd by lofty sound.</l>
     <l n="17">So sweet she sung</l>
     <l n="18">That infidels would hear;</l>
     <l n="19">The hallow'd notes which fir'd her sacred tongue</l>
     <l n="20">Infus'd her faith, and taught them to revere.</l>
     <l n="21">Her soul was meek, her energy was strong,</l>
     <l n="22">And force divine fir'd each seraphic song.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="23">Her simple frame no ornaments adorn'd,</l>
     <l n="24">No earthly radiance blush'd,</l>
     <l n="25">But every look her mental force inform'd;</l>
     <l n="26">The infant soul with beams immortal dawn'd,</l>
     <l n="27">And breaking forth her eyes and bosom flush'd.</l>
     <l n="28">Her temperament was so replete with fires</l>
     <l n="29">She scarcely seem'd to feel the earthly part;</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="30">Her genius with excentric force aspires,</l>
     <l n="31">Its boundless flights with strong conceptions dart:</l>
     <l n="32">But dazzled by its light, and led astray,</l>
     <l n="33">Her inexperienc'd reason fell a prey;</l>
     <l n="34">Th' entrancing Muse seduc'd her early youth,</l>
     <l n="35">More fraught with energy than fed with truth.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="36">Her soul, enrich'd by Nature's noblest stores,</l>
     <l n="37">Gave to wild fancy mad and sovereign sway;</l>
     <l n="38">Imagination drew her finer powers,</l>
     <l n="39">Until the balance of her soul gave way;</l>
     <l n="40">And, its pure tenor thus destroy'd and broke,</l>
     <l n="41">The dormant passions of her nature woke:</l>
     <l n="42">For minds with innate force and quickness fir'd,</l>
     <l n="43">To their own operations left in youth,</l>
     <l n="44">Too oft, by foster'd prejudice inspir'd,</l>
     <l n="45">Are warp'd from the more simple paths of truth.</l>
     <l n="46">Strong inclination points the unknown way,</l>
     <l n="47">And licens'd passions blindly lead astray.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="48">Her strengthening Muse still more enchanting glows;</l>
     <l n="49">Deluded the frail mortal strains her powers,</l>
     <l n="50">While giant weeds in her rich soil arose,</l>
     <l n="51">Vainly the self-supposed saint adores.</l>
     <l n="52">Till lost in feverish dreams,</l>
     <l n="53">'Mid fancy's fires she heavenly visions saw,</l>
     <l n="54">As rapt she sang her wild melodious themes,</l>
     <l n="55">Nature she thought relax'd its rigid law;</l>
     <l n="56">Angels she saw descending from on high,</l>
     <l n="57">Unfolding all the wonders of the sky,</l>
     <l n="58">And caught a glimpse of the DIVINITY.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="59">One noon amid the sea-girt rocks she stray'd,</l>
     <l n="60">Th' expansive ocean and the heavens survey'd;</l>
     <l n="61">Her soul was aw'd, while lost in zeal she stood,</l>
     <l n="62">And the majestic wilds of nature view'd.</l>
     <l n="63">The air condens'd, to sullen mists transforms,</l>
     <l n="64">The sky frown'd awful, big with threatening storms,</l>
     <l n="65">And gathering clouds unite;</l>
     <l n="66">The blackening ocean foams upon the shore,</l>
     <l n="67">While distant thunders 'mid the mountains roar,</l>
     <l n="68">And pelting drops fast o'er the rocks alight.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="69">The angry clouds in troops convolving part,</l>
     <l n="70">The dun horizon gleams with horrid dye;</l>
     <l n="71">From sulph'rous vapours bursting lightenings dart,</l>
     <l n="72">And louder thunders echo through the sky.</l>
     <l n="73">Shelter amid the rocky caves she sought,</l>
     <l n="74">From the large shower and vivid flash retires,</l>
     <l n="75">While solemn peals woke every awful thought,</l>
     <l n="76">And the fierce lightenings fill'd the cave with fires.</l>
     <l n="77">Still rolling on terrific o'er her head,</l>
     <l n="78">The rain in hasty torrents burst the clouds,</l>
     <l n="79">Which spent like smoke cross the blue ether fled,</l>
     <l n="80">Whose brightness following vapours dimly shroud;</l>
     <l n="81">Trembling her face amid the rocks she hides,</l>
     <l n="82">Till the fierce horror of the storm subsides.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="83">Flush'd by her fears, with awe she rear'd her head,</l>
     <l n="84">By all the grandeur of the scene inspir'd;</l>
     <l n="85">As distantly the solemn clouds retir'd,</l>
     <l n="86">She quits the cave, and hail'd them as they fled,</l>
     <l n="87">With wild imagination strongly fir'd:</l>
     <l n="88">While lambent still the lightnings flash'd around,</l>
     <l n="89">And the hoarse thunders roll'd a sullen sound;</l>
     <l n="90">Her lifted eyes the clouded heavens transpierce,</l>
     <l n="91">Divinest strains she sang of heavenly verse.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="92">Thus, with enthusiastic raptures blind,</l>
     <l n="93">A heavenly vision fir'd her feverish mind;</l>
     <l n="94">GOD'S voice she thought amid the tempest roll'd.</l>
     <l n="95">And fancied streams of glory fill'd the skies!</l>
     <l n="96">The fires of heaven the awful clouds unfold,</l>
     <l n="97">Ethereal essence flush'd her mortal eyes!</l>
     <l n="98">More wild she dreams a cherub downward flew,</l>
     <l n="99">And dimm'd the sun as tow'rds the earth he drew.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="100">Her spirit saw him cut the ambient skies,</l>
     <l n="101">While ocean burns with radiance as he flies;</l>
     <l n="102">Such hues empyreal his bright frame adorn,</l>
     <l n="103">He seems a ray of the eternal morn!</l>
     <l n="104">So fraught with living fires, his ardent eyes</l>
     <l n="105">Shot forth long beams, which sparkled thro' the skies;</l>
     <l n="106">From him bright emanations darted round,</l>
     <l n="107">And his wav'd pinions gave celestial sound!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="108">Entranc'd, nor doubting what her fancy saw,</l>
     <l n="109">Her youthful bosom heav'd with sacred awe;</l>
     <l n="110">She view'd him on the strong rock's pointed height,</l>
     <l n="111">Thence breathing strains enchanting mortal ears,</l>
     <l n="112">Such as he tun'd amid th' eternal spheres,</l>
     <l n="113">Genius immortal wing'd its ardent flight!</l>
     <l n="114">The sea responsive mighty surges roll'd,</l>
     <l n="115">Bearing each other on, a voice they found,</l>
     <l n="116">Heaving, inspir'd, they labour'd with the sound,</l>
     <l n="117">And awfully their wondrous nature told.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="118">The winds which roll the clouds along the sky</l>
     <l n="119">In every blast sang forth the Maker's praise;</l>
     <l n="120">The spirit seem'd descended from on high</l>
     <l n="121">To catch the song, and to th' Almighty raise.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="122">Then, like a meteor, fierce he shot along;</l>
     <l n="123">(Refulgence brake, for mortal eyes too strong)</l>
     <l n="124">Amidst the clouds emerg'd his radiant head,</l>
     <l n="125">Wafting the tributes which all nature pays;</l>
     <l n="126">Day seem'd as twilight while the spirit fled,</l>
     <l n="127">The amber clouds receiv'd his parting rays.</l>
     <l n="128">Then round the shore th' Enthusiast throws her eyes;</l>
     <l n="129">(Still foam'd the main, and troubled were the skies)</l>
     <l n="130">Dazzled, thro' clouds the watery sun-beams views,</l>
     <l n="131">While parting vapours wild and various stray;</l>
     <l n="132">Faintly her lucid bow fair IRIS shews;</l>
     <l n="133">ARLA conceiv'd it a remaining ray,</l>
     <l n="134">And wildly stretch'd her arms t'implore its stay.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="135">Not unobserv'd her ecstacies had flown,</l>
     <l n="136">Nor the vibrations of her heavenly tongue;</l>
     <l n="137">For EDRAN 'mid the rocks survey'd her charms,</l>
     <l n="138">And the seraphic phrenzy of her eyes,</l>
     <l n="139">Her hair long-streaming o'er her trembling arms,</l>
     <l n="140">As from her lips the note of rapture flies.</l>
     <l n="141">He saw her with fanatic ardour blind,</l>
     <l n="142">And smil'd, while passion in his bosom wrought,</l>
     <l n="143">And mischief mingling in the villain's thought</l>
     <l n="144">With triumphs o'er religion puff'd his mind.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="145">He in the world's base school had studied long,</l>
     <l n="146">Vain of his parts, devotion to decry,</l>
     <l n="147">And learnt bewitching eloquence of tongue</l>
     <l n="148">To palliate vice with shifting sophistry:</l>
     <l n="149">His ample front deep penetration shows,</l>
     <l n="150">Beneath his powerful brows</l>
     <l n="151">Strong flash'd his eyes,</l>
     <l n="152">And with invention strength of actions vies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
     <l n="153">Potent in ill; he bent his subtile powers</l>
     <l n="154">To draw young ARLA in his wily snare,</l>
     <l n="155">Join'd in her raptures, while sublime she pours</l>
     <l n="156">Entrancing strains of music on his ear.</l>
     <l n="157">Her pious fancies he enrich'd with thought,</l>
     <l n="158">She listen'd to the wisdom of his tongue,</l>
     <l n="159">And from his eyes fresh inspiration caught,</l>
     <l n="160">Whilst he enamour'd on her accents hung.</l>
     <l n="161">Her passions were already set on fire,</l>
     <l n="162">Without a guard her heart defenceless lay;</l>
     <l n="163">Soon to his arts her virtues fell a prey;</l>
     <l n="164">Her sweet affections glide to his desire.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18">
     <l n="165">Ruin'd, he left her plung'd in deep despair;</l>
     <l n="166">The lov'd delusions of her soul were broke,</l>
     <l n="167">'Mid anarchy and horror she awoke,</l>
     <l n="168">Tumultuous passions her sad bosom tear:</l>
     <l n="169">Love warmly lingering in her mem'ry sat,</l>
     <l n="170">Urging her wounded soul to desperate hate;</l>
     <l n="171">The rapt'rous dreams her heart had cherish'd long</l>
     <l n="172">Flew, like the empty echoes of a song.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19">
     <l n="173">Devoid of basis, all support decays,</l>
     <l n="174">Her frantic mind can no where find relief;</l>
     <l n="175">The bubbles burst which shone with glittering rays,</l>
     <l n="176">And nought remain'd save passion, guilt, and grief.</l>
     <l n="177">Rob'd in religion, EDRAN won her heart;</l>
     <l n="178">Her faith is broke while she resents the wrong,</l>
     <l n="179">Wild-panting with love's agonizing smart</l>
     <l n="180">She burns, convuls'd with feelings deep and strong;</l>
     <l n="181">And oft diseas'd</l>
     <l n="182">With mingled passions, fiery ecstasies</l>
     <l n="183">Her trembling lips pour'd potently in song.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>