<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>NOON.</title>
    <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">10</measure>
    <measure unit="line">123</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Ann Batten Cristall_noon</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>NOON.</title>
     <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>NOON.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">THE sun had thrown its noontide ray</l>
     <l n="2">Amid the flowers, and scorch'd the plains,</l>
     <l n="3">Which panted for refreshing rains;</l>
     <l n="4">While gaudy flies their golden wings display,</l>
     <l n="5">And bees cull'd sweets to chear a wintry day:</l>
     <l n="6">Each beam that darted down</l>
     <l n="7">Chas'd lingering shades,</l>
     <l n="8">Through the thick umbrage of the trees pervades,</l>
     <l n="9">And universal splendour shed around:</l>
     <l n="10">The slippery grass, burnt brown with heat,</l>
     <l n="11">Unkindly scorch'd the traveller's feet.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="12">And now, oppress'd,</l>
     <l n="13">While every creature languid hied to rest,</l>
     <l n="14">Amid the blaze LYSANDER bounds along,</l>
     <l n="15">Bold as a lion, scorch'd by many a clime;</l>
     <l n="16">Far off was heard the echoes of his song,</l>
     <l n="17">Responsive to his clear and artless rhyme:</l>
     <l n="18">He seeks no shade, nor grotto's cool retreat,</l>
     <l n="19">But on, amidst the furzy heath, he press'd;</l>
     <l n="20">The heart's warm passions through his pulses beat,</l>
     <l n="21">And native fire inspires his manly breast.</l>
     <l n="22">He seeks the craggy shore which ocean laves,</l>
     <l n="23">And, seated on a rock, surveys the swelling waves:</l>
     <l n="24">The eminence th' horizon's scope commands,</l>
     <l n="25">The plains surrounding, and the burning strands.</l>
     <l n="26">O'er the wild scene he threw a happy look,</l>
     <l n="27">Compares the present pleasure with the past;</l>
     <l n="28">Gladly he turns each page of Nature's book,</l>
     <l n="29">And prays the freedom of his soul may last.</l>
     <l n="30">He roll'd his eyes</l>
     <l n="31">Across the seas;</l>
     <l n="32">Now glancing o'er the glassy waves,</l>
     <l n="33">Now mounting to the skies,</l>
     <l n="34">Th' immortal prize</l>
     <l n="35">Of valiant souls who find deep watery graves.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="36">Thus as he sat, by strong reflection bound,</l>
     <l n="37">Up the rough rock ascends a sound,</l>
     <l n="38">Which piercingly pervades his ears;</l>
     <l n="39">It seem'd the frantic cry of woe,</l>
     <l n="40">Which struggling groan'd, without the aid of tears.</l>
     <l n="41">The sounds like lightening reach'd his heart; and flush'd</l>
     <l n="42">With quick alarm he made no longer stay,</l>
     <l n="43">Ardently down the craggy steep he rush'd,</l>
     <l n="44">Rough heights he leap'd, impatient of delay,</l>
     <l n="45">And tow'rds the sufferer bent his eager way;</l>
     <l n="46">Till by the sea he reach'd some rocky caves,</l>
     <l n="47">Lash'd by the loud-resounding waves.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="48">There a wild female rent her golden hair,</l>
     <l n="49">With raging passions blind;</l>
     <l n="50">Her sad young bosom bare,</l>
     <l n="51">And frantic seem'd her stormy mind.</l>
     <l n="52">Swift tow'rds the sea she flies,</l>
     <l n="53">With direful cries;</l>
     <l n="54">Driven on by fierce despair,</l>
     <l n="55">Mid oozy waves to drown remaining sense of care.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="56">Touch'd by each generous thought,</l>
     <l n="57">By strong humanity impress'd,</l>
     <l n="58">The damsel in his arms he caught,</l>
     <l n="59">And held her, struggling, to his breast.</l>
     <l n="60">"Why trembles thus thy soul, O wretched maid!</l>
     <l n="61">" O agony! too piercing agony!</l>
     <l n="62">"Is through thy miserable frame pourtray'd.</l>
     <l n="63">" O could my breast relieve thy misery!</l>
     <l n="64">"Just heaven! if thou hast pity, ease her pain!</l>
     <l n="65">" Her heart will burst! she faints within my arms! -</l>
     <l n="66">"Upon my bosom she reclines her charms;</l>
     <l n="67">" My falling tears bedew her cheeks in vain! "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="68">He stretch'd her on the shore -</l>
     <l n="69">He fetch'd cool water from the seas,</l>
     <l n="70">And sprinkled her all o'er,</l>
     <l n="71">And fanning her with leaves collects the breeze:</l>
     <l n="72">Till on the heavens she op'd her azure eyes,</l>
     <l n="73">And, with returning thought and grief, look'd up -</l>
     <l n="74">"Ah, wretched me!" she cry'd, with bursting sighs,</l>
     <l n="75">"I've plenteous drank at sorrow's bitter cup!</l>
     <l n="76">" To GOD I fly; no help on earth I find,</l>
     <l n="77">"And from my soul would tear the mortal part;</l>
     <l n="78">" Such sad disorders fill the human mind,</l>
     <l n="79">"Such deep afflictions rive my guilty heart.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="80">"I far in vice have stray'd;</l>
     <l n="81">" And, too severe,</l>
     <l n="82">"The parents who ador'd the maid,</l>
     <l n="83">" No sighs from my repentant heart would hear:</l>
     <l n="84">"Till, raging in despair,</l>
     <l n="85">" I franticly resolv'd to die -</l>
     <l n="86">"Rather than (sad alternative!) to lie</l>
     <l n="87">" Amid the streets, and common insults share. "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="88">Stung to the heart, she rose;</l>
     <l n="89">Tears stream'd from her fair eyes;</l>
     <l n="90">Shame in her cheeks reviv'd the damask rose,</l>
     <l n="91">And poignant sorrow burst in bitter sighs:</l>
     <l n="92">She wept all silently:</l>
     <l n="93">LYSANDER scarce could speak,</l>
     <l n="94">Though sometimes, "Cruelty! O cruelty!"</l>
     <l n="95">Forth from his lips would break.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="96">With generous passions swell'd his noble breast;</l>
     <l n="97">Passions too strong and deep to be express'd;</l>
     <l n="98">Pity and rage with equal strivings beat,</l>
     <l n="99">And sympathy, wrought high by nat'ral heat:</l>
     <l n="100">"By my true soul!" at length he cried,</l>
     <l n="101">"As Nature's my director and my guide,</l>
     <l n="102">" My heart, chain'd by thy woe,</l>
     <l n="103">"Shall neither joy nor comfort know,</l>
     <l n="104">" Till I've reveng'd thy wrongs, and giv'n thee ease,</l>
     <l n="105">"And, by my love, have set thy troubled soul at peace.</l>
     <l n="106">" O! let not misery o'erwhelm thy heart,</l>
     <l n="107">"Nor the fair path of life and joy decline;</l>
     <l n="108">" Vengeance shall find the authors of thy smart -</l>
     <l n="109">"O! fearless rest thy drooping soul on mine,</l>
     <l n="110">" Which, like the oak, round which the ivy strays,</l>
     <l n="111">"With blessings yet may store thy future days."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="112">The damsel's sorrow, like a furious storm,</l>
     <l n="113">Rack'd her celestial system with its rage;</l>
     <l n="114">Her desperate passions deadly warfare wage,</l>
     <l n="115">And the mild radiance of her charms deform.</l>
     <l n="116">At length the vivid fires rush'd to her heart,</l>
     <l n="117">Tingled in ev'ry vein, blaz'd from her eyes,</l>
     <l n="118">While sudden joys before her spirits rise,</l>
     <l n="119">And o'er her cheeks warm transient colours dart:</l>
     <l n="120">Fir'd by his zeal,</l>
     <l n="121">Extatic feelings tinge her frame;</l>
     <l n="122">Whose glow the passions of her breast reveal</l>
     <l n="123">Bright blossom of a future ripening flame!</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>