<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>EVENING.</title>
    <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">17</measure>
    <measure unit="line">163</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Ann Batten Cristall_evening</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>EVENING.</title>
     <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>EVENING.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1">
     <l n="1">IN clouds drew on the evening's close,</l>
     <l n="2">Which cross the west in ranges stood,</l>
     <l n="3">As pensive GERTRUDE sought the wood,</l>
     <l n="4">And there the darkest thicket chose;</l>
     <l n="5">While from her eyes amid the wild briar flows</l>
     <l n="6">A sad and briny flood.</l>
     <l n="7">Dark o'er her head</l>
     <l n="8">Roll'd heavy clouds, while showers,</l>
     <l n="9">Pefum'd by summer's wild and spicy flowers,</l>
     <l n="10">Their ample torrents shed.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
     <l n="11">Why does she mourn?</l>
     <l n="12">Why droop, like flowret nipp'd in early spring?</l>
     <l n="13">Alas! her tenderness meets no return!</l>
     <l n="14">Love hovers round her with his airy wing,</l>
     <l n="15">And warms her youthful heart with vain delight:</l>
     <l n="16">While URBAN's graceful form enchants her sight,</l>
     <l n="17">And from his eyes shoots forth the poisonous sting,</l>
     <l n="18">Another's charms th' impassion'd youth imspir'd,</l>
     <l n="19">The sportive ROSAMONDE his genius fir'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
     <l n="20">The drops which glide down GERTRUDE'S cheeks,</l>
     <l n="21">Mid bitter agonies did flow;</l>
     <l n="22">And though awhile her pallid lips might glow,</l>
     <l n="23">'Twas as a blossom blighted soon with woe:</l>
     <l n="24">Her disregarded tresses, wet with tears,</l>
     <l n="25">Hung o'er her panting bosom straight and sleek;</l>
     <l n="26">Her faithful heart was all despondency and fears.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="27">The skies disgorg'd, their last large drops refrain,</l>
     <l n="28">The cloudy hemisphere's no more perturb'd;</l>
     <l n="29">The leafy boughs, that had receiv'd the rain,</l>
     <l n="30">With gusts of wind disturb'd,</l>
     <l n="31">Shake wild their scattering drops o'er glade and plain;</l>
     <l n="32">They fall on GERTRUDE'S breast, and her white garments stain.</l>
     <l n="33">Sighing, she threw her mantle o'er her head,</l>
     <l n="34">And through the brakes towards her mansion sped;</l>
     <l n="35">Unheedingly her vestments drew along,</l>
     <l n="36">Sweeping the tears that to the branches hung:</l>
     <l n="37">And as she pass'd</l>
     <l n="38">O'er the soak'd road, from off the shining grass,</l>
     <l n="39">In clods around her feet the moist earth clung.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="40">The clouds dispers'd, again to sight</l>
     <l n="41">The evening sun glow'd lambent bright;</l>
     <l n="42">And forcing back the lowering shades,</l>
     <l n="43">Spread its enlivening beams, and kindled mid the glades:</l>
     <l n="44">With high-wrought verdure every object glow'd,</l>
     <l n="45">And purple hills their glittering mansions show'd.</l>
     <l n="46">The universal gleam invites to sport,</l>
     <l n="47">For toil and care cease with the ebbing day;</l>
     <l n="48">Th' industrious youths to plains or groves resort,</l>
     <l n="49">Dance on the lawn, or o'er the hillocks stray.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="50">GERTRUDE, wandering up a lane,</l>
     <l n="51">From among the winding trees,</l>
     <l n="52">Fann'd by a refreshing breeze,</l>
     <l n="53">Ascends upon the glistening plain.</l>
     <l n="54">Across gay Iris flung her bow,</l>
     <l n="55">Reflecting each celestial ray;</l>
     <l n="56">As if the flowers that deck'd the May</l>
     <l n="57">Were there exhal'd, and through its watery pores did glow.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="58">From a fair covert, URBAN'S gay resort,</l>
     <l n="59">A whistling pipe in warbling notes respir'd;</l>
     <l n="60">The well-known sound invites each youth to sport,</l>
     <l n="61">And every heart its harmony inspir'd;</l>
     <l n="62">While from each mead,</l>
     <l n="63">So thick with daisies spread,</l>
     <l n="64">The bounding nymphs with fairy lightness sprung,</l>
     <l n="65">And gayly wild their sportive sonnets sung;</l>
     <l n="66">The air was scented by the odorous flowers,</l>
     <l n="67">Bright sprinkled with the dew of fresh-fall'n show'rs.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="68">Of lively grace, and dimpled smiles,</l>
     <l n="69">Slim CYNTHIA, the refin'd,</l>
     <l n="70">Came, with neat PHILLIS, full of tricksome wiles;</l>
     <l n="71">While SILVIUS stroll'd behind,</l>
     <l n="72">Chas'd by the marble-hearted ROSALIND:</l>
     <l n="73">The loud and witty large-mouth'd MADGE,</l>
     <l n="74">With her obsequious servant HODGE.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="75">Blythe from the mill, which briskly turning round</l>
     <l n="76">Made the young zephyrs breathe a rural sound,</l>
     <l n="77">Leap'd CHARLES, gay glowing with industrious heat,</l>
     <l n="78">Active to lead in every rustic feat:</l>
     <l n="79">Back from his brows he shook his wavy locks,</l>
     <l n="80">And turning quick his lively eyes,</l>
     <l n="81">His lovely, modest PEGGY spies,</l>
     <l n="82">Returning with her aged father's flocks.</l>
     <l n="83">Straight with his hand he gave his heart sincere,</l>
     <l n="84">Devoid of order danc'd, and whistled loud and clear.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="85">HEBE, a blooming, sprightly fair,</l>
     <l n="86">With shallow HED, an ill-match'd pair;</l>
     <l n="87">Simple DAPHNE, rosy JOHN,</l>
     <l n="88">And ever-blundering HELESON:</l>
     <l n="89">From a large mansion, gloom'd by shading trees,</l>
     <l n="90">Forth sprung the star-ey'd LUISSE;</l>
     <l n="91">Graceful her tresses flow'd around,</l>
     <l n="92">Like scatter'd clouds, that catch the moon's pale beams;</l>
     <l n="93">Scarcely she seem'd to touch the verdant ground,</l>
     <l n="94">But, as inspired, along the plain she streams.</l>
     <l n="95">More join the flock; - they spring in air,</l>
     <l n="96">Light as wing'd doves, and like to doves they pair;</l>
     <l n="97">The sun's last ray now linger'd o'er their head,</l>
     <l n="98">And sweets delectable around were spread.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="99">Poor GERTRUDE, hid amongst the trees, survey'd</l>
     <l n="100">Each ardent youth, each blooming maid;</l>
     <l n="101">And as she gaz'd,</l>
     <l n="102">Pleasure by slow degrees within her senses steals:</l>
     <l n="103">Her eyes, with tears impearl'd, she rais'd,</l>
     <l n="104">Her heart each sweet sensation feels;</l>
     <l n="105">Lightly her feet the grassy meadows tread,</l>
     <l n="106">While music's power deludes her from her cares;</l>
     <l n="107">Among the nymphs, by its soft influence led,</l>
     <l n="108">Her sympathetic breast their raptures shares.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="109">Thus while she felt, and join'd the lively throng,</l>
     <l n="110">Lo! quick ascends the plain</l>
     <l n="111">The glory of each swain,</l>
     <l n="112">URBAN, with sportive song,</l>
     <l n="113">Whose chearful notes in frolic measures fled;</l>
     <l n="114">While ROSAMONDE,</l>
     <l n="115">Fleet-footed, glowing ROSAMONDE, he led:</l>
     <l n="116">The rapture of the lark her voice sent forth,</l>
     <l n="117">Too well, ah! GERTRUDE knew its worth;</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="118">Dire tremblings soon her spirits seize:</l>
     <l n="119">Could she, vain untaught nymph, aspire to please?</l>
     <l n="120">Her body owns no grace,</l>
     <l n="121">No smiles, no dimples, deck her eyes or face:</l>
     <l n="122">She feels that she has nought to prize;</l>
     <l n="123">Yet, totally devoid of art,</l>
     <l n="124">Expression's charm was her's, with beaming eyes,</l>
     <l n="125">A voice far-reaching, and a feeling heart.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="126">She turn'd around -</l>
     <l n="127">The flying breezes loosen'd to the air</l>
     <l n="128">Her ill-beseeming vests, her scatter'd hair:</l>
     <l n="129">So sad she look'd, so artless was her woe,</l>
     <l n="130">As from a thinking mind had drawn a tear;</l>
     <l n="131">But joy through every vein had stole,</l>
     <l n="132">And mirth shut out the sympathetic glow.</l>
     <l n="133">The heart's gay dance admits of no controul,</l>
     <l n="134">Sweet joys but seldom through our senses steal;</l>
     <l n="135">Tis pity then we should forget to feel.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="136">Gay wicked wit amid the circles spread,</l>
     <l n="137">And wanton round the lively sallies sped;</l>
     <l n="138">Each neat-trimm'd maiden laugh'd with playful glee,</l>
     <l n="139">Whom whispering swains divert with mimickry.</l>
     <l n="140">Fair ROSAMONDE, whose rival bosom burn'd,</l>
     <l n="141">With taunting mirth directs young URBAN'S eyes;</l>
     <l n="142">He, with mischievous archness, smiles return'd,</l>
     <l n="143">Amid whose circles wounding satires rise;</l>
     <l n="144">Their sportive feet still beat the flowery ground,</l>
     <l n="145">While wicked looks, and jests, and jeers went round.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="146">Pierc'd by their insults, stung with bitter smart,</l>
     <l n="147">Sad fell poor GERTRUDE'S tears, high heav'd her heart.</l>
     <l n="148">Distant she flew, and siting on a stone,</l>
     <l n="149">Conceal'd, gave sorrow vent, and wept alone:</l>
     <l n="150">Till 'mid her grief, a virtuous just disdain</l>
     <l n="151">Came to her aid, and made her bosom glow;</l>
     <l n="152">With shame she burns, she blushes at her woe,</l>
     <l n="153">And wonders at her weakness and her pain.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
     <l n="154">"Unhappy maid!" she cry'd, "thou art to blame,</l>
     <l n="155">" Thus to expose thy virtuous breast to shame:</l>
     <l n="156">"Poor heart! thy love is laugh'd at for its truth;</l>
     <l n="157">" Yet 'tis a holy treasure, though disdain'd,</l>
     <l n="158">"And wantonly by thoughtlessness profan'd;</l>
     <l n="159">" Ah! why then waste the blessings of thy youth?</l>
     <l n="160">"No more fair reason's sacred light despise;</l>
     <l n="161">" Thy heart may blessings find</l>
     <l n="162">"That dwell not in the eyes,</l>
     <l n="163">" But in the virtues of the feeling mind. "</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>