<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>THE ENTHUSIAST. SONGS OF ARLA. WRITTEN DURING HER ENTHUSIASM.</title>
    <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="stanza">16</measure>
    <measure unit="line">179</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>UNED University</publisher>
    <idno>Ann Batten Cristall_the-enthusiast-songs-of-arla-w</idno>
    <availability status="free">
     <p>The text is freely available.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>Eighteenth Century Poetry Archive</title>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title>THE ENTHUSIAST. SONGS OF ARLA. WRITTEN DURING HER ENTHUSIASM.</title>
     <author>Ann Batten Cristall</author>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <head>THE ENTHUSIAST. SONGS OF ARLA. WRITTEN DURING HER ENTHUSIASM.</head>
  </front>
  <body>
   <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
    <lg n="1" stanza_type="pentameter">
     <l n="1" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">WILD wing my notes, fierce passions urge the strain;</l>
     <l n="2" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">Strong flame the fires that kindle in my soul;</l>
     <l n="3" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">I strike the wiery harp, nor will refrain;</l>
     <l n="4" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">Mad is despair, and scorns each feeble rein,</l>
     <l n="5" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">Feelings like mine no virtue can control.</l>
     <l n="6" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">Stifled, th' inflated heart with pain respires,</l>
     <l n="7" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">My crimson veins with struggling blood are press'd,</l>
     <l n="8" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">My cheeks are flush'd with passion's transient fires;</l>
     <l n="9" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">My brain with agonies distracted flies,</l>
     <l n="10" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">Till the fierce streams burst from my burning eyes,</l>
     <l n="11" met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+" line_length="10">And drowning torrents cool my panting breast.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="12">With awe my soul the wreck of Nature views,</l>
     <l n="13">The storm amid the echoing mountain hears;</l>
     <l n="14">The sighs of Autumn, mingling with my tears,</l>
     <l n="15">Mourn the sad ravages which time pursues.</l>
     <l n="16">Hear the wild roar of the tempestuous blast,</l>
     <l n="17">Whirling the forest leaves to distant air!</l>
     <l n="18">See blooming flowers in scatter'd fragments cast,</l>
     <l n="19">While torrents pouring thunder on the ear!</l>
     <l n="20">The sun's bright beam in dreary winter lost,</l>
     <l n="21">Not joyless is, as me, on passion's tempests tost.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3" stanza_type="ten-line">
     <l n="22">My youthful charms fade 'neath my burning eyes,</l>
     <l n="23">The soul-entrancing morn of pleasure flies;</l>
     <l n="24">A raging sorrow sweeps without control</l>
     <l n="25">Those germs of genius which alone inspire:</l>
     <l n="26">The sensual passions which consum'd my soul,</l>
     <l n="27">Burn my distemper'd bosom with their fire.</l>
     <l n="28">Long lightnings glance still from my streaming eyes,</l>
     <l n="29">Though vain around the fiery circles roll;</l>
     <l n="30">Virtue and pleasure vanish from my soul;</l>
     <l n="31">The transient shadow of my glory flies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
     <l n="32">Impassion'd strains my trembling lips rehearse,</l>
     <l n="33">Echoing my soul the numbers pierce the skies,</l>
     <l n="34">I seem (delusions thus my mind impair)</l>
     <l n="35">To catch the potent fires of EDRAN'S eyes:</l>
     <l n="36">On loftiest pinions then, more noble verse</l>
     <l n="37">Bursts into sound, and floats upon the air,</l>
     <l n="38">Till memory bursts on my deluded heart,</l>
     <l n="39">Mingling discordant strains of deep despair.</l>
     <l n="40">Distracting thoughts upon my spirit pour,</l>
     <l n="41">No longer in delusive dreams I rest,</l>
     <l n="42">Such passions mingle with each bitter shower!</l>
     <l n="43">A father's image meets my troubled breast;</l>
     <l n="44">Ah! wandering heart! how bitterly distress'd!</l>
     <l n="45">Consuming flames will soon thy strength o'erpower,</l>
     <l n="46">And thou abandon'd die, with guilt oppress'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
     <l n="47">HER father, soon returning, heard her fate,</l>
     <l n="48">Whilst he anticipates his child's embrace,</l>
     <l n="49">And empty hopes his joyful heart elate;</l>
     <l n="50">O'erwhelm'd at once he's blasted with disgrace:</l>
     <l n="51">No deeper pang his bosom can endure;</l>
     <l n="52">The laurels fade on his victorious brow;</l>
     <l n="53">From his uplifted arms, in fraud secure,</l>
     <l n="54">The villain fled, and shunn'd th' impending blow.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
     <l n="55">The parent view'd his lost desponding child,</l>
     <l n="56">But did not chase the sufferer from his breast,</l>
     <l n="57">For Christian charity, benign and mild,</l>
     <l n="58">Was deeply on his noble heart impress'd:</l>
     <l n="59">Patient enquiries taught him the base art</l>
     <l n="60">With which the vile seducer spread his snare,</l>
     <l n="61">The weakness of her lost deluded heart,</l>
     <l n="62">And present struggles of her wild despair;</l>
     <l n="63">To snatch her from th' abyss with haste he ran,</l>
     <l n="64">And warmly thus the tender sire began:</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
     <l n="65">The strong rebellious spirit heard him speak,</l>
     <l n="66">As fix'd on death her desperate passions wrought;</l>
     <l n="67">A sudden paleness smote her crimson cheek,</l>
     <l n="68">And trembling horror chill'd awak'ning thought.</l>
     <l n="69">She roll'd her fiery eyes, but found no rest,</l>
     <l n="70">Her panting heart congeal'd with sudden fears;</l>
     <l n="71">Then, rushing on her father's suffering breast,</l>
     <l n="72">Burst in an agonizing shower of tears.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
     <l n="73">Nor did he strive her anguish to control,</l>
     <l n="74">But let it rage till all its force was spent,</l>
     <l n="75">Then touch'd the filial feelings of her soul,</l>
     <l n="76">Till to his words a willing ear she lent;</l>
     <l n="77">And then the heavenly precepts he diffus'd</l>
     <l n="78">Which breathe forgiveness to the guilty heart,</l>
     <l n="79">The simple tenets she had once abus'd</l>
     <l n="80">Now snatch her from despondency and smart:</l>
     <l n="81">But, ere the tumult of her soul had rest,</l>
     <l n="82">The sun of truth her mental darkness clear'd;</l>
     <l n="83">Burst the thick clouds which had her mind oppress'd,</l>
     <l n="84">While hope divine her woe-fraught bosom chear'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
     <l n="85">To depths of solitude she would have flown</l>
     <l n="86">To purify the passions of her breast,</l>
     <l n="87">To cherish truth sequester'd and alone,</l>
     <l n="88">With meditation's pensive pleasures blest:</l>
     <l n="89">But her wise parent check'd her erring mind,</l>
     <l n="90">Who piety with strong reflection join'd.</l>
     <l n="91">He cried, "What new delusions wouldst thou try?</l>
     <l n="92">" To what romantic wilds would ARLA fly?</l>
     <l n="93">"A mind prone to extremes these wishes fires,</l>
     <l n="94">" 'Tis passion, and not virtue, which inspires.</l>
     <l n="95">"Large powers, with deep experience, scarce are food</l>
     <l n="96">" For the reflective cave of solitude.</l>
     <l n="97">"O'er what would thy sad meditations roll?</l>
     <l n="98">" Still idle dreams would rise and cloud thy soul;</l>
     <l n="99">"Which practical devotion must efface,</l>
     <l n="100">" And the strong exercise of virtue chase:</l>
     <l n="101">"Thy mind already on itself has prey'd,</l>
     <l n="102">" Blinded through inexperience, and betray'd;</l>
     <l n="103">"From Nature's grander traits conceptions caught,</l>
     <l n="104">" Have wak'd thy genius and enrich'd thy thought;</l>
     <l n="105">"But weak at root, though lofty and o'ergrown,</l>
     <l n="106">" Thy mind is by each casual blast o'erthrown;</l>
     <l n="107">"Let strengthen'd virtue, then, each thought inspire,</l>
     <l n="108">" And cherish'd reason check wild fancy's fire. "</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
     <l n="109">He spake; she felt the wisdom of his words,</l>
     <l n="110">Her heart, resign'd, to simple truth accords.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
     <l n="111">FLUSH'D, from my restless pillow I arose,</l>
     <l n="112">To calm my thoughts, sad stranger to repose;</l>
     <l n="113">Wandering through woods, by night's dread shadows gloom'd,</l>
     <l n="114">At every glade I pensive rear'd my eyes,</l>
     <l n="115">And view'd the fleecy clouds fleet o'er the skies,</l>
     <l n="116">Which gathering thick a thousand forms assum'd.</l>
     <l n="117">Sudden, while yet I gaz'd, the heavens grew bright;</l>
     <l n="118">The graceful star of night</l>
     <l n="119">Shot, 'midst the dark assembled host of clouds,</l>
     <l n="120">A pure resplendent light.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
     <l n="121">The parting vapours floating on the air</l>
     <l n="122">Seem'd spirits teeming with immortal fire,</l>
     <l n="123">Bright emanations of th' Eternal Sire</l>
     <l n="124">Unto my soul reveal'd by ardent prayer.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
     <l n="125">Clear, by the moon, a numerous host I view,</l>
     <l n="126">Circling its orb, the unclad spirits wing,</l>
     <l n="127">On music's pinions mystic flights pursue,</l>
     <l n="128">Glide through the air, and heavenly numbers sing;</l>
     <l n="129">While from on high</l>
     <l n="130">Descend long beams of light;</l>
     <l n="131">A thousand visions crowd upon my sight;</l>
     <l n="132">I seem to mount, and, borne along the sky,</l>
     <l n="133">Rapt'rous I sing, in frenzied ecstasy:</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
     <l n="134">"Whither flies my soul, amid the lunar night?</l>
     <l n="135">" Glory rushes on my sight!</l>
     <l n="136">"Seraphic music fills my ear,</l>
     <l n="137">" Visionary forms appear</l>
     <l n="138">"In solemn grandeur dight!</l>
     <l n="139">" Drawn by silver rays</l>
     <l n="140">"Round the all-attracting orb,</l>
     <l n="141">" While Night her sable wings displays,</l>
     <l n="142">"Which every vivid beam absorb.</l>
     <l n="143">" Amid the sacred host I fly,</l>
     <l n="144">"Fraught with solemn harmony.</l>
     <l n="145">" Mingling with the lunar beams,</l>
     <l n="146">"From every eye immortal genius gleams;</l>
     <l n="147">" The soul of sound</l>
     <l n="148">"Pervades the shadowy space around:</l>
     <l n="149">" From each wild harp a nightly spirit springs,</l>
     <l n="150">"And peals of heavenly music sings;</l>
     <l n="151">" Grand clouds of darkness, hurried by the wind,</l>
     <l n="152">"Bearing th' emanations of the mind:</l>
     <l n="153">" The touch most fine,</l>
     <l n="154">"The gleam most magic;</l>
     <l n="155">" The voice most rapt'rously divine,</l>
     <l n="156">"Strains most wild and energetic!</l>
     <l n="157">" All, all combine,</l>
     <l n="158">"They gather, stream;</l>
     <l n="159">" The sounds encrease, they join,</l>
     <l n="160">"While still we fly the circle round,</l>
     <l n="161">" We dart along, wake every sound,</l>
     <l n="162">"And amidst the harmony, and light, and darkness, shine."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
     <l n="163">Now op'd the starry regions on my sight,</l>
     <l n="164">And 'thwart dark space shot radiant streams of light;</l>
     <l n="165">Th' aereal forms in mists dissolving rise,</l>
     <l n="166">Yet still I hear the grand concordant song,</l>
     <l n="167">Echo'd by all the offspring of the skies,</l>
     <l n="168">Who each in their eternal language sung,</l>
     <l n="169">While all around brake forth ethereal rays:</l>
     <l n="170">From high I heard a new and awful sound,</l>
     <l n="171">Swelling with voice divine the song of praise.</l>
     <l n="172">My feeble sense no longer bears the light,</l>
     <l n="173">Oppos'd my eye-lids close,</l>
     <l n="174">The heavenly forms I lose</l>
     <l n="175">Amid th' all-piercing light.</l>
     <l n="176">My ears resound no more, my pulses cease,</l>
     <l n="177">And for a while my soul was hush'd to peace.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
     <l n="178">Till, waking in the fields, with chill'd affright,</l>
     <l n="179">I feel a shivering being wandering in the night.</l>
    </lg>
   </lg>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>